This section is going to focus exclusively on Docker Compose, which is a combination of a command line
tool and a configuration file. Requirements for this section are that you really need to know a lot of the fundamentals
from the last few sections around images and containers.
As we're going through this course, you're probably going to start to hear me get more and more excited
because things just keep getting better.
Right?
As you learn one component, you're thinking, 'man, bind mounts and volumes are really cool. That's going
to save me some time. I can imagine how I'm going to use that. Blah blah blah blah.
Then, I'm going to come with the next thing that's going to be even better than what you just learned.
In this case, it couldn't be more true.
Docker Compose. So, what is it? And why do we care? So few software services are truly standalone.
When you think about your containers, they're a single process solution, and we're rarely going to use just
a single container to solve a problem or provide a service to our customers.
Our containers will often require other containers such as SQL or a key value. And other applications
that we'll need to run in containers, like proxies or web frontends or backend workers, and so on.
What if we had a way to connect all those pieces of our solution together, where we didn't need to
remember all of our docker run options, and then get them into discreet, virtual networks with relationships
between them, and only expose the public ports, and then spin them all up and tear them down with one
command.
Well, that's Docker Compose.
Before we dive in, we need to clear up that there's two parts to
Docker Compose. The first part is the YAML file and it's super simple to understand.
It's written in YAML, and if you've never dealt with YAML, that is a very easy configuration language.
It's almost as easy as an INI file would be.
I actually think it's easier because it shows hierarchy.
We'll dive into that. That file is where you would specify all the containers you need to run, the
networks you need, any volumes you might need, environment variables, images, and all sorts of other configuration
options.
Then the second part of Docker Compose is a CLI tool, which is docker -compose, that we use normally
for just local dev and test, using that YAML file we created to simplify our Docker commands.
Let's talk about that Docker Compose file.
There's actually versions to the things that you can put in the compose file. So when Docker Compose
was created years ago, it was actually called "Fig" and it was just assumed version 1. It didn't actually
even list a version in the file. As it's matured and added new features to what the file can have in
it, such as networks and volumes, they have created the version statement, which is actually the first
line in the file. This file can actually be used with a Docker Compose CLI, which we'll talk about
in a minute.
This is, again, mainly for local development management and just making it easier to get around in
your environments on your local machine.
Now, starting with the beginning of 2017, we have version 1.13 and anything beyond that, these files
can now be used directly with the docker command line in production with swarm. Of course, there's
great help at the command line with the --help.
As we look at some of the examples, know that the Docker Compose file is a default name, but you
can actually use any file name you want, as long as it's proper YAML and that you use the -f to specify
which file you're trying to use.
If I open up my editor and look at the template here, I just wanted to show some of the outline of what this
is supposed to look like.
We have the version value in the beginning.
The newest version in the first quarter of 2017 is 3.1.
But I always make it at least version 2. If you don't add that line there, it's always assumed to be version
1.
But I don't recommend that because you lose a lot of the features.
So I typically start with version 2. Then if I need specific features out of version 3 and 3.1,
I end up typing the version number in there. You'll see the other three main sections are services,
volumes and networks, right?
So, this is hierarchial.
Under services, everything can be two or four spaces, but it does need to be consistent.
If you just look up YAML on the internet, you'll find some sites that guide you with the specifics of
how to format this file.
If you're using a modern editor, it's going to actually speak the YAML language and know how to deal
with these files and their formatting.
Usually, here, you have, at a minimum, services, which is really just containers.
The reason they actually call them services is because each container that you create in here, you could
actually have multiple ones of those containers for redundancy. So they needed to come up with a different
word.
I think services is great because that's basically what you're doing. Right?
Each container, or containers, that are identical, that you're using are usually providing a service to
something.
Underneath the service name, and again you can call it whatever you want.
It doesn't have to be the name of the image or it doesn't have to be anything related at all.
It could be Barney for the service name, but it will be the DNS name, that we'll find out later, is used
inside of your Docker networks.
Similar to when you give the --name to a docker run command.
Here, I've shown that we can optionally specify the image. We can specify the alternate command to
run. If we wanted to overwrite the actual command that was specified in the image when we run it,
we can do that here.
Basically, all the things we do from the docker run command, we can save them here. Because that's
what really this is about, is taking all of the work out of remembering all the different things in
docker run command for those things you're running constantly.
If you have your own development environments, or your own tools, you probably don't want to type those
commands over and over. And shell scripts can only do so much.
Right?
So, this file would actually replace a shell script that would automate your docker run commands.
This is a much better way to do it.
It's easier to read and it's better documented.
You'll notice that spaces in here are allowed.
You can have spaces in comments wherever you want.
If you had multiple services, you just need to make sure they're unique names.
Then, the other parts that we specify are volumes and networks. And again, these are optional as well.
It's basically the same rules as when you're running from the command line.
If you were to ever need to use the docker volume create or the docker network create commands, and
again, you don't always have to.
It just depends on your situation.
You can put them here as well.
Let's look at a real world, simple example.
You remember in the last section, we had a lecture where we used Jekyll really quick to just do a bind
mount example.
So this is what the compose file would look like for that docker run command, and you'll see that I have
specified the image here.
I've named it Jekyll.
I've given it a volume. You'll notice instead of using the pwd, Compose actually understands the dot,
meaning this is the current working directory I'm in.
Just use this directory that I'm running the compose file from. Then the ports or the -p option.
You'll notice some little things about YAML, where when something only has one option, like if there's only
going to be one image for each service, it would usually be a key and value format like this.
If it's going to be a list of items, like volumes and ports where you can have multiple ones, you'll notice
that the compose file usually has a plural. Instead of volume, it's volumes. And instead of port, it's ports.
And then there'll be a list format with a -.
If we jump into another example real quick.
You'll see that in this one,
this is actually a sample WordPress setup where you have the database service down here that's running
a database container.
And then the WordPress web server container up top.
You'll notice a little thing that's different about this one is that we're using the environment
variables, which would be the same as a -e at the command line. But instead of a list format where
we have a -,
this is, again, another key and value statement.
In this format, we don't use the -, we just list the key and the value.
If I needed to add another one, I would just do that here. All of these would be passed into the
container, when it runs, using the compose command line.
Then lastly, we have one more example. This one is a little more complicated. It's actually one I
was working on recently to set up a three-database server cluster behind a Ghost web server.
Ghost is actually a blog system similar to WordPress. You'll see that I have multiple environment
variables for each one of these containers.
So I've got my Ghost container up top. Then I actually have this thing known as a SQL Proxy, which
it sits in front of MySQL servers and acts as a load balancer and failover solution.
Then I have each of my two, MySQL servers. You'll notice another option down here that says,
'depends on,' and depends on is a pretty common one.
It basically helps Compose understand the relationship between these services. It knows that if I
need to start my Ghost one, then I also need to start other ones as well.
You can see up here that my Ghost one actually depends on these. We'll get into the details of how
this works in later lectures.
But for now, this is probably a lot to digest, and all these different commands and whatnot, but trust
that Docker has some really great documentation on their website. If you just look for Docker Compose
file on Google, you'll probably find this with the first couple of hits.
It's going to be under the docs.docker.com website, as usual, and it's going to be documentation
about every single little key and value option you have.
You'll see the depends on I just mentioned. You'll see environment here where it shows different ways
to put in environment variables. What's great about this documentation is it gives you plenty of
examples.
Personally, I'm on this site every day, just like I'm on the docker run command options page or the compose
command options page.
I'm constantly referencing these because there's just frankly so many features nowadays that I can't
remember them all.
So I keep them close in my bookmarks.
Now that we have a general idea of what the compose file format might look like, let's jump over to
the command line and learn about the Docker Compose CLI tool.