We previously talked about the Docker Compose YAML file and in this lecture, we're going to be talking
about the compose command line. Requirements for this lecture are like the rest for this section where
you really need to know images and containers, and how to use them and the concepts around them from
previous sections, so that you can use all of those inside the compose command and the YAML file. The
Docker Compose command line tool is actually separate from the Docker tool.
It's actually a separate binary. If you're on Docker for Windows or Docker for Mac,
it actually comes bundled with that.
If you also use the toolbox on Windows 7, it bundles with that.
But if you're on Linux, you have to download it separately and you can get that at GitHub.com/
docker/compose, but you can also just search for it on Google, and there'll be a link in the references
for this section.
But I should state really quick that it's not designed to be a production-grade tool.
It's super ideal for local development and testing things really quickly that might otherwise be complex
to type in a bunch of commands from the command line. Two common commands that we use will be docker compose
up, which is by far probably what you're going to be typing 90% of the time.
It's a one stop shop.
It's basically a single command to do everything in the compose file, including creating volumes, creating
networks, starting all the containers with all their configuration options. Then to clean up when you're
done,
the docker compose down, which a lot of people actually forget to do, will actually clean up after
you. It'll get rid of the containers, remove the networks and volumes that aren't needed anymore.
It allows you, with these two commands, to quickly jump in and out of different environments for development.
This is where I really get the attention of developers that are used to using vagrant up and other
tools to customize complicated environments locally they need for development.
Once I show them Docker Compose and the compose file and how easy it is to use along with a Dockerfile,
it really starts to click for them that this could be a better way and a more reliable way to set
up their environments.
And it doesn't require the time to set up different VMs
or the complexity of managing a virtual machine environment.
Just to give you a little taste, if you had a project where you had the typical new developer onboarding
process that was all about learning how to get the right tools for their system, and the right virtual
machines downloaded, and the right add-ons, and all the things that normally they would just have to build
a replicated environment for, with Docker Compose,
it's as easy as cloning the environment that has your compose file from some repo somewhere and then
running the docker compose up command.
It can really be that easy.
Let's jump in and play around. I'm in the compose sample 2 directory. The compose sample 1 directory
was simply some visual examples that we showed in the last lecture.
But in this one, we'll be able to actually run this one and get a quick output.
I'm just going to do a docker compose up.
Well, actually before we do that, let me just show you what it is.
This has got two services, or two containers, and the first one is an Nginx server which is configured
as a proxy in this case.
And that's going to be listening on my port 80 on my local machine.
You'll notice there's a volume command there where I've actually done a bind mount to a file in this
directory called an nginx config file, and it's really a very simple little file.
It's not necessarily important that we know how that file works yet. It just shows how, in this case, I'm
actually taking a file on my local environment. Let's say that this directory is a Git repository that
stores these config files for me. It allows me to map that file in to the container and I actually, at
the end, you'll see it say, 'ro,' that means read only, meaning I can't change it in the container.
That's not necessarily required here. I just wanted to show you that that's how you would do that
in this case. That config file is actually telling Nginx,
'instead of being a web server,
I would like you to be a reverse proxy, and sit in front of another server,' which in this case we're calling
our web server, with its service name, and it's running the Apache 2 server, which is the image httpd from
the official image repository on Docker Hub.
You can also see, at the top, I've specified a version here. That's how I would do that.
Inside the image line.
So, what should happen is when I type this docker compose up, it should start up both containers. It
should create a private network for the two of them.
It will automatically bind mount that file.
It'll open up the port, and it will start dumping logs out to my screen.
You'll see how there, it said, 'creating these two containers.'
It's actually creating the network.
You'll notice in my file, I didn't specify a networks area, or a volumes area because they're not actually
required.
They're only necessary if I need to do some custom things in the network, like maybe change the default
IP addresses or change the network driver that's used.
Or in the volumes case, I can create named volumes, or use a different volume driver, and we'll get into
all of that later in advanced sections.
Just so you know, that's how simple these files can be.
You don't normally need all that stuff.
Those features are there if you need them, but usually these very simple, little commands like this will
get you going.
What have I done? This is now my Apache server and my Nginx server.
You'll notice the logs are actually colored here.
That's a neat feature of Compose that you don't necessarily get out-of-the-box with Docker
is that it will log all the containers that it's running on the screen in the foreground.
I can always do the same thing as I do with Docker and run docker compose up -d, which will run
it in the background. But it's nice to see when I'm developing or testing things locally, that I've got
my logs right on the screen.
If I jump over to my browser, and then go to localhost, you'll see that it says, 'It works.'
That's actually the Apache server replying, not the Nginx server.
The traffic is actually going through the Nginx reverse proxy.
It's repeating the traffic over to the Apache server. The Apache server is responding with its default
basic HTML file because we didn't change anything.
Then the Nginx is repeating it back to me.
So, it's your basic web server, web proxy configuration.
You can tell that the traffic hit both of them. They actually work through the proxy because
the proxy is actually a different color
here. The logs are pumping out here with a random color for each container in my setup so that I can
easily see what's going on.
If I hit refresh several times, you'd see the traffic showing up. Then it's hitting first the proxy and
then the backend web server.
If I wanted to stop this here, I'd hit Control c to stop the compose in my screen.
I could actually run it again with the -d to run it in the background.
You can see here that I can refresh it and it's still there. I can do a docker compose logs to see
the same output of logs that I saw a while ago.
A lot of the commands that you might be used to in Docker are also in Docker Compose. Really what
Compose is just doing is it's talking to the Docker API in the background
on behalf of the Docker CLI. It's kind of like a replacement for the Docker CLI still talking
to the Docker server API in the backend.
Of course, the great help here, docker compose help, shows me all the commands I can run.
You'll see a lot of these look really familiar because they're the equivalent of the docker command
just using the context of the configuration of the compose file.
I want to clean all this up because they're still running. I can do a docker compose ps here, which
will show me that both of my containers are running.
I can do a docker compose top to actually list all of the services running inside of them in a nice
formatted output.
That's pretty cool.
Then finally, I can do a docker compose down to stop and clean up my stuff that I just started.
You'll see that it's telling me what it's done there. Cleaned it all up.
So, great.
This is just a little taste.
We're going to be using Docker Compose a lot throughout the rest of this course for the local development
and testing stuff. Then we'll keep using the Docker Compose files as we transition into the production
concerns for how we deploy complex environments with a simple YAML file.