Requirements for this lecture are that you understand what an image is and that you've done a little
bit of work with containers.
In this lecture, we're going to take a quick tour around Docker Hub and get to know a few of its basic
features. Then we'll kind of discuss the difference between an official image and maybe other just
as good images, and how to tell the difference between a good image and a bad image.
Then I'll show a little bit around downloading images and how you can see the different tags that
they'll use and the difference between an Alpine image and other image options.
...
You should have signed into hub.docker.com. When you sign in your default home page is your
dashboard, which will show you all of your repositories, public and private.
You're not going to have any yet, but you can see I have some here.
They're all public.
I have one private. For now let's go to the top and search nginx. What we'll get back is the
search results of Docker Hub and you'll see that there's a lot. I could scroll for pages and pages.
One of the challenges is there's 15,000 images of Nginx.
That's a lot.
So I pretty much just use one or two.
The official one right here,
you'll see at the top, has 10 million-plus pulls.
There's several characteristics to figuring out what's the right image.
Like me, you're going to start using the images for your workflow that are related to what you do
and you're going to get used to specific ones. You're going to like specific ones.
Typically, we always start with the official.
The official is going to be the only one with the word 'official' actually below it.
It will also be the only one where its name doesn't have a forward slash in it.
When you and I create images on Docker Hub, we have to create them with our account name in front
of them.
So when you look at all these other ones, these are account names slash image repository names.
It might be actually an organization slash nginx or something like that.
But the only ones that get to have just the name of the repo are considered official. Official images
are ones that Docker, Inc. actually has a team of people that help take care of them, ensure that they
have quality documentation, that they're well tested and that they're put together properly with Dockerfiles
that are obeying best practice rules. They usually work with the official team of that software who
actually makes it to ensure that it's doing all the things that it should be doing.
So I'm going to click on this one.
Let's look at a couple of things about Official Repositories.
Like I said before, you're often going to be using officials to start with and then eventually you may
find that you want to change it slightly or add a few things to it and you'll make your own images.
Official images are a great way to start.
One of the best things about official images is their documentation.
They're always really great at documenting how to make them work,
what options there might be, what environment variables, what's the default port and so on.
So back up at the top, you'll notice these versions. Versions are a common feature of official repositories.
You don't have to have versions in every image but official ones do.
Because most open-source software there's always at least a few official versions out in the wild that
are officially maintained and supported.
That's what we have here. We have the mainline 1.11 for Nginx and then
we have what's considered the stable branch of Nginx, which is 1.10. We can see the little name
here says stable jessie Dockerfile.
All right.
So let's break this down.
1.11.9, mainline, 1, 1.11 and latest.
Those are all tags.
When we start talking about images, images aren't necessarily named. Images are tagged. A version
of an image can actually have more than one tag.
We're going to dive into this a little bit later when we start making our own images and we can
play around with tagging.
But for now, if I wanted to actually download that specific image, and you remember earlier that we actually
already downloaded it,
so if I do a docker image ls, you'll see the three images that we've worked with so far on my machine.
You see the tag that says latest. Now latest is a special tag.
It doesn't necessarily guarantee it's always the latest commit in the repository.
What it usually means is you're getting the latest version of this product. In the official
repositories,
it's very well-defined and consistent so that if you didn't really care right now exactly what version
you wanted, you just wanted the most current, then you could just say docker pull nginx. It would
download the latest. You'll notice that it already knew I had it, it checked the SHA to make sure it
matched the one from Docker Hub and said "Hey I've already got this image,
it's up to date." What if I wanted to download docker image version 1.11.9?
It's going to go check and see what it needs to do to download that image
and it turns out it doesn't need to do anything because it's the exact same version.
That's what this line means up here.
I can refer to this 'main, latest' version right here by any of these tags.
The reason is if I just wanted to stay on the latest version of 1.0, whatever that might be for
Nginx, I could just specify a 1. If I wanted to be more specific when I downloaded images and I wanted
the most latest version of 1.11, then I could just type 1.11 like this and just
leave out the .9 and it would download that one.
But in my case, I actually specified the most specific of all the 1.11.9 which shows
the point release and that was just to ensure that I got the exact version I wanted.
So in your software, a best practice is when you're going to production and you're actually testing software
that you're going to be using for others,
you always want to specify the exact version.
It's rare that you really want your software to update automatically.
You usually want to control that process with some other DevOps tool.
But when you're developing or just testing something locally, it's super easy with official images to
just type in the name and just assume you're going to get the latest.
So you'll notice here there's other ones.
There's 1.11.9-alpine and these all have very similar names to the first one
but they all have the word alpine in them.
We're going to get into base images and distributions later, but just for now, Alpine is actually
a distribution of Linux that's very very small.
It's actually less than 5MB in size I believe. This version will actually mean that it comes from
a base image of Alpine, keeping it very small and light, whereas the default one or the latest image actually
comes from jessie, which is a Debian distribution. It's a little larger in size probably a little
bit over 100MB.
In fact, we can actually go over here and we can look.
So nginx 182MB right here.
If I want to download that exact version of the Alpine, I can say 1.11.9-apline
and then do docker image ls and you'll see that the alpine version is actually only 54MB
and the latest version is 182MB.
You'll also notice that the three versions that I've downloaded all have the same image ID because
the image ID is based upon the cryptographic SHA of each image in Docker Hub.
So this isn't actually three different copies of 128MB images.
It's actually a little deceiving.
It's really just three tags of the exact same image ID and it's only total ticking up 182MB
and these are just two other lines showing the same image ID with different tags associated to it.
But enough about tags and versions for now.
Let's check a few more things out
in Docker Hub. If I go back up to nginx in the search bar and search for nginx again, you'll see
again that there's a lot of other options and these can be made by anyone.
You can create your own custom Nginx version and because it's open source software and free to
distribute, you can put it back up here and offer it up to the public.
This is very similar to the model of GitHub where they allow you to store open source software and
you can fork other people's software and also offer it up.
The same thing goes here.
You can use other people's images and download them, make them your own, re-upload them.
So if I ever want to consider not using an official repository, what I usually look for is a number
of stars and a number of polls because a popular repository, to me, tends to establish trust.
I always recommend you download and inspect the software before you use it. Look in their Dockerfile
and hopefully they'll have an open source repository that you can go look at exactly how they
made that image.
A good indication is when you see things that have five million pulls on them and 945 stars; clearly
there's something interesting about this package and why so many people are choosing it rather than
using the official image.
You can come in here and look at their repository.
You can actually see over on the right that he is linked to his GitHub repository where the actual
open source software is that builds this image so that you can go and inspect it; and, possibly download
the actual source code outside of an image.
But, he clearly has done something with this Nginx image that makes it better than the official
default.
A couple more things. On the top bar, you'll see Explore. Explore
just gives you a summary of all the official images and you can peruse through them and, trust
me, there's a lot. In fact, in the resources for this section,
you'll find a link to the actual list of official images and under 'library,'
this is where all the official images and their Dockerfiles live.
You can see there's a lot. As a quick recap, in this lecture we talked about Docker Hub and how it's
similar to being the apt package manager for Containers,
Then how to recognize official images and how to use them.
Then I helped you figure out how to determine a good public image from maybe a not-so-good one.
Then a few tips about base images and how Alpine ones are typically smaller than their Debian counterparts.
So we're going to use these skills in the rest of this section.