Alright, in this lecture we're going to talk about image layers.
So this is a fundamental concept of how Docker works. It uses something called the union file system
to present a series of file system changes as an actual file system.
We're going to dive into the history and inspect commands and see how we can use them to understand
what an image is actually made of. We're going to learn a little bit about the copy on write concept
of how a container runs as an additional layer on top of an image.
What do I mean by image layers?
It's actually transparent completely to you when you're using Docker, but when you start digging into
certain commands, like the history command, the inspect and commit, you start to get a sense that an image
isn't some big blob of data that comes and goes in one huge chunk.
Right?
If you notice when we actually did Docker pulls, certain times you might see words that indicate that
there's something that you already have, like you've cached some part of it already, and that all comes
down to the fact that images are designed using the union file system concept of making layers about
the changes.
If we could quickly just look at what we have in Docker...in Docker images actually...
A while ago, we were playing around with the tags with Nginx. Right? We remember that the Nginx
image ID is the same and we had different tags for the same image name.
So let's do a quick docker history on nginx latest.
What am I looking at here?
This is not a list of things that have actually happened in the container because this is about an image.
This is actually a history of the image layers.
Every image starts from the very beginning with a blank layer known as scratch.
Then every set of changes that happens after that on the file system, in the image, is another layer.
You might have one layer, you might have dozens of layers and some layers maybe no change in terms
of the file size.
You'll notice on here that we actually have a change here that was simply a metadata change about
which command we're actually going to run. We'll cover that in a little bit when we go over the
Dockerfile.
But, for now, you can actually see that this one added a huge amount of files that was 123MB.
Then we made a change here and a change here and I happen to know because of Dockerfiles that these
are really just Dockerfile metadata information.
As you go up, we have some more data changes.
You'll see that this is actually quite different in another image.
So if we go to docker history mysql, it has a completely different set of image layers.
Let me draw this a little bit for you and maybe this will help.
When we start an image, when we were creating a new image,
we're starting with one layer. Every layer gets its own unique SHA that helps the system identify
if that layer is indeed the same as another layer.
Let's just say that at the beginning of one of yours, you might have Ubuntu at the very bottom.
That's the first layer in your image.
Then you create a Dockerfile, which adds some more files and that's another layer on top of that
image. Maybe we use Apt for that.
Then in your Dockerfile, you make an environment variable change. That together is your image.
OK?
You might have a different image that starts from debian:jessie and then on that image you may also
use Apt to install some stuff,
let's say MySQL. You might copy some files over, you might open a port.
So each one of these changes that you usually make in the Dockerfile, but you can also make with the
commit docker command that we'll check out in a minute.
This is also another image and those are all bundled together.
What happens if I have another image that's also using the same version of jessie?
Well, that image can have its own changes
on top of the same layer that I have in my cache. This is where the fundamental concept of the cache
of image layers saves us a whole bunch of time and space. Because we don't need to download layers we
already have, and remember it uses a unique SHA for each layer so it's guaranteed to be the exact
layer it needs. It knows how to match them between Docker Hub and our local cache. As we make changes
to our images, they create more layers.
If we decide that we want to have the same image be the base image for more layers, then it's only
ever storing one copy of each layer.
In this system, really, one of the biggest benefits is that we're never storing the same image data
more than once on our file system.
It also means that when we're uploading and downloading we don't need to upload and download the same
layers that we already have
on the other side. If you were to have your own image and it was custom that you made yourself, and then
you added, let's say, an Apache server on top of that as another layer in your Dockerfile, and then you were
to open up port 80. Then, at the very end, you actually told it to copy in the source code but you
actually ended up having two different Dockerfiles for two different websites, and every line in the Dockerfiles
were the same except for that last little bit where you copied Website A into the image and
then Website B, you would end up with two images. We'll show that in a minute. This makes up one image
and this makes up one image, but the only files that are actually stored is this one,
this one, this layer and then this little layer and then this little layer.
So we're never storing the entire stack of image layers more than once if it's really the same layers.
How does this work with containers?
If you have your image, let's say we have our Apache image, and we decide to run a container off of
it, all Docker does is it creates a new read/write layer for that container
on top of that Apache image. When we're perusing the file system and these things, all the containers
and the images all just look like a regular file system, but underneath the storage driver that's used
by Docker is actually layering, like a stack of pancakes,
all these changes on top of each other.
So if I ran two containers at the same time off of the same Apache image, container 1 and container 2
would only be showing, in terms of the file space, they would only be the differencing between what's
happened on that live container running and what is happening in the base image, which is read-only.
When you're running Containers and you're changing files that were coming through the image, let's
say I started container 3, and I actually went in and changed a file that was in this image in the running
container...
this is known as copy-on-write.
What that does is the file system will take that file out of the image and copy it into this differencing...
up here... and store a copy of that file in the container layer.
So now the container is really only just the running process
and those files that are different than they were in the Apache image.
If we go back to our image list and we look at these commands again, and we look at the bottom one
and see how the dates are different? We can actually see as this image got changed in Docker Hub and was
updated over time, that these changes haven't been changed
at the very bottom layer in four weeks and then the latest changes have been happening in the last
two weeks.
Oh by the way, don't worry about the missing part.
That's actually just a misnomer inside the Docker interface.
It doesn't mean that something's wrong or it's misconfigured. What it means is that really, this mysql
image right here is this image ID.
The other layers in the image aren't actually images themselves.
...
They're just layers inside this image,
and so they wouldn't necessarily get their own image ID there.
Personally, I think it's a little misleading in the interface to say that, but that's how they wrote it.
So now that we've get a sense of the history command to show us what an image might be made of, let's
use the inspect command.
What this does is this gives us all the details about the image.
This is basically the metadata. Remember when we talked about that an image is made up of two parts,
the binaries and its dependencies,
and then the metadata about that image? Well, inspect gives you back the metadata.
Besides just the basic info, like the image ID and its tags, you get all sorts of detail around how
this image expects to be run.
It actually has the option to expose these two ports inside the image so that you know when you want
to start it, which ports you need to open up inside your Docker host if you want it to accept connections.
You can actually see that environment variables were passed in, including the version of Nginx that
it's running and the path. You can actually see the command it will run when you start up the image by
default.
Again, a lot of these things can actually be changed like we did earlier with the docker container
run command.
But these are showing us all the defaults and some other interesting information like the author,
and down here at the bottom, that it's an architecture of AMD64, which is pretty much what all normal
PCs and Macs run on nowadays.
We don't really have too many 32 bit machines around, so this is just a standard 64 bit Intel architecture
and it's designed to run on the Linux OS.
Ok, a quick review.
So we've learned a lot about images and how they're made up, and we find out that they're actually not
that complex. Really, they're just a series of changes on the file system and metadata about those changes.
You learned that each layer has its own unique identity as a SHA.
They're only stored once on each system, so on each Docker daemon, each layer is only represented once
in the file system.
That gives us a lot of savings in space, as well as transfer time in sending images back and forth
between registries, like Docker Hub. And, really, when you start a container,
it's just a single layer of changes on top of an existing image.
So it's actually usually very small. We learned about the history and inspect commands and how they
can teach us what's going on inside an image and how it was made.