Requirements for this lecture include knowing the basics about what a container and an image are in
Docker and understanding the layers,
or at least the basics of layers. Know a few things about Docker Hub.
This lecture is going to be all about image tags and how to upload them to Docker Hub.
There's actually a lot to tags because they're not as intuitive as you might think when you first
start using them. They need to actually be in a specific format in order to work with a registry,
specifically with Docker Hub. Then I'll talk to you about the relationship between the tags that are
assigned to your images and the IDs of those images.
So let's get started.
First let's talk about tagging. docker image tag --help. Images don't technically have a name even
though we kind of refer to them like that when we're talking casually.
If we do a docker image ls,
you notice that there's no name column.
Besides the image ID, which none of us are going to remember those right?
We have to refer to them by three different pieces of information.
On this screen for the image ls command, we actually only see two of them. Over on the left,
we're seeing the repository,
then we're seeing the tag. The repository is actually made up of either the user name or the
organization slash the repository.
Here we're only dealing with official repository images
so we're only going to see the actual repository name.
We mentioned earlier that the special images that are considered official are the only ones that
get the right to just be called their name of the repository, not the actual name of the organization
slash repository.
But if we go over to Docker Hub, and I just do a search on mysql, we'll find that there's actually an
organization, not only just the official mysql, which is just referred to as mysql, but there is
the SQL organization with a mysql-server, which seems to be pretty popular as, well, it's got
over a million downloads. It looks like what it is here is this is actually the same MySQL server
but it's actually created by the MySQL team at Oracle.
If I actually wanted to download it, you'll notice here on the right,
I have to do a docker pull mysql/mysql-server. I can actually click the copy button and
I copy this in. It will actually download this unique organizational-based image and if I do a docker
image ls again, you'll notice that the repository name includes the organization name.
On my account on Docker Hub, I'm known as bretfisher. You can see it from the top right.
So if I were to look at my dashboard and look at my images that I have that are public,
for example, let's look at the nodemongoapp.
If you were to download this, I would need to do
docker pull bretfisher/nodemongoapp.
Now that we understand how the repository is named what does the tag for?
The tag is not quite a version and it's not quite a branch, but it is a lot like Git tags.
So it's kind of a little bit of both.
It's really just a pointer to a specific image commit, and really could be anything, into that repository.
If we went back to Docker Hub for a minute, and we went up to mysql official image, you'll see on the
front page it has these different tags. What they're trying to say here is that the 8.0.0 and the
8.0 and the 8 are all tags for the same image ID.
If I scroll up here and look at the tags button, I get a full detailed list of all the various tags
that they've given to the mysql.
So let's go to Nginx, which is what we've been working on a lot.
We'll see in here that it isn't just numbers but it's actually names as well.
It's important to point out that these are actually all the exact same image and Docker's smart enough
to know that. I go to my command line and I see that I already have the nginx latest downloaded.
If I looked at the web page, I see the latest tag right here but it's also called mainline.
So what if I did a docker pull nginx:mainline? What this is telling us is it actually already
knew that based on the image ID, this image is already in my cache. Now if I do a docker image
ls again, I'll see two different nginx. You'll notice that they have the exact same image ID because
they're not really stored twice in the cache and, again, this goes back to a lot of the savings. These
tags are just labels that point to an actual image ID and we can have many of them all point to the same
one.
So how do I make new labels?
Well I could make my own Dockerfile and create my own custom image, but we can also re-tag existing Docker
images so I can just do a docker image tag nginx
bretfisher/nginx. The format of this command is the image that I'm going to give a new tag
to goes first, and then the new tag that I want to give it.
If I did a docker image tag --help again, just to refresh your memory, it shows the SOURCE_IMAGE and an
optional tag
and then the NEW_IMAGE an optional tag.
So if you don't specify the tag, it'll always default to latest. Latest doesn't actually always mean
latest because I technically could take some old software and tag it latest.
There's nothing special about it but it is just kind of the default. Really,
I wish they would just call it default and not latest.
So it is a little confusing,
but generally on Docker Hub, especially when you're using official images, you can trust that the latest
is generally the latest stable version of the software that you want to use.
So let's do a docker image ls
again. Notice what's happened.
I have added a new tag to an existing image that I didn't make.
It shows the same image ID
and now it's labeled with my user name and a new repo that doesn't exist yet on Docker Hub.
If we went and looked at my dashboard,
I don't have anything called bretfisher/nginx.
So what if I did a docker image push, similar to like a Git push, bretfisher/nginx?
denied: requested access to the resource is denied.
So it clearly tried to upload what I just created, it tried to upload that tag, but it gave me access
denied.
That's because I haven't actually logged in.
So if you look at the docker --help you'll see a login and logout command. We haven't used those yet.
So once you have your own free Docker Hub account, you can actually login from the command line docker login.
...
So what this actually did was there was this wrote to a file, that by default is in my profile under cat .docker/config.json,
and it actually stored an authentication key that would allow my local docker CLI to access
Docker Hub as me.
This is an important point that we'll learn about later on in production is that wherever you login
with the Docker CLI, by default, it's going to store this authentication key for your account in the
profile of that user.
So just be aware of that.
If you're using a machine that you don't trust, when you're done just type docker logout.
So now that we're logged in, I'm going to hit the up arrow to try to push that image again.
OK.
So it seems like it's done.
Let's go over to Docker Hub and hit refresh. There it is,
bretfisher/nginx. Again, I didn't actually have to create this from scratch to upload
it.
I just simply gave a new tag to an existing image and when I uploaded it, it automatically created a
new repo based on that tag.
Of course I could fill out all the information here, and you'll see that it defaulted to the latest
tag name because I didn't specify one. So I could actually go back and do the up arrow thing until I
get to my tag and I could actually give it a different tag.
We're going to add an additional tag to that same image and I'm going to call it testing. If we do a
docker image ls,
you'll see that I now have three all with the same image ID.
If I did a docker image push bretfisher/nginx:testing, and this time I specified testing,
notice how it says layers already exist.
That's part of our awesome savings rate.
When we're downloading and uploading images, that there's already layers that exist, it won't bother
re-uploading them.
If we go back and I hit refresh, you'll see that I now have another tag.
But of course if I just did a docker image ls, we see just like we saw that it's the same image ID and
both sides of this connection know it. If I wanted this to be a private repository, because that is
a supported feature of Docker Hub, what I'd probably want to do is create the repository first, and when
I created it, I specified for it to be private.
Then when I pushed to it, the code would never be publicly on the Internet.
Wow, there's a lot to images and their tags.
So let's just do a quick review.
As you can see, you can pretty much tag anything on to images but they have to be in a specific format
to work with Docker Hub. You can't just call something nginx and then upload it because it's
not going to work unless it has your account ID or organization ID in the front of it.
Then I talked about how you can actually have many tags for the same image ID and just because you
re-tag or tag differently an existing image, it doesn't actually change that image ID.
Remember that the latest tag is really just the default tag.
There's nothing inherently special about it, but we do kind of assume on Docker Hub, it is pretty
much a standard there, that people use the latest tag as a way to indicate the latest stable version
of their image. I showed you how to quickly login and out of Docker Hub from the CLI. Remember
that that stores a session ID in your local config if you're on a Linux machine and you make sure that
you logout to remove that
if you're on a shared Linux machine or a host, like a server. Then, just a reminder, if you want to
create a private Docker Hub image, you should probably create the repository first before you upload
it.