Let's dive into the Dockerfile, which is actually a recipe for creating your image.
So far, all of the Docker images we've been using were created from Dockerfiles where you can go look
at them on Docker Hub.
If you've cloned my repository from the resources listed in the first section you should see a
docker sample file 1 directory, and in there we should have just one file. A Dockerfile.
We're going to go line by line and talk about these different stanzas. A Dockerfile seems to look
like a shell script, but it's not.
It's not a batch file, it's not a shell script. It's a totally different language of file that's unique
to Docker and the default name is Dockerfile with a capital D.
But, from the command line, whenever you need to deal with a Dockerfile using the docker command, you can
actually use the dash f. Which is actually common amongst a lot of the tools with Docker, you can use
dash f to specify a different file than a default.
So, first up is the from command. The from command is in every Dockerfile. It's required to be there.
It's normally a minimal distribution.
In this case it's Debian.
But a lot of times nowadays it's going to be Alpine.
And really, the reason you would use these is to save yourself time and pain. Because these minimal distributions
are actually much smaller than the CDs you would use to install a virtual machine from them.
For example, the Ubuntu one doesn't even have cURL in it, whereas obviously, if you installed
a full Ubuntu installation on a VM it would have cURL and a lot of other commands already installed.
Because all of these distributions are official images, it means that they're going to be always up
to date with the latest security patches and you can depend and trust on them.
And one of the main benefits for using them in containers is to use their package distribution systems
to install whatever software you need in your package.
In this case, we're actually using the Jessie release, which is what's after the colon.
And, as you remember from our Docker Hub conversation, there's lots of different options you can specify
here for the Debian repository.
Next, we have the ENV stanza, and ENV is for environment variables.
It's a way to set environment variables, which are actually very important in containers because they're
the main way we set keys and values for container building and for running containers.
In this case, it's actually setting the version of Nginx it would like us to install and this environment
variable will be set so that any subsequent lines will be able to use it.
Now, as a reminder from previous lectures, each one of these stanzas is an actual layer in our Docker
image.
So the order of them actually matters, because it does work top down.
As you'll see by this relatively long run command here for the next one. Youll see that it looks like
one long command.
What it is doing is really just executing shell commands inside this container as it's building
it.
You'll usually see run commands when you need to install software with a package repository, or you
need to do some unzipping, or some file edits inside the container itself.
Run commands can also run shell scripts that you've copied in earlier in the file or any commands that
you can access from inside the container
at that point in time in the file.
Since we're coming from Debian, this run command has access to all the commands and binaries that
would have been installed with that release.
And in this one for Nginx, this list of commands is more or less adding a key to the repository where
you can get the package to install the latest Nginx from the official Nginx repository.
There's a few things here that are really key in making good Dockerfiles and we'll actually talk
about this more in a later section where we talk about best practices.
But two things to note.
The reason that we're adding all these commands with the double ampersand here, so that they're chained
one after the other, is because, if you remember, each stanza is its own layer.
What this does is ensures that all of these commands are fit into one single layer.
It saves us a little time.
It saves us space. And it's so common that you'll probably see it in every Dockerfile on Docker Hub.
Okay, on line 27 we've got another run command.
This one is all about pointing our log files to the stdout
and to the stderr.
We'll see later, the proper way to do logging inside a container is to not log to a log file. And there's
no syslogd or any other syslog service
inside a container. Docker actually handles all of our logging for us. All we have to do inside the
container is make sure that everything we want to be captured in the logs is spit to stdout and stderr
and docker will handle the rest.
There's actually logging drivers that we can use in the Docker Engine itself to control all the logs
for all the containers on our host.
And so that's really what you want to do with them.
It adds more complexity to your app if your app is actually doing the logging itself.
And then, if you have to deal with files in every container, now you've got a problem of how do you get those
files out, and searchable, and accessible. Here, we're taking the default Nginx logs and we're actually
linking them to the stdout.
So that Docker can capture them.
We also have an expose command.
By default, no TCP or UDP ports are open
inside a container. It doesn't expose anything from the container to a virtual network unless we list
it here.
And, of course, because this is a Web and proxy server it's going to expose 80 and 443.
Now, this expose command does not mean these ports are going to be opened automatically on our host.
That's what the dash P command is whenever we use docker run.
Lastly, we have the CMD here. The CMD is a required parameter that is the final command that will
be run every time you launch a new container from the image, or every time you restart a stopped container.
There is some really excellent documentation on all of these stanzas, plus a whole lot more, that
we're going to go into later, on the Docker documentation website at docs.docker.com,
which you can find in the resources of this lecture.
Okay, so these are the basics, right? These five different stanzas are pretty normal in every single Dockerfile.
Some of them are required.
Some of them, like the run, and the ENV, and the expose, are optional, but they're pretty typical for most
containers that you're going to create images for.