So what do we do with this file?
Well, let's exit out. We're going to see in this directory that we just have this one file.
It's barely a k in size.
It obviously doesn't have anything in it other than the text, but it's the instructions on how to build
our image.
The from command, when I build this image, is going to actually pull that debian jessie image from
Docker Hub down to my local cache. And then it's going to execute line by line
each of those stanzas inside my docker engine and cache
each of those layers.
Lets type docker image build and we're going to tag it.
Remember, that's the name that we're going to give an image.
Since I'm going to only use this image locally I don't have to use my Docker Hub account name. I
can call it whatever I want.
I'm going to call it custom nginx, and I'm going to put a dot here, which basically says, build the
dockerfile in this directory. And you'll see as it that steps through this,
that each step is a line in the dockerfile that it's executing inside this image as it's building it.
And then there's a little hash at the end which is actually the hash
it keeps in the build cache so that next time we build this thing, if that line hasn't changed in the
dockerfile, it's not going to rerun it.
This is one of the magic pieces of why Docker makes deployment and software building so fast is
it actually is intelligent enough to cache the steps in the build.
So quite often, after youve built an image the first time, and you're really just there changing your custom
source code and not necessarily changing the application in itself,
all this installation stuff has already happened.
So you will have very short built times.
Okay, so now we're done building. That took about a minute.
But, what if I go back in that file? I'm going to add an additional exposed port.
For example, I'm just going to do 8080.
Now, that doesn't mean that nginx is smart enough to know that I'm opening this port, or that it's
in any way communicating with nginx.
It's just me allowing the container to receive packets on that port.
Just to be sure, let's do a docker image ls. We'll see right up at the top that it auto tagged
it as latest,
right?
Because we only called it the repository name.
We didn't actually give it a colon tag name when we tagged it.
So let's build it again.
Wow, that was fast, right?
That only took us a couple of seconds. And you'll notice that on each step it'll say using cache. Starting
with Step 2,
it'll say using cache, using cache on 3, using cache on 4. On 5, it recognizes on step 5, that that
line is different.
So it actually executes that into the container. And then, on Step 6, it has to rerun that line because
the minute a line changes, every line after that now has to be rebuilt as well.
This brings up the point about the ordering of your lines in your Dockerfile. Because, if you
get things out of order,
for instance, if you copied the code in...let's say you're building a website. If you're copying the software
code that you're creating at the very beginning of the file, then every time you change a source file
and you rebuild, it's going to have to build the entire Dockerfile again.
So it's critically important for your sanity and time that you usually keep the things at the top of
your Dockerfile that change the least and then the things that change the most at the bottom of your
Dockerfile.