All right. Let's look at some more Dockerfile examples.
In our repository that you've downloaded from my Github, let's go into Dockerfile sample number 2.
This time, we actually have two files.
We have the Dockerfile. And now we have an index.html.
Super simple. Hello world. HTML.
It's not really important to understand the HTML.
We're just going to copy it into our container image as we're building it.
If we look at the Dockerfile, you'll see on this one that we're actually using Nginx as our FROM
command.
We're not building our own Nginx because ideally, if you can use an official image to get the
job done from Docker Hub, then it will be a lot easier for you to maintain this Dockerfile and
keep it working well.
In simpler scenarios, quite often the official image is work. But as you grow and add complexity to
your environment and your systems, you'll probably find that you need to add additional custom software,
or change the way that it starts, or add scripts in so that it tweaks the configuration.
But when I'm starting a new greenfield project, or if I'm converting some old app, I always start with
the official images from Docker Hub. Then once I hit some roadblocks and I'm not able to use that
image anymore, I might go back to Docker Hub and take another look and see if there's anything custom out
there that's really popular, that I can trust, and look into and see if it's going to solve my problem.
But there's nothing wrong with building your own.
It's just more work and more upkeep over time.
So here is super simple. We've got three stanzas.
You've seen the FROM before. And this time we have the WORKDIR.
Now that's really just basically running a cd space directory change. So you might be tempted to
use the run command and just type run cd to this directory and then do some things. But really the best
practice for Dockerfiles is to always use a separate WORKDIR stanza for whenever you're changing directories.
So if your file gets a little complex and you have to move back and forth in your container to do things
while it's building, you always want to use the WORKDIR because it's a lot easier to describe in the
Dockerfile what you're doing.
In this case, what we're actually doing here is we're changing to the default Nginx directory
for its HTML files.
In the default configuration on Docker Hub, Nginx is acting just as a web server, and it's just serving
static files right off the container disk.
The last stanza here, we have, is the copy. And this is the stanza you'll always be using to copy your
source code from your local machine, or your build servers, into your container images.
In this case, we're just taking our simple index.html and we're overwriting the file in the
Nginx default directory so that it's our custom home page for the web server.
Before we build this, you'll notice that we're missing required stanzas, like the cmd.
So how can we get away with that?
Well, there's already a cmd specified in the FROM image.
And when we use the FROM, we inherit everything from the Dockerfile we're 'froming,' if that's even a word.
This is how you can chain Dockerfiles together so that images depend on other images that depend
on other images.
All right. Let's see how this works.
Before we build this, let's just quickly remind ourselves what a default Nginx server does.
Let's do a quick docker container run -p 8080, and we're not going to need this very long so we're
going to do a --rm so it will delete on quitting. We don't care about the name. We're just
going to run Nginx. If we hop over to our browser and just type in localhost, we see the default
Nginx index page.
OK.
Let's remember that, and then let's just quit this container and we're going to now build our version
of Nginx with our extra source code file.
OK.
This one should actually go really quick.
You notice it only took a few seconds. That's because we already had Nginx in our image cache. And
all it was running was copying a very small file and changing the working directory.
Now let's run the exact command we just ran for Nginx. Only this time, we're going to use this
new image we just built.
Switch over to our browser, and refresh, and great.
Our custom index HTML is running in there and our container works.
If we do a quick image ls, we can see our latest image up there at the top.
If we actually wanted to send this up to Docker Hub, it works the same way as we did earlier.
We just need to re-tag it. So we can do docker image tag.
If you remember the help command, we can look at the format and it's always the one we're tagging
and the tag that we want it to then be called. So docker image tag nginx with html latest.
And then I'll have to call it bretfisher...like that.
Then if I do a docker image ls again, you'll see those top two lines are the same image ID again and
just tagged differently.
Now I could do a docker push with that repository and tag, and I could get it up on Docker Hub.