One of the big promises of containers is that we can easily deploy our apps like we were a platform
service, you know, like Heroku or something. We can do that on anyone's hardware, whether it's on our
hardware, it's a cloud provider, whether it's virtual or physical. With Docker, our apps can run
the same whether they're an Amazon, Azure, DigitalOcean, Linode, Rackspace, Google Cloud or whatever. Without
all those platform features, how do we easily deploy and maintain our dozens, or hundreds, or even thousands
of containers across many servers or instances? Or nodes or droplets or whatever.
That brings to bear some really new problems that weren't previously problems for small organizations.
We all know about Netflix and big organizations like that that scale to thousands and thousands
of nodes, and tens of thousands of nodes, and they've got lots of engineers.
But, if you have just a couple of people on your team, or if you're just a solo developer, how do you take
your containers and scale them and deal with their entire life cycle? From deploying them, to starting
them, to restarting them, to recreating them, to deleting them and updating them and all that.
We start to ask questions around how exactly does Docker do that or does it even do that at all?
Some of the questions we ask ourselves are things like, how do we scale out? How do we scale up? How do
we ensure that our containers restart if they fail?
How do we replace those containers when we actually have an update for them? Which is something called
blue green deploy nowadays, which means that you have zero downtime and you take servers out of the pool
in order to bring new ones in. You end up with always something available so that you're never really
down when you update. How do we know if we've got dozens of nodes or even just three nodes where we
started those containers? Which node is our container on? How do we talk across those different nodes
or servers with our networking inside the containers?
When it comes to security, how do we be sure that our containers are only running on the machines
that we intended for them to run on?
Now that we're moving things around and deploying them dynamically on the fly, how do we store the
private information we need for our containers, like secrets or passwords?
So this brings us to a major evolution in the scope of what Docker tries to solve.
When people talk to me and they think that Docker is just a container runtime, that's when I actually
just mention Swarm Mode, which is a brand new feature in 2016 that brings together years of understanding
the needs of containers and how to actually run them live in production.
So at its core, Swarm is actually a server clustering solution that brings together different operating
systems or hosts,
or nodes, or whatever you want to call them, into a single manageable unit that you can then orchestrate the lifecycle
of your containers in. Just to be clear, we're not actually talking about Swarm, which I'm going to
call Swarm Classic, which was an add-on component to Docker before 1.12 came out. It was really a container
that would run inside of Docker,
that really just took your Docker run commands and repeated them out to multiple servers.
It did solve a few problems, but it wasn't really at the scale that we needed to truly solve 80%
of the cases for how you're going to run your containers.
In the summer of 2016,
at dockercon 2016, actually Docker announced Swarm Kit, which was a set of libraries or a tool kit related
around a whole bunch of new Swarm features.
Then they stuck that right in the Docker server. All along in this course, you've actually had the
features available to you in the CLI and on your server.
Now we finally get to dive into them.
In January of 2017, 1.13 came out, and of course because Swarm Mode was new
in 2016, they're going to continue to make it better in the years to come.
In January, they added additional features called Stacks and Secrets, as well as other bonuses
we'll talk about later. It's important to note that Swarm is not actually enabled out of the box.
In fact, on your machine, you couldn't use these commands listed here right now. That would actually give
you an error because Swarm has to be enabled.
That was one of the design goals was that none of the Swarm code would affect the existing Docker
daemon, and that all the tools and systems out there that were already relying on Docker, or maybe they
had their own orchestration on top of Docker, would continue to function and not be interfered with by
Swarm
now being a part of Docker. Some really basic concepts before we start diving in, is that these blue
boxes you see over the top are what we call Manager Nodes, and they actually have a database locally
on them known as the Raft Database.
It stores their configuration and gives them all the information they need to have to be the authority
inside a swarm.
So what we have here is three different managers that have all been added to the swarm, and they
all keep a copy of that database and encrypt their traffic in order to ensure integrity and guarantee
the trust that they're able to manage this swarm securely.
Below in the green, we actually have worker notes. Now you can see in the concept of Swarm, we
have now managers and workers.
Each one of these would be a virtual machine, or a physical host, running some distribution of Linux or
Windows server.
This is showing how they're actually all communicating over what we call the Control Plane, which is
how orders get sent around the swarm, partaking actions. In a little bit more complicated view,
we have this Raft consensus database I mentioned, that is replicated again amongst all the nodes.
They issue orders down to the workers.
The managers themselves can also be workers. Of course, you can demote and promote workers and
managers into the two different roles.
When you think of a manager, typically think of a worker with permissions to control the swarm.
Again, the only requirements for each one of these servers is that they're running the same Docker
that you're already using now. With this concept of a swarm, and these managers, we now have new concepts
of what our containers look like.
So, with the Docker run command, we could only really deploy one container.
It would just create a container.
It was always on whatever machine the Docker CLI was talking to.
That's usually your local machine, or maybe a server they are logged into. That Docker run command didn't
have concepts around how to scale out or scale up.
So we needed new commands to deal with that.
That's where the Docker service command comes from. In a swarm,
it replaces the Docker run command, and allows us to add extra features to our container when we run
it, such as replicas to tell us how many of those it wants to run.
Those are known as tasks.
A single service can have multiple tasks, and each one of those tasks will launch a container.
In this example, we've created a service using docker service create to spin up an Nginx service
using the Nginx image like we've done several times before.
But we've told it that we'd like three replicas.
So it will use the manager nodes to decide where in the swarm to place those. By default, it tries
to spread them out.
Each node would get its own copy of the Nginx container up to the three replicas that we told
it we needed.
This is a quick and basic understanding of how the managers work and what they're doing in the background.
All these features are new.
It's not simply just taking your command and running it on an API like we would experience with a Docker
run command.
There's actually a totally new Swarm API here that has a bunch of background services, such as the scheduler,
and the dispatcher, and the allocator and orchestrator, that help make decisions around what the workers
should be executing at any given moment.
So the workers are constantly reporting in to the managers and asking for new work.
The managers are constantly doling out new work and evaluating what you've told them to do against what
they're actually doing.
Then if there's any reconciliation to happen, they will make those changes, such as maybe you told it
to spin up three more replicate tasks in that service.
So the orchestrator will realize that and then issue orders down to the workers and so on.
With this Swarm Mode, we actually get a feature-packed set of capabilities out of the box that allow
us to already use the existing Docker skills we have in order to deploy our containers to the Internet
in a reliable fashion, and solve a lot of problems that we would have
once we go production.