All right.
Wherever you're running your Docker from, we can actually create a single node swarm for our own testing
purposes.
The way I can tell whether Swarm is on or not, I can just do a docker info and you'll notice Swarm
inactive.
So we know that Swarm hasn't been enabled here. Again, by default, Docker does not enable any of the Swarm
features.
I can run a docker swarm init for initialize. That took about a half a second and we're done.
What we have now is a single node swarm with all the features and functionality that we get out of the
box.
So that was probably the shortest demo of this entire course.
I mean, what just happened? We typed one command and magic. Wasn't actually any magic.
It was a lot of very quick and efficient things in the Go programming of Docker, but essentially, right
out of the box,
it does a bunch of PKI and security stuff. It creates a root certificate for the swarm that it
will use to establish trust and sign certificates for all nodes and all managers. It will create
a special certificate for this first manager node because it's a manager versus a worker.
Then it creates these tokens that we can actually use on other nodes to join this swarm.
Then a bunch of other things in the background where it enables the swarm API and creates something
called the Raft Consensus Database, which we'll talk about later in a production part of the course.
Just so you know, Raft is a protocol that actually ensures consistency across multiple nodes, and it's
ideal for using in the Cloud where we can't guarantee that any one thing will be available for any moment
in time.
It creates that database on disk. It stores the configuration of the swarm,
and that first manager, and it actually encrypts it.
Assuming you're on Version 1.13 or newer. Then it will wait for any other nodes before it starts actually
replicating the database over to them.
Again, all of this traffic that it would be doing once we create other nodes is all going to be encrypted.
One of the key components of Swarm that differentiated it when it first came out was that we didn't
need an additional key value storage system or some database architecture to be the backend configuration
management of our swarm.
If you've been around the industry for years or decades even, there is this concept typically of
the config db, which is this separate database system that you usually need to make redundant that will
store all the information about your orchestration and automation system. Swarm has actually built that
straight into Docker right into the daemon and handles it for us.
We never really need to do anything. There's no passwords to worry about. There's no special services
to start up or anything like that.
So, back to the command line.
You'll notice here that it talks about...if I want to add a worker to the swarm,
I just really need to cut and paste this onto the other servers I would add.
Later, we're actually going to build a multi node swarm, but for now, we're just going to keep this
at a single node. Let's take a look at a couple of the commands will get out of it.
First thing is we can do docker node ls. In this case, we're just seeing the one manager node
that we've created.
You'll notice it's marked as leader, and there can only be one leader at a time amongst all managers.
Again, since we only got one, then obviously it's the leader. We can look at help see what other
options we have here. Really, the nodes commands used for bringing your servers in and out of the
swarm, or promoting them from workers to managers, or demoting them from managers back down to workers.
If you go back the dockers swarm command for a little bit, we'll notice that it actually is a very narrow
scope to command.
It really is just to initialize, either join or leave.
The new unlock command, which we can talk about in a later lecture.
For now, let's focus on the exciting new Docker service command.
Again, service in a swarm replaces the Docker run.
I don't know for a fact, but I really think that this was centered around the idea that we didn't
want to break existing Docker run functionality, but Docker run was always built from the ground up
as a single host solution.
It's whole idea was to focus on local containers on the system that it's talking to. Whereas, when we
start talking about a cluster, we don't care so much about individual nodes.
We don't actually probably name them. We treat them like cattle, if you've ever heard of the pets
versus cattle analogy where they're just a number.
We don't really individually go to each node and start up an individual container.
We really just throw requirements at the swarm in the form of services and then it will orchestrate
how it needs to lay all that out, on which nodes they need to be,
and we just know that it's got our back. docker service create
is how we give it some new orders. Let's do something really simple.
Let's just actually have it start the Alpine image. Then we're going to have the Alpine image just
use ping to hit 8.8.8.8, which is actually a Google DNS server, but we really just want to give it something
to do while we investigate what happens.
Then you'll see like docker run, it spits back an ID, only that's not the container ID. That's actually
the service ID.
You'll see that we now have one service listed. Just like with our docker run command, since we didn't
name it,
it gave it a random name. We can see that it's actually already spun up.
The one of one. When you're looking at services, you're always going to see this number with a /
in the middle. That represents the one on the left is how many are actually running.
And the one on the right is how many you've specified for it to run.
The goal of the orchestrator is to make these numbers match, whatever that takes.
But this again doesn't actually show us the real container.
This is really just showing us a list of our services, so we can drill down a little farther.
We do a docker service ps, and then we give it the name or the ID of the service, and that will
actually show us the tasks or containers for this service. You'll see that it's similar to the docker
container ls command, but it actually has now this node component because when you're dealing with multi servers
scenarios, we might need to know which server it's actually running on. You'll notice that it actually gave
it a name of an increment on the service name.
If we went back to the docker container ls command, that still works.
In this case, the orchestration of Swarm is actually adding some information to the names and to the
actual images that are running. We'll cover some of those subtle differences later as well.
For now, let's actually take that service and let's scale it up. For that, we use the docker service update,
and then the name of our service, or the ID in this case, I'll do the ID. And I want to change an attribute
about the service.
In this case, I want to change the number of replicas.
So if we do a docker service ls again, we now see three of three. If we do a docker service ps,
we actually now see three tasks. You'll notice that two were just created seconds ago.
If we were fast enough, and if we were deploying something big enough, we could actually run the service
ls and actually see it show us zero of three. One of three.
It'll actually increment as things start up. It just so happens that Alpine was already on this machine,
in terms of its image, and it didn't take very long to start up a ping command.
We just couldn't be that fast.
What's interesting about that update command is that you can imagine the difference between the
Docker run command that you might use on a single dev or test server or on your local machine, and the
production concerns of always keeping something available
as much as possible.
That's one of the design goals of Swarm. That command that we actually haven't used yet is the Docker
update command. That was a command for the Docker run containers that allowed us to update certain
variables on our running container without having to kill it and restart it.
Almost all of those options are related to limiting and controlling resource usage for that container.
Because that's one of the typical things that you see when you're running a long term application is
that you need to change its resources maybe because the databases have gotten bigger and need more RAM.
Or maybe you have an out of control process that's eating up too much CPU and you need to limit it.
If we do a help on the docker service update command, you'll see that we have a lot more options.
Because the goal of a Swarm service is that it's able to replace containers and update changes in the
service without taking the entire thing down.
If you had a service with three containers in it, you could technically take down one at a time to
make a change and do sort of a rolling update, which is the blue green pattern we talked about. That's
why we see a lot more options here is because we can change these options that may require a container
restart, but the swarm will intelligently make sure that the way we update them is in a pattern that
ensures consistent availability.
So back to our docker container list real quick. You'll notice that we have these three now, and what if
I went in and, sort of as a rogue, did a docker container rm, and I specified one of these containers, and
I forced it...let's say I beat the first one and just take it out.
All right.
Now I do a docker service ls, and you see how it shows two of three?
Because I went in behind the back of Swarm and I actually took away a running container,
it's going to identify that and it's going to launch a new one within seconds to replace the one that
went down.
So if I did a docker service ps on frosty, you'll see that it actually shows the history of the
first task here in the list is that it had one that failed and it started a new one 24 seconds ago.
This is one of the responsibilities of a container orchestration system is to make sure that the
services you specified are always running,
and if they fail, it recovers from that failure. Which is way different than docker run, right? docker run would
never recreate a container.
So that's why whenever we do any of these Docker service commands, we're not actually speaking directly
to an action like create a container.
We're actually telling an orchestration system, hey put this job in your queue.
When you can get to it, please perform the actions on the swarm that I've asked here. That's a
big difference.
It's subtle in the command line, but it's a big difference because it means that there's rollback possibilities.
There's failure mitigation and a lot of intelligence built into that.
In this case, if I actually wanted to remove all these containers,
I'd have to remove the service. I'd have to do docker service rm.
And then the frosty.
If we do a docker service ls, we see nothing. If we do a docker container
ls, we see three containers.
Oh and there we go.
That shows right there the automation happening on the backend.
We were able to quickly show that we deleted the service, but the orchestration system hadn't gone through
all of its processes of cleaning up the service and the task behind it. These concepts should be pretty
easy to understand because they're just really expanding on the Docker run concepts that we've had earlier
in this course.
Next let's actually build a multi node swarm and start scaling our containers out.