This is going to be the first lecture where we're actually going to use multiple hosts or nodes,
or instances, or whatever you want...multiple OS's. We're going to set up a 3-node swarm across
all three of those nodes.
We unfortunately can't do this part with the built-in Docker on your machine because that's only going to
provide us one OS. We need three Linux OS's to play with this next set of features.
The first option you're going to have is using play-with-docker.com.
It's absolutely the easiest way to get started.
It comes with Docker pre-installed. It takes you seconds to provision three different machines, and it requires
no investment on your end. But it does mean that every four hours it will wipe all the work you've done.
So if you think you're going to do the rest of this section over the course of days, then this may not
be the best option for you. But if you're going to focus for a few hours, you can definitely get through
most, if not all, of the multi node swarm stuff using Play With Docker in one sitting.
Another option you have is you can use docker-machine, which is not something we've talked about yet,
but it's a command line tool that actually gets installed with Docker for Windows and Docker for Mac.
You can download it for Linux, and it is basically an automation tool for provisioning virtual machines
locally, and on the Internet, and then automatically setting up Docker for you.
The default way that it works is with VirtualBox, which you can install free. But it does mean that if
you're going to run three virtual machines locally, each one of them probably needs a gig of RAM or so
to run through a lot of these examples. So you'll need a machine with a good amount of RAM in it. Another
option, and the one that I'm going to default to for a lot of these demos and walk throughs, is DigitalOcean.
I just recommend DigitalOcean just because they have the cheapest and easiest service to
get started, and they run everything on SSD so it's nice and fast. You can actually use this in a
very, very similar set up to what production would be because you're using three actual virtual machines,
in the cloud, and it takes about a minute to launch each virtual machine.
If you're thinking that that might be an option, you can use my referral code and the references to
this section to get your first $10 free.
If you're only going to take a few days to get through this swarm stuff, you can provision three, $10 a
month nodes and have them up for days or a week.
And that might fit within the $10 budget so technically wouldn't cost you anything.
And then lastly, there are so many ways to get Docker installed, and that's really all you need is three
machines with Docker installed on them. You can use Docker Machine.
It has built in drivers that allow you to use it to provision Amazon instances, or Azure instances, or
DigitalOcean Droplets, or Google Compute nodes or any place you can get a Linux virtual machine, you
can actually just install Docker with an automated script from get.docker.com.
Frankly, I prefer the get.docker.com version only because Docker Machine may save you a few steps,
especially for locations like Amazon and Azure that require you to provision a lot of different things
before you can get to just provisioning a virtual machine. But you're probably not going to be using
Docker Machine in production.
It is a tool to simply automate dev and test environments. It was never really designed to set up all
of the production settings you might need for a multi-node swarm.
There's nothing inherently wrong with it, but typically get.docker.com works on all the major
Linux distributions and doesn't take any longer than actually using Docker Machine itself.
I'm going to give you a really quick example of just getting any of these scenarios to the point
where Docker is installed. Then they all will be very similar in the way we actually create the
swarm and do our services.
So don't think that you have to do it the way I do it.
Really we're just trying to get Docker info to actually bring back information, and then just to make
sure that the three nodes have networking access to each other and they're on a well connected network.
So ideally they should be in the same network.
If you were going to use Play With Docker, you actually just go to play-with-docker.com and check
on the box for I'm not a robot.
And if it gives you the CAPTCHA screen, just follow along.
All right. You'll see that it's counting down by four hours.
But if I just click the creating instance, and then I click it two more times, it'll create three virtual
environments very quickly.
As a side note, this is actually using Docker in Docker, which is a pretty neat technology where we're
actually running Docker inside a Docker container.
But in this set up with Play With Docker, which was created by other Docker captains and the Docker team,
it's really hard to tell a difference.
If I go to node1, I can already see that Docker info gives me the latest version. And if I even tried
to ping node2, it actually recognizes friendly names, so it will make it easier to communicate back and
forth between them.
So if this is something you want to try, it's a great and easy way on either low-powered machines
or if you just don't want to take the time to set up an environment for the next four hours.
Option two is to use docker-machine. If you have it installed, it should be at least version 10
if not newer.
You'll know if it's installed because you'll type the docker-machine command from your command line and
it'll either work or it won't.
If you need to download it for your particular Linux OS, then you can hop over to the Docker Documentation,
which will actually give you a quick curl line to download it.
If you're using the ToolBox on Windows 7 and 8, or Docker for Windows on Windows 10, or Docker for
Mac on Mac OS, it's already going to be up to date on those OS's for you.
If you want to use the VirtualBox option, which is the default, you just need to jump over to
virtualbox.org and download the latest version for your OS. And you don't even have to do anything with
VirtualBox.
It just needs to be installed. And then from your command line, you can just type docker-machine create
node1, and this will actually run through creating a virtual machine with BusyBox, which is a very
lightweight Linux distribution.
This will actually run through creating a very lightweight Linux machine, and you'll just repeat those
two commands for node2 and 3.
If you need more information on a Docker Machine, you can actually look at my reference section
for tutorial links.
Once your machines are created, you really have two options for how you can access those machines.
You can either use docker-machine ssh, and then the name of the node you created and that'll hop you right
into that machine.
Or you can use the environment command.
So the command docker-machine env, and then the name of the machine you want, will give you some output,
and you can either cut and paste these options to your command line or you can copy and paste the bottom
option, and that will actually create the environment variable so that when I run my docker command,
because again, the Docker CLI just needs to know what Docker host to talk to. And by default, it's talking
to your local machine.
But that just reprogrammed it to talk to the Docker Machine
node1.
If I do docker info, you'll see that its name is node1 because that's the one I'm actually now operating
on.
For the last example, I'm going to use DigitalOcean, which I have created an account on.
Here, they call servers Droplets. I recommend if you don't have a specific reason to run another
OS, to start with Ubuntu 16.04 because that tends to be the first Linux distribution to support the
newer Docker features.
So that's the default there.
Then I would recommend for the remainder of this course for us to use the $10 a month server. You
might be able to get away with the $5 a month server, but it might get a little bit slow during some of
the later demos when we do monitoring and logging containers on top of our applications.
Then you can pick the data center closest to you. Then the only other option is to add an SSH key.
If you're not familiar with how to create your own SSH key locally and then upload the public into
DigitalOcean,
there's a great tutorial that they have for it that you can find in the resources of this section.
Down at the bottom I'm going to create three machines, and I'm going to call them node1, 2 and 3.
Then I need to wait probably about 60 seconds and they'll be ready for me.
You could just use the IP addresses here...jump on these machines.
Clicking the copy button and then ssh root @ the IP address.
And if your SSH key is properly set up on your machine, then it'll automatically log in with that
key.
But in the resources section, I've given you an example of how to set up a .ssh config file that will
allow you to have these three nodes in a config so you can just simply call them node1, node2,
node3, instead of having to remember their IP addresses, in case you're going to be doing this over multiple
days. That's really an easy way to get in and out of these servers.
If you've used Docker Machine, or if you used Play With Docker, then Docker is already installed
and you're getting ready to create your swarm.
But if you use DigitalOcean, or you roll your own VMs, then you need to get Docker installed.
The easiest way to do that, that I like to use, is to use the script over at get.docker.com.
You can see examples up here of how to use this script to get the current production release of
Docker on your machine.
Now, all three of my servers have the latest version of Docker installed and we're ready to set
up our swarm.
Again, all that's required is that these three nodes have solid networking to each other and specific
ports open.
If you're curious about the ports of swarm, look in the resources of this section where I actually
have a link to my own list of the firewall ports necessary for Swarm to work.
If you remember before, we did docker swarm init. Now, in this case, which is pretty common in cloud
servers, it wants us to specify an IP address to advertise the Swarm service on.
You want to use an IP address that is accessible from the other servers.
In this case, I'm going to use the public IP address for my DigitalOcean
host.
And there we go.
So far, this is just like on our local machine.
This time, though, I'm going to copy the swarm join command and go over to node2 and add it in.
And there we go.
This node is now a part of the swarm.
So we go back to node1, docker node ls, and now we have two.
You'll notice the second node is only a worker. Because as it says, if we wanted it to be a manager,
we should have gotten this manager token. But no worries. We can actually update this worker to promote
it to being a manager.
But if we're over on node2, notice that I can't use Swarm commands. Because workers aren't really privileged.
They don't have access to control the swarm.
So they're not going to be able to use any of the Swarm commands that we're used to using on the managers.
Back on node1 and the manager, I'm going to do a docker node update...
What I was doing there was hitting Tab for tab completion, which is always a fantastic feature in
Docker, especially with so many features. It was walking me through each step of how to use that update
command.
Now I've got this final update finished and it has changed node2.
Now if I do my docker node ls, you'll see that now it's considered reachable.
But the original node is still the leader. By the way, the little asterisk? That just means that's the
node you're currently talking to.
For node3, let's add it as a manager by default.
We need to go back to our original command of docker swarm, and then we need to get the join-token
manager.
You can get these tokens at any time.
You don't have to write them down or save them.
They're part of the swarm configuration and stored encrypted on disk, so don't worry about that.
You can also change these in case they possibly get exposed or you maybe get a server that might have
had a vulnerability on it, and you want to make sure that no nodes can join the swarm from the old key,
you can actually rotate these keys.
I'm going to copy this, paste it into node3.
And there we go. Back on node1.
If I do a docker node ls again, you'll see I've got three nodes. And they all have a manager status indicating
that they are managers.
So now we have a 3-node, redundant swarm, with three managers. Let's just do the same thing
we did earlier, docker service create alpine
ping 8.8.8.8
Only this time,
let's give it three replicas.
And then do a docker service
ls, and we'll see
we've got three of three already running.
If I did a docker node ps, I can actually see my local node is actually running this task or container.
I can actually specify the node, node2, and it'll give me just the containers running on node2.
If I wanted to get a full list, I could do a docker service ps, and then sleepy brown is the name that
it gave our service. And you'll see here..let me expand the screen a little bit.
You can see here that it's listing all three of our tasks.
Once you've got this swarm created, you normally don't need to be typing commands into all the different
nodes. You can really operate the whole swarm, for most things, from node1.
So we'll be doing a lot of our work from node1 in future lectures, but for now, pat yourself on the back
because you have a fully operational swarm cluster.