Alright, since this is the first lecture in this section, I'm going to cover real quick what this whole
section is about and that's containers.
Containers are the fundamental building block of the Docker toolkit and that's one of the first things
we're going to learn.
We're not going to build images or do any advanced stuff until once we've learned what containers are,
how to run them, a little bit of how they're different from a VM, and other basic functionality of a container.
So the first thing we want to do is make sure that we have the latest version of Docker and it's working.
Once we get through that and this lecture, other lectures will talk about how to start containers, how
to manage different aspects of a container: start it,
stop it,
delete it,
create it...
that sort of stuff.
And we're going to use Nginx for all that. Nginx is a really basic web server that is going
to be easy for us to use just to learn the Docker commands and how to do Docker container stuff.
After that, we're going to jump in some networking basics. You'll learn Docker networking and how the
containers talk to each other.
And for this whole section, the only real requirement is that you have the latest version of Docker
installed and that it's working properly.
So in this lecture we're going to make sure real quick that that's set up correctly.
In order for the Docker command line to work properly, you need to make sure you're in the proper
terminal for your operating system.
I'm going to be using Mac, so I can use either Terminal or iTerm2; the two popular choices on the Mac.
Then on Windows, if you're on Docker for Windows you'll use PowerShell.
If you're on the Docker ToolBox, you'll use the QuickStart Terminal that comes with Docker ToolBox.
And if you're on Linux you'll just use a Linux shell of your choosing.
These are all things that I talk about in the previous section for your set-up of your own operating
system.
So if you have more questions just look at those videos.
But let's get started.
The first command is docker version. This command simply returns the version of your client --
that's the CLI that we just used -- and the server, also called the engine; and, the engine is running
in the background on your machine.
On Windows it's usually called a service on Mac and Linux,
ot's usually called a daemon.
And what is happening here is our docker command line is actually talking to the server on my machine and
then returning its values, as well as the client values themselves.
Ideally they should be the same but they don't have to be the same versions.
And you want them to be the latest version as possible. If you have an older version like 1.12 or 1.13,
you definitely want to make sure that you go to the previous section and get the proper versions installed
because we'll be using a lot of new features that are only in the latest versions.
The fact that I did get returned information from the server, validates that I can talk to the server
and that it's working properly.
If you do get an error there, that means maybe you need to do a sudo docker version.
If you're maybe on Linux, or possibly your Docker isn't actually running and you maybe need to go to the
previous section setup videos to make sure that Docker's running properly.
Now let's get a little more information out of our Docker engine.
If we do a docker info, it'll return a lot more stuff than just the version. It'll actually give us a
lot of details about our configuration and setup for our engine.
Some of these are obvious, like the number of containers you have running or possibly the number of images
you have stored in Docker.
But a lot of this other stuff may not make sense now and that's fine.
We're going to go through a lot of it throughout this course.
Now you might be wondering what are all the commands you can use in Docker.
And you can get a list of those by simply just typing docker and hitting return.
You'll see a long list down here at the bottom.
This is not actually the full list, because if you notice up here at the top,
we now have this management command.
So starting in early 2017, Docker realized that we're getting so many commands down here in this list --
where I would just type docker space and the command -- that there were so many of them that they needed
to create an easier way to organize all these commands.
That's when they created the management commands and that creates a format where you have docker
space the management command and then the subcommand. So you will see throughout this course that we're
trying to use a little bit of both.
We mostly will use the new model of Docker.
Let's use an example here of container run -- and that's the new format of that command.
But since the beginning of the Docker project, docker run has usually been the way that we type that
command.
It's just recently that the docker container run has become the new way to run that command.
Now the cool thing about Docker, is that it's really focused on backwards compatibility.
So the docker run will probably work forever; but, new commands that we get are not going to be using
this docker command value.
It will be using docker space command space subcommand value. So, each time I use these commands,
we will explain what they are and I will show you possibly the old way of doing it and the new way of
doing it depending on whether the command has that option.
So it'll start to make sense as we go through this course.
OK even though we had a very short lecture, and it was pretty simple, let's just review real quick those
commands.
The docker version command is the one I always use first on a new Docker system; just to make sure that
my client can talk to the engine and that I'm running the version that I would expect.
Secondly docker info gives me a lot of the configuration values out of the engine just to make sure that
it's set up that way that I expect.
And lastly, we talked about the command line structure. The old way still works.
So for older commands that have been around for the last 4+ years, they still work with docker
command and then the options.
But for new commands going forward, Docker is creating a new model of the management commands with docker
space command space subcommand. The example we use was docker run,
one of the most common commands you use in Docker where the old way was docker run but the new way of
docker container run also works.
And you can decide how you want to use those commands whether you want to use the old way or the new
way because they both will still work.