All right. Enough of the lectures.
Let's actually give you a little bit of an assignment. Now that you've had some chances to play around
the container commands
in Docker, I'd like to give you a little bit of homework to start up multiple containers. We're going
to go through some of the process of what it's like to set up multiple types of images in different
containers at the same time.
You're going to maybe need some documentation with this.
You know about the --help command.
With that in mind, there's also docs.docker.com.
If you haven't been there, definitely take a few minutes to check it out and just click around.
Even if it's not something you need to look at right away, just get an idea for the breadth of documentation
there.
The actual website is totally open source and you can actually use GitHub to add documentation or
recommend changes. It's rare that a day that goes by that I don't go to that website. There is constant
amount of new information there.
I highly recommend you check it out.
Most of the time when I'm actually searching Google, it ends up being one of the two or three top choices
anyway.
You're going to start up a three-container application. We're not actually going to set up these
three different containers with application data or our source files.
I just want you to get the ideas around how to start these and how they're different and managing
them together.
You definitely want to use the -d for detached.
Then I recommend you always use --name. That's just easier to deal with when you're working
on your local machine.
You can name them whatever you'd like. I need you to give each one of them their own port because
each container can't run in the same port as other containers
if you're exposing them at the host.
Right.
If we're going to allow the host to listen for each container and forward traffic, they all need to
run on different ports.
The nginx is going to act as our proxy in this case, and it's just going to sit on port 80. The
apache server or httpd is going to run on 8080.
Then the mysql server is running on its default port of 3306.
Again, these actually aren't going to be three containers that talk to each other in any way right
yet.
But we're just going to start them up and then tear them all down again.
Something that you haven't yet experienced is one of the options for the container run command is
an environment variable passing.
So, -e or --environment will pass any environment variable you want to pass into that container.
This is a very common way for us to pass environment based settings into our containers.
It's quite often to have different environment variables for test or dev, versus production and the
environment option is how we do that.
With the mysql image you'll be using,
it actually has an option for setting a random root password on bootup.
The way that you find that password is actually going to be using the logs command to see at startup
the first time and it will spit out to the logs what that random password is going to be.
Once you start up all the containers, and you think it's correct, you can tear it all down again
with the stop and the rm commands.
I'd like you to use the ls command to make sure that you have them all started and that they're
all cleaned up.
You might need to use the ls -a to actually make sure that you've removed all of them. I'm
going to leave a video after this that actually shows how I would do it in case you get stuck.
Good luck. We'll see you on the next section.