This lecture is the answers to the assignment lecture right before this one for managing multiple
containers.
This is basically just a recording of me thinking out loud and walking through the assignment. You
might have slightly different commands. That's OK as long as you got to the end result of the three
different containers, running the three different images, with the required parameters.
Here we go.
I'll probably want to run the MySQL one first.
mysql, but I'm going to need to detach it and then open up port
3306. Then I'm going to give it a name called db. Then I'm also going to throw in this environment
variable.
That should do it.
Oop, I have too many dashes on the e.
OK.
Now I shall do docker container log mysql.
Nope. Sorry. db
logs not log.
So I don't -- let's see, I'm not sure -- I don't see it yet.
I don't see the password.
It's pretty obvious.
Let me try it again.
There we go. Generated root password right there.
I want to copy that for later.
I don't actually need it for this assignment.
But that's how I would get the password if I needed to log into that MySQL server. All right. We're going to run
the next one...docker container
run
detached
name
webserver
and then port.
It's going to be the Apache one so port 8080 on my host is going to go to 80 in my container. Then
httpd.
OK, and if I do a docker ps, both of those should be running. I can see on the right that their proper ports
are redirecting from my host into my container. That's what that little arrow means. Then, let's see one more
docker container run.
Give it a name of proxy. I'm going to have that listed on port 80 and forward to port 80. It's detached. And proper name.
OK I think that one's good. docker ps
You'll notice, by the way, that I'm typing doctor ps, not docker container
ls
just because old habits die hard and the old command is docker
ps. But it still works. All right.
All three are running. All the ports are forwarding. I properly named them...
And
I'm actually going to...
I'm actually going to test their ports. If I do curl local host,
it should give me back the nginx. If I curl...let's see, localhost 8080, I should get back the Apache.
All right.
Those are open.
Now I need to clean them up. I want to do docker container
stop
Oh that's right.
I didn't name them that.
That's silly.
I'm just going to use tab to give me a tab completion. I can do this one and this one.
Now.
OK.
All three are stopped.  docker ps -a.
Yep.
All three of them. I could have also done docker container ls -a.
Same thing.
Now, I need to remove them.
I'm going to do a
docker container rm.
I'm going to use tab completion again
and remove them.
docker ps -a -- nothing there. docker images.
This is a new command actually -- image ls. That shows me the three different images that are still there.
OK.
Everything's cleaned up. That's my assignment.