Is in this lecture, requirements are that you know how to start a container.
What we're going to be doing at the command line here is running Docker commands to understand what's
going on inside a running container. There's multiple ways that we can see what's going on in there.
We've covered the top command, which is a process list of what's happening inside the container, but there's
other stuff we can do as well. We can use the inspect command to actually see the details of how the
container started and how it's configured.
We can look at the stats command which actually gives us a view of all of our containers and the performance
statistics for each one of them in a real time stream.
Let's dive in. In order to look at some of these commands and how they act with containers, we're going
to need to actually start a few containers.
The first one we're going to start is an Nginx container like we've done before.
docker container run -d --name, lets call it nginx, and we're going to use the Nginx image.
OK.
Then the second one we'll use is another MySQL server so docker container run -d --name
mysql and we'll also need to specify the environment variable like we did before.
So, RANDOM_ROOT_PASSWORD=true
And then the mysql image.
Note that with the mysql image, as you can read on Docker Hub, it'll tell you that you have to specify one of
three options for the password.
Either you can specify a password in the command line, you can let it use no password, or you can do
what I've done here which will have it, on first boot, actually create a random password like we did in
the exercise a few minutes ago.
OK.
If we do a docker container ls,
we should see two running containers.
Great.
So we've used docker container top before.
If I just specify the mysql, you'll see that it actually lists the processes running inside that
container.
We can do the same thing, docker container top nginx, and that lists the processes running
in that container.
Another way to look at how this container is configured when it was started and all of its metadata
config, we can actually use the inspect command. docker container inspect. Then just say my mysql
and we get back a JSON array of all the data about how this container was started.
A lot of this will start to make sense as we go throughout this course.
As you can see, it is obviously a lot of data about this container. But as interesting as this config
data is, it doesn't tell us anything about the active container and what it's doing.
So let's use the docker container stats command.
If I give you a --help, you can see that it allows us to actually specify a container to only
show that. Or, if we just leave it empty and just type docker container stats,
we actually get back a streaming view of live performance data about our containers.
Unfortunately, it only shows the container ID, not the container name, but you can see by the CPU column
that every few seconds something is changing.
Obviously in a production environment, you're going to have a more complicated monitoring and performance
solution for tracking all this stuff.
It's really great for local machines where you need to make sure that you're not exhausting your
machine's RAM, because maybe you have too big of a database, or they're not filling up the hard drive
because of an out of control process.
This is a quick command to just make sure that everything is within its memory limits, and that it's not
using a ton of networking, and the block I/O is actually for your disk performance.
As you can see, these containers aren't really doing anything because we haven't asked them to do
anything. To get out of this, Control c. Let's do a quick docker container ls so that we
can match the container ID up with our stats command.
So you can see the mysql server was the one actually using almost 400MG on startup.
Just to recap what we did in this lecture, we actually first used the docker container
top command to list all the processes that will be running in a single container.
Then we got into container inspect. In container inspect,
we can actually see how the container was run, what was run with it, and what the environment and options
were when it started. Then container stats, which is sort of a live updating ability to see all containers
and what resources they're taking up as they're running.