Requirements for this lecture are that you know how to start a container from previous lectures.
We just finished the last lecture talking about seeing what's going on in a container from the outside.
This is all about getting into a container to mess around with the inside. There's a few commands
that we can use.
The first one is container run with a -it.
We'll talk about how the -it works to actually get a shell inside the container.
Then for running containers that you want to run a second process, you can also use the container
exec, and we'll show several examples of that.
Then along the way we're going to actually mention a few differences between a regular Linux distribution,
like Ubuntu, for installing on a virtual machine or on hardware.
And then what those Linux distros are like inside of a container.
Let's get started.
Looking into a container from the outside is very handy at times.
But one of the first questions that people often ask me is how do I get into the container and actually
do things in it live from the command line.
Sometimes people confuse this with wanting an SSH Server inside their container so they can ssh
into it.
But we don't actually need to do that because we have several commands at our disposal that let us get
a shell inside the container itself while it's running.
The first one is just the docker container run command.
But we're going to specify a few extra options.
We're going to do a -it.
The -it is actually two separate options.
If I just show the help real quick, you can see that the t actually gives us a pseudo tty or
a prompt similar to what you would have through ssh.
And then if we scroll up to i,
that's really what allows us to keep that session open so that we can keep running more commands.
If we do a docker container run -it, and then run another nginx. Let's call it proxy.
Then we're going to have to specify an alternate command.
If you remember at the beginning of this section where we talked about the format of the docker command
line, when you're doing a docker container run, as you can see through the help, here at the end, after
the image, you have optional command and arguments that you can send in to this new container that you're
about to start to tell it what to run. The image has a default command in it that we will see later how
to configure.
But if you wanted to change what was run on startup, you can do that right from the run line.
Let's just say Bash. Because Bash is one of the common shells that you would usually find in a container
that will give you a shell to work with.
Look at that. I'm in a prompt.
You'll notice my prompt says root which is the user that the container started as. It doesn't actually
mean I'm root on the host.
It just means I'm acting as root on the container.
That number after it is actually the container ID.
If I do a ls -al, I get a full listing of everything where I'm at.
And you can see that I'm in the root path of the file system inside the container.
I'm actually looking at all the files inside the container which is based on the Nginx image.
From here, I could go change config files,
I could download packages from the internet and do just about any common administrative thing that you
would do from a normal shell.
To get out of the shell when you're done, I'm going to type exit, like you would with any shell and now that
container has stopped.
If we actually did a docker container ls, you would not see it there.
Remember, we called it proxy.
So I had to do a -a.
And it's there. Now see the command that it ran. The default command for an Nginx container is to run
the Nginx program itself.
But when we typed our last command, we changed that default program to actually be Bash, which gave us
our shell. When we exited the shell, the container stopped. Because container
s only run as long as
the command that it ran on startup runs. Since we changed it to Bash, simply exiting Bash quit it
Now,
what if I used a full distribution of Linux instead of actually doing the Nginx. Let's do a full
Ubuntu.
It's actually going to download the Ubuntu image and place me in the prompt of this new container.
If you've ever used Ubuntu, you know about the apt package manager.
So I can use that here. Just like I would in a standard Ubuntu server. I could actually install
something apt-get install
-y
curl.
The thing about Ubuntu and other distributions inside a container is that they're usually very minimal.
A live CD or a download of the ISO of Ubuntu which you would normally put on a virtual machine is going
to have a lot more software installed by default than a Ubuntu container which is really a very minimal
version of Ubuntu that you can always add more software to with the apt package manager.
So now this running container has curl installed and I can use it just like I would on a local machine.
Once I exit the shell again, it will actually stop the container. docker container
ls. You notice I don't see it. There's that Ubuntu image that we just ran.
If I started that container up again, it would have curl installed in it.
But if I created a new container from the Ubuntu image, that different container would not have the curl
command line installed.
What if we wanted to rerun that container and get Bash right back in it again.
We could use the docker container start command.
You'll notice it's slightly different when we start an existing container, but it's similar to the
it...it's just an ai.
Then the name of our container Ubuntu. You'll notice we're right back in it and I can curl google
again and it works.
If I exit, it stopped it again.
What if I want to actually see the shell inside a running container that's already running something
like MySQL or Nginx.
We can do that too.
And that's using the exec command. docker container exec.
And you can see we have a few options here.
And the most common one is...let's say I want to jump into the MySQL container because I need to do
some administrative stuff on the MySQL itself.
I could do the it again and then the name of the container. Then the program I want to run.
And in this case again it's Bash and I'm now in the container with MySQL.
I can actually do a ps aux right inside the container which lists the processes. This will, of
course, show me the MySQL daemon that's running in the background, as well as the Bash process that I'm
currently sitting in, as well as the ps command that
I just ran. In this shell, I could jump into MySQL itself with the mysql command line. You'll
notice when I exit this Bash shell and do an ls, MySQL is still running. Because the docker container exec
actually runs an additional process on an existing running container,
it's not going to affect the root process for the MySQL daemon. Let's try one more.
As you can see here this is very useful for jumping into containers when you need to troubleshoot or
when you need to change something slightly on a running system, as well as using containers of different
distributions to give you the environment you would have if you had a full machine like a Ubuntu or
an Alpine.
Now what's Alpine? We haven't mentioned Alpine before. Alpine is another distribution of Linux, but Alpine
is designed to be very small.
It's actually only 5MB in size.
If I do a docker pull alpine, that will pull down the latest Alpine image and if I do a docker image
ls, you can actually see how small the Alpine image is compared to the Ubuntu.
The neat thing about Alpine is that it also comes with its own package manager.
So you'll see Alpine as an option on Docker Hub alot in the next section when we go over images and
Docker Hub.
But for now let's do a Bash shell inside of Alpine.  docker container run -it alpine bash.
Now what just happened here?
Why did I get in there?
It tells me that it's starting the container process and it caused the executable file bash to not be found
in the path. And what that really means is that Bash isn't in the container.
And this goes back to the concept that we can only run things in the container that already exists in
its image
when you started it.
Or maybe something that you've added later through the exec or run commands.
But in this case, how would I get in the Alpine image?
Well, Alpine is so small that it doesn't actually have Bash in it. But it does have sh. So we can replace
the command with sh, which is not quite as full featured as Bash but does get us right into the container.
If you were to search Alpine Linux on the internet, you would learn that its package manager is
apk and we could actually use that to install Bash if we really needed it.
Just to recap real quick of what we learned in this lesson.
We learned about the -it option for container run, which gives us the equivalent of an interactive
shell to actually do things in the container as we would if we were ssh'd into a server of some sort.
Then we learned a new command for
docker container exec with the it that does exactly the same thing as run, but it does it on an
existing container that's running not starting a new container.
And last, we learned a little bit about Alpine and how that's different from major Linux distributions
and how it's actually like 4MB in size and ideal for container images.