...
Requirements for this section include understanding how to start a container. Then basic TCP/IP
networking concepts, such as subnets and IPs and ports and firewalls.
You don't have to know all that, but it'll definitely make it a lot easier for you to understand this
section which is focused on conceptual stuff,
before we actually get into a bunch of the command line stuff in the next lecture.
I just want to remind you about the -p option on your container run commands which exposes the
port on your machine.
There's actually a lot more going on in the background of Docker networking that we'll talk about.
Docker has this concept of batteries included but removable which basically means that the defaults
are pretty easy and common to work with, but that you can change a lot of the options under the hood.
We'll quickly check out in this lecture the container port command that gives you a quick output
of what ports are open for that container on your network.
Then we're going to break down some of the concepts of Docker networking and virtual networks and
how packets flow around the network.
And we'll finish up with a network diagram showing how containers talk amongst each other and how that's
different from the -p of exposing them onto the physical network.
When you actually start a container, you're really in the background connecting to a particular Docker
network. By default, that is the bridge network, as we'll check out in a minute. Then each one of
those networks that you would connect to actually route out through a NAT firewall, which is actually
the Docker daemon configuring the host IP address on its default interface so that your containers can
get out to the Internet or to the rest of your network and then get back.
But we don't actually need to use the -p when we have specific containers wanting to talk to each
other inside our host.
For example, if you had an application that had a sequel server and PHP Apache container, those two containers
should be on the same network and they're able to talk to each other without actually opening their
ports up to the rest of your physical network.
If you had another application that was unrelated, that let's say was using Mongo and Node.js, you could
create a network for that so that they could talk with each other without using the -p to expose them
to the network. But they couldn't actually talk to the other network where you might have an unrelated
app running.
But the thing is that just about all those settings I described are actually changeable.
And this brings up a good saying that Docker likes to use...that is batteries included but removable.
You'll see that throughout this course that a lot of times there are defaults that just work out of
the box.
You don't even have to specify them. You just notice that things are configured in a sort of standard
way.
But a lot of these options are configurable either at runtime or even changeable after the fact. And
we'll see some of that take place here when we play around with the networks.
Some of the things that you can actually change would be creating multiple virtual networks, maybe one
per app, or different ones based on different security requirements.
You can actually, just like in the physical world, have two physical NICs on a real computer. You can
actually have two virtual networks connected to one container, or you can actually have the container
talk to no networks.
You can skip any of the virtual network configuration that comes out of the box and actually use
--
net=host, and you'll lose some of the containerization benefits.
But in some cases it might be required.
Later on, we're actually going to get into Docker network drivers. There's this whole plugin
ecosystem around Docker that extends the capabilities of Docker to a lot of third party tools.
But in this case we're going to look at a couple of different Docker network drivers and how they might
change up our networking and give us new abilities.
This is really just scratching the surface.
There's actually networking concepts throughout this course where we'll be talking about more advanced
topics of multi host private networking and concepts like sub interfaces and so on.
But for now, let's dive into some command line stuff.
As a quick review,
let's look at the -p of our container running commands...docker container run.
If you remember when we first ran a container, we used the -p to expose port 80 of our Nginx.
That took the left side, which is the host port, and forwards traffic from that port into the port
80 of the container.
If we did docker container port webhost, it actually shows this in a nice, easy format
which ports are forwarding traffic to that container from the host into the container itself.
We haven't talked about the IP address of the container.
So you might just assume that the container is using the same IP as the host. But by default, that's
not true.
We can easily get the Docker IP of that container by inspecting it and we're going to use the
format command, or option really, which you'll notice actually has a pretty specific format for how
to filter incoming stuff.
You can always use the grep command which we used earlier to filter out your text output, but the
format, the --format, it's actually a little cleaner and consistent. You do two curly brackets,
and then once we get used to knowing the format of the config file, we know that NetworkSettings.IP
Adress is the actual node of that JSON output that we want to look at.
And then webhost. Oops that means I didn't spell it right.
I P A d d.
And that's not what I expected.
If I was going to use the IP of my host because I know my Macs on my local network, and if I do an
ifconfig on my Mac, I just know that the IP address is on my home network or a 1 9 2 1 6 8 Subnet.
That's interesting that they're not the same network.
So why is that?
Let's see if it'll make more sense if I draw it out.
If my host operating system is connected to my network...this is my network...physical network. Then
this is the Ethernet interface on my host machine, in my case it's my Mac.
There's a little firewall in there that does several things. It blocks all incoming traffic coming
in from the network so that everything is blocked by default. I would call it a firewall. Any traffic
that's coming out from my containers is going to be NATed by default.
It's acting like a pretty common edge firewall on a network.
But there's this concept of the virtual networks, and by default, you'll see a network called bridge
or docker0.
When you start a new container, we'll call it C1, that container is attached to that network, that virtual
network, and that virtual network is automatically attached to your Ethernet interface on your host so
that it can get out.
In our case, when we just launched that Nginx, we gave it a -p 80:80. That told it over
here to open up port 80 on my Ethernet interface on my Mac and forward
anything coming into port 80 through that virtual network
to port 80 in that container.
By default, when I create a second container, it's put on that same bridge network.
Those two containers can talk freely back and forth on their exposed ports.
Unless I specify the -p, no traffic coming into my internal networks here is going to get to
my containers.
I can actually create more virtual networks and call them what I want. I'm going to call this one
net my app, let's say. And let's say I connect two containers here...I got MySQL.
Then I got an Apache.
On MySQL,
I didn't open up any ports, and never specified a -p. But on the Apache one, I gave it a -p of
8080:80.
That would mean over here on the right, at my Ethernet interface on my host, it's going to start listening on port
8080.
As soon as traffic comes in to my host on port 8080, it's going to route it through down to this
new virtual network I created and into that Apache server on port 80.
Inside this virtual network, the Apache server is free to talk to the MySQL server over its listening
port.
When you think about virtual networks in Docker, and where containers belong, think about how you
would put different containers in proximity to each other because they're related in their application.
As you can see, these two examples, if I had a container one and a container two up top rank something different,
If they're not going to be talking to the services in this network down below, then it would make sense
to keep them on separate virtual networks.
If they ever had to talk to each other, they would have to go through their published ports all the
way out and back in.
As a reminder, on any interface on your host, you can't listen on more than one port for multiple containers.
So, you can't have two containers listening on the port 80 at the host level.
Only one can do that.
If you try to start another container, it would actually error out and say that there's already something
else on that port. That's not a Docker limitation; that's just a limitation of how IP networking typically
works.
Just a quick recap on this section. We actually spent a lot of time on the concepts of Docker networking,
including the exposing of ports on your host to the physical network using the -p. The idea of
Docker focusing on sane defaults where they call it batteries included but removable.
How for local dev and testing, you probably can just get by with the defaults, but everything is changeable.
Then we learned about the container port command which is a quick way to look at the ports exposed
for your particular containers.
Then we broke down the packets moving around virtual networks and how those relate to other virtual
networks, and how they get in and out of your Docker machine.
So, these are all really good concepts to understand as we jump into the actual CLI stuff in the next
lecture.