The requirements for this assignment, or the things you need to know before you should do this assignment,
is that you've gone through some of the lectures in the past around getting a command shell inside the
container, and also some of the basics around Linux distributions and how they might differ,
and of course running a container. OK here's another assignment for you and it's going to be a little
different than your traditional developer-meets-container scenario.
But it's just as valid and just as common in the real world.
In the past you might have set up a whole virtual machine just to simply test something like a different
command line version or different Linux distribution.
But with containers that gets WAY easier.
Imagine yourself being a support engineer for a server farm that runs both Ubuntu and CentOS, and a
ticket comes in that asks you to check on the different curl versions in those two distributions.
So in the old, pre-container world, you'd probably have to set up a virtual environment and wait for operating
systems to install unless you had them ready.
But in this world we can actually just run a few commands.
So really the goal here is just to run the curl version command inside two different Linux distributions
in just a few minutes.
So we'll be using the centos:7 version.
And then the ubuntu:14.04  version. You'll want to use the -it on your docker run command
and give it the bash command at the end.
Then there's a new option you should try, which is the --rm, which will save you some time
later. So I recommend looking that up through Help on the command line or through the Docker Support
site at docs.docker.com.
And really once you're in there,...
oh and by the way, you definitely want two different terminal windows so you can switch back and forth between
these two...
and in order to run the curl version command, you're going to need to update each one of the distributions
or check whether or not curl's installed.
I've given you some commands there that they're a little bit different between the two. Really
this exercise isn't going to give you an interesting output.
It's really just helping you understand how easy and quick you can jump into different software or Linux
distributions, run some tools, and then get out. In the end, I would expect you to have different curl
versions in those two distributions.