OK.
This is a lesson where I'm going to walk through the assignment for the CLI app testing and you can see
my thought process as I just sort of talk out loud while I do it.
OK.
So, I need to start two Linux distributions. We're going to use the rm, so docker container run rm.
Let's see...I'm not going to want to run it as a daemon.
I am going to want to use i t
cent os 7.
I don't need a port open but I do need to get bash.
OK. Then I going to need to do yum update curl.
And then while that's going, I'm in iTerm2 and iTerm2 is my terminal command.  So command shift d
will give me another window... another shell
so I can then do docker container run rm
it ubuntu 14.04 bash and then do an apt get update then apt get install curl. I'm actually going to throw
in a -y so it automatically does it.
Then up here, I can do a curl version while that one is going. All right.
And it's got curl version 7.2 9 installed.
And then ubuntu.
All right curl version.
All right and ubuntu is 7. 35. I just happen to know that CentOS tends to lag behind in
some more enterprise-y Linux distributions so it tends to have older packet package versions than
Ubuntu even though we're actually running a Ubuntu version that's more than a few years old.
OK.
So when I type exit I shouldn't see my container in there anymore.
No. And then appear if I type exit and I do another listing,
you'll see that one thing left is an nginx container I had left over from my previous unrelated session.
So my CentOS disappeared.
And my Ubuntu disappeared, which is what the --rm does for us.
All right.
And that's it.
Nothing to clean up.