Hey there. My name is Bret and I'll be your instructor for this course.
This is just a quick video about me.
I been in I.T. for 20 years and I've done lots of things.
I've worked in the Navy.
I've worked for the federal government, local government, big business, little business.
I've been a freelancer for 7 years now as a consultant.
I've worked for startups. I've actually been a startup...so I have quite a diverse background but
I've always been sort of an ops and sysadmin person with developer on the side sort of thing.
I don't pretend to be the amazing developer like a lot of you probably are.
I've been using Docker for over 3 years now and I've been teaching it almost as long.
I pretty quickly got excited about Docker and realized how awesome the container ecosystem
was going to become and saw that it was sort of the future of development and deployment and managing
servers. I started the local Meetup for Docker in early 2016 and I speak a lot there and talked a
lot with people there.
I've been teaching at workshops and at conferences a lot for over a year and a half now so I've taught
hundreds of people now how to use Docker and specifically orchestration and production concerns because
that's my focus and I run a couple of local Meetups.
I mentioned the Docker Meetup.
I also run a Code for America Meetup. I'm very excited about that.
You should totally check out Code for America.
And I'm a big believer in community and open source in particular.
So 3% of the profit for this course will actually be donated to a couple of charities that I
really believe in: the Electronic Frontier Foundation and the Free Software Foundation.
And you should definitely check those out as well.
When I'm not actually doing Docker in all of its forms I'm probably traveling with my wife or Crossfitting
or cooking or gaming.
So thanks so much for learning a little bit about me and I look forward to meeting you in the course
in the Q&A or in the Slack chat.