All right you're a Windows user and you want to get Docker working.
So let's get you to it in this lecture.
You're going to learn the two types of containers that can now run on Windows.
You're going to get through which dog addition you want to install based on your version of windows
in your edition of Windows you're also going to learn the difference between Windows 10 and server 2016
and how the desktop and server treat are a little bit differently.
And then the next lecture is going to get to installing it.
There are two types of containers.
Now on Windows which is really cool we have the options now for Linux containers or.
Up until recently we just called them containers because that was the only type of container we had.
Now we have windows containers.
Now this course by default is actually going to talk about Linux containers because we've had those
for four plus years and that's everything that we all know about containers was Linux based.
It was only till late 2016 that Microsoft really formalized the concept of a Windows container and made
it usable and they're rapidly innovating.
So it's a pretty exciting space.
But most of the concepts are the same.
You're going to use them the same way you're going to manage them the same way.
It just matters that buying areas that are running inside them you know SQL X-C vs. MySQL
on Linux or something.
So we'll going to talk in this course about containers when I say that I really mean Linux containers
when I talk about specifically on Windows containers.
I will say Windows containers so that we're clear.
OK.
And the best version of Docker on Windows is Docker for Windows.
That's actually an edition of Docker and it's got a whole install that we're seeing a moment and it's
really great on Windows 10.
It only works on pro and enterprise.
Unfortunately if you had the home version of Windows 10 or an older version of Windows it's not going
to work.
In those cases you're going to use the or tool box which was the only option we had until a year ago
so it's still a great option.
It's still updated it's still supported.
It's just not going to have all the nice cool features that Docker for Windows has because Windows 10 has
new innovations in it using Hyper-V that we just don't get in those old versions unfortunately.
Windows now with server 2016 it does support Windows containers.
We won't go in a whole lot into that in this course because that's still really new stuff and they're
making major changes even just three or 4 months ago they added a whole new networking feature set
to it.
So it's a rapidly evolving ecosystem.
I will continue to update this course and any other courses with all that stuff as well and just as
an example of what that's like is we had in the spring not only this new networking overlay networking
that we'll get into later in the course but we also have native Linux containers that we haven't even
seen yet.
But Windows announced it at DockerCon and that basically is some feature we're going to see in the near
future that supposedly will have Windows intelligently and automatically figuring out when you want
to run a container whether it should be on Linux or Windows and then do that for you.
Today we have to manually specify they're supposedly going to make some new feature in the future that
works on that.
That's something that nobody else is doing.
No other platform is doing that so it's pretty cool to be on Windows.
It's just evolving rapidly so be prepared.
So if you're on Windows 10 pro in Enterprise you're one of the lucky few that get to actually run Docker
for Windows and you can get that from stored up.
Docker Delcam it's actually got more features than if you just installed Linux in a Linux VM on your machine.
So if you're tempted to just say screw it I'm just going to install an exe VM and I'm going to install
Linux on it.
Well that would work like a server in the cloud like a Linux production server might but the docs for
Windows and the Docker toolboxes are really helping you develop and test stuff locally so it does things
like map drives from your host operating system into the container and we'll get to that stuff later.
But it's worth trying.
OK before you go that other route in the background Docker for Windows is actually using Hyper-V which
uses a tiny little Linux VM for the Linux containers.
So if you're on Windows 10 pro or Enterprise right now and you have a virtual box or VM where they may
not work with Hyper-V I know virtual box and Hyper-V don't play well together so you may have to google
around the Internet for solutions on trying to get those to work right.
If you want to use both.
Personally I just decide to shift everything in the Hyper-V once Docker shift it into Hyper-V.
It is power native which means in this course if you're on Docker for Windows I expect you to be using
power shell and I will show you commands on how to do that.
You can get other shells to work if you press shell ninja and you like bash or you like the old command
prompt.
That's fine on Docker for Windows 7 8 and 10 home we already use a Docker tool box which is not as fancy
as the Docker for Windows but it's still great.
Still works fine.
You could use it every day.
Like others you're going to download that stored at Docker.com and it does run a tiny little Linux
VM in the background and it uses virtual box and it uses a command line called dock or machine to manage
that virtual box and you'll see that later in the course as well.
If you just want to learn how Docker machine works right now you can actually just go google it and
I'll give you great instructions on how you use or machine command line to create IMs and destroy them.
You can actually create multiple Docker machines if you wanted.
Now in this machine it comes by default with a tool box.
It comes with a bash shell called the dock or QuickStart terminal I believe is it's called and that's
what I expect you to use in this course.
That's the one that's going to work the best.
It's going to auto start things and make sure everything's working correctly.
If you're more savvy and you wanted to get into other options for shells I might give you some tips
along the way but I can't really support every shell in every possible configuration for your environment.
So I'm going to focus on how a Docker provides it out of the box.
Note that those versions of Windows that we're talking about right now do not support the windows containers
they only support the Linux containers in that small little VM.
And lastly just a note about Windows Server 2016 as it is a part of this course and it supports Windows
native containers so it runs a Windows binary out of the box without Hyper-V or anything installed in
a doctor container which is pretty cool.
It does also support Docker for Windows but Docker for Windows is really a tool kit for local development
and testing.
It's not meant as a production tool.
So the only reason I would tell you to do this is if you had Windows Server installed on your local
machine as a replacement for Windows 10 right.
Some developers do that they developed locally on Windows Server because that's the platform they use
in production and they like to develop on that platform.
So if you're doing that totally install Docker for Windows it'll give you a better experience but if
you're in production don't do that you really want to run Docker Windows containers natively on server
2016.
And if you're going to do Linux containers you run those natively on Linux not on onger for Windows
in production.
The previous versions of Windows don't really support anything with Docker unless you're talking about
a previous version of Windows that's running Hyper-V and that's running on your bare metal.
And then you just run a Linux VM.
Of course you can do that.
You can do that anywhere anywhere you can run a VM you can put Linux on it and it can run Docker so
that one is definitely still on the table.
If that's the way you want to go.
But in this course I'm not going to expect you to be developing and testing on server 2016.
I'll assume that you're on Windows 10 or Ubuntu or Mac or something.