Now we're going to actually get into the real install. First we're going to download install doc
or we're going to tweak some of the settings of it or check them out at least and then we're going to
go clone my repo.
We're going to get an editor.
You don't have a code editor.
And then we are checking out a few options if you want to tweak your terminal and your shell set up
we can get to that to.
So here's my plain old windows Tim Pro machine.
And the first thing we're going to do is we're going to store it at Docker.com
and I'm going to click on Docker see here in the middle and then Docker Community Edition for Windows.
Now in here you'll notice that by default when I click to get Docker it's going to download the Docker
for Windows.
He says this requires when asked in professional if I had an older version of Windows that will show
in a few minutes I would click on the dock tool box.
But here I'm going to say get Docker and by the fall by the way this is installing the Stable condition
not the Edge for one Edge I guess scroll down a little farther and I could choose edge or if I was actually
on the server version I could actually do the Edge there as well.
Let's save this.
I personally save it before I run it because it seems to work better that way.
And then we're going to run the install and the install is pretty typical for Windows.
It's going to ask me if it's OK now it's installing.
You know it's not running.
I would see a little Moby icon down there.
So let me actually run it and it's going to ask me about Hyper-V.
So if you don't have Hyper-V installed on your machine then this will actually enable it and reboot.
Now that means you have to have local admin.
I mean you had to have local admin to install this thing and you don't have to have local admin for
Hyper-V.
If you're on a laptop or desktop that you've never done virtualization on there there's a rare case
that you may need to go in the BIOS and actually enable the virtualization features in the BIOS.
And that's well-documented on the internet.
If you have an error I recommend just looking at the error up on the Internet and you'll probably will
find that everyone saying oh yeah go in your bios and find the extensions and install the VTX extension
or whatever it is in the BIOS.
You're not actually installing it you're actually just enabling it.
But that's a rare case.
Most of the time people that have problems installing it's either because they're on a home edition
but they forgot to check and they thought they had pros so they try to install the pro version.
Or maybe they're running an older version of Windows 10 doesn't have the latest updates.
It is important that you keep your windows machine up to date for Docker because Windows is updating
their stuff as rapidly as Dockers updating theirs and they're both related.
So you definitely get to keep those.
You can actually now see on my machine I've rebooted and Docker is starting in this little icon down
at the bottom once it's booted then I'll see this little prompt and I can run my power show as me not
as admin but just as me and I can do a darker version and I should see it running.
And this is the version I have installed this is the latest stable version.
And in case you were so inclined in the background this is running Hyper-V so I can run the Hyper-V
desktop app and I can actually see on my desktop that this is running in something called a Moby Linux
VM and it's got 2GB of RAM installed and it's uptime is just a minute because it just started so real
quick.
Let's just go into the settings right click on that little icon down there and we'll go up here to settings
and as a couple that you need to care about if you store your code that you might use in this course
on a different drive you need to check that here.
I definitely going to check see because that's where I keep a lot of my code so I need to enable where
ever I'm going to have code running inside a container.
You'll see more about that later.
But you got to do that here.
And the other thing is you might if you want if you have enough resources you can always bump up the
memory or the C-p use.
I think it comes pretty cool out of the box.
I mean 2GB in two-CD uses a pretty good amount.
But if you start hitting it limits and starts to get slow you can always bump those up depending on
your hardware.
Right.
And the rest of these options you're kind of kind of leave the same probably you're not going to have
to mess with those too much in this course.
But when I apply these settings it will require restarting of ducker and while that's happening.
Let's go clone my repo.
And remember that this is in the resource lecture earlier in this section.
Now I'm going to clone this but I want to clone it in desktop.
If you've never use get up before then you can use a GUI.
And that's probably one of the easiest ways that you're not used to get up if you know get how you get
you've got your own way to do it.
But here what I can do is I can actually use the GitHub gooey to download and clone my repo.
So I'm going to install that.
All right and then I'm actually going to put all of my code in a directory called code.
So I'm going to make a directory so you'll see on my machine that I actually put all of my software
code inside a directory called code on underneath my user.
So that's where I'm going to clone this from GitHub at.
And if you remember earlier I just changed the settings so that the C-Drive could be where I store some
code that Docker can see.
So I'm just going to log in as me.
OK.
Now that I have GitHub installed one of the ways I can clone it is from the website I can copy to your
el and then go back over to desktop and say clone repository.
Copy that in and then member I wanted it.
This is not going to be under Documents.
It's going to be under code that's where I put my hands.
So clum Now the advantage of doing it this way instead of downloading the zit is that you can come in
here and update it because I do update this repo when there's fixes or changes in Docker which happens
pretty pretty much every month.
So now if I do it during Here you can see them in the doctor that to me Docker M.E. directory.
And there we go.
Now if you're not savvy on code editors a little tip here is the best one.
I like for editing is Visual Studio code.
I can you can just search vs code in the US code and you'll get the Web site coming right up.
And then you can download it and install it just like a regular Windows app and it works quite well.
One of the best parts about this editor is that it has a built in Docker syntax so it'll let me open
up Duck or compose files and Docker files.
As you'll learn in this course and it will highlight the code in them and give me actual little hints
about how to use it.
And the last little tip here is around a couple of options for your command line.
So if you want to add a Docker documentation you'll see that they have a whole section on setting
up tab completion in power show and tab completion and Power Shell is what we get.
And Linux and Mac out of the box.
So basically it means that when I type the dog or command I can actually hit tab and it will fill out
the information for that common command depending on what I've typed.
And you can see that I don't have it here it just kind of list directories which is not what I want.
I actually wanted to list things like duck or run or other commands.
Well the way you get that widget install this and it's a couple of steps you'll.
You can see both of these will actually give you full steps to get it started and running.
But I'll just show you the quickest way I know how.
So we're going to actually install the module per the instructions on the GitHub repo and you'll see
right here.
All I have to do is install module with a scope of current user posh Docker and when I do that it's
going to actually ask me to install a different option called New get and New get is fine.
It's actually from Microsoft.
It's partly how you install modules on your machine.
So just say yes there and say yes again.
And now that we've installed it we need to actually enable it and we do that with import module posh
Docker and if you get an error about your security scripts disabling thing that has what is actually
happening is partially secure by default and it's preventing you from running an Internet script.
So what we want to do is if we go over here to the Docker documentation they have a little more information
on how to get this going and what you can do here is you can set an execution policy.
But what that's going to mean is that you're going to have to it's not going actually let you do it
as a non admin.
So what you're gonna have to do is then start power shell as an admin.
If you just saw I right click there run that and then in that window I'm going to set my execution policy
to a little less secure.
But it should be fine for remote sign that's pretty reasonable.
And then now we should be able over here to try the import module again on this window and there we
go.
Now the way I know it works is when I type in Docker and then I hit tab it gives me Docker commands
here.
So for example if I just typed in Docker help I get a list of all the different command options.
But if I type in Docker and I hit tab it actually starts going through those.
However this module is a little bit limited and it's a little bit dated.
So unfortunately it's the best option we have on Windows for power show command depletion but if you'll
notice it's actually a little dated.
It hasn't had an update in over 6 months.
So with the current command line formats you may not find it extremely valuable.
I did find it better than nothing but there's a long way for it to go it's certainly not as good as
Mac or Linux.
But it is the good thing is it's open source.
So maybe when you have some time and you want to get savvy at power show command completion.
You can go here and help out.
Now I do want to point out that even though we've installed the module for the current user and enabled
it it's not going to automatically start every time unless we add it to our power show profile.
If you didn't know what that was it's actually very similar to a bash profile that profile of a file
or a bash RC file.
Maybe depending on which one you prefer and actually on the darker side it's really nice to give you
this little snippet which we'll check to see if you have an existing profile file and create it.
If you don't
and so I didn't have one.
So what it did is it automatically created that profile in my documents directory and then added this
import module posh Docker to it which is pretty cool.
If you start to get into power show you learn that that power profile is actually pretty powerful and
you can do some pretty cool stuff with it and make your power cells set up pretty advanced and fancy
The other option is if you want to replace this window right so this power show window is a terminal
emulator not the same as the shell that's inside it because we still have to use the power shell shell
but we can use is a different gooey for that show.
And that might be commander dot net and Commander is basically a console emulator that gives you a huge
amount of features for free open source out of the box.
And the way I install it is I just download it.
It's a zip file and I actually make sure that by the way when you do this you right click go to properties
and unblock so that you can actually unzip it and then it works doesn't complain to you.
All right.
Now that I've extracted the commander I'm going to hear and I'm going to drag the commander button down
here the commander you is actually what that is.
I'm just going to drag that down to my start menu or my task bar rather and that way I can launch it
from here.
And the first time it's going to do some stuff that's going to set up some things.
Notice that it's actually got a tab down here and I can create more tabs and I can do that over here.
A dropdown menu is actually several of them here.
This one allows me to decide what my next tab is going to run as is it going to run Bash is going to
run power shell or they're going to run the command prompt.
Well I remember I told you earlier we need to run this power show so we're going to be in here and then
we're going to type in Docker p.s. and that way we go talker info works and you'll learn about these
commands all in a minute.
But the point is a kind of just works out of the box.
If you wanted that posh to always work then what you will you might need to do the posh Docker thing
rather you might need to come over here and come up in two settings and then you know you look at this
you're like all the cow there's a whole lot of settings here.
So what you need to do is come down here to startup tasks.
Don't be distracted by everything else.
And over here under power shall power shall we need to take out this little option right here that says
no profile.
OK.
Because that will prevent it from loading the profile file we just created.
And you can say those settings and then you close the commander and then you started up again.
No set defaults the command by default.
So you can always go in the settings and change that.
If I go over here and say power show Power Shell then I get this nice little power shall prompt.
And see that I have power show completion then if I do Docker and I have completion here as well.
Look at that.
All right.
So we got everything working but this is a pretty neat show.
You do not have to use this for this course.
I do expect that everything works in here before it works in here.
So if you're having problems here don't come running to the Q&amp;A just yet.
Actually just try and get a partial window to see if it works because it might be something messed up
with Commander but it's a neat option.
And I tend to run it whenever I'm using Windows.