OK so this lecture is for getting the tool box installed.
That means you're using Windows 10 Home, or one of the older versions of Windows like 7, 8, or 8.1.
Even though the Toolbox is legacy, it's still got some pretty cool features.
In this lecture, we're going to actually download and install it, then we're going to clone my GitHub
repo, then we're going to start the QuickStart Terminal and that is actually the command line interface
that Docker gives you for the Toolbox.
Then we're going to maybe tweak some of the VM settings or at least show you how to do that.
And finally getting a code editor and seeing how we might change the shell out so maybe you can use
a different shell instead the default command prompt that comes with Windows.
All right.
As you can see I'm on a Windows 8 machine, actually 8.1, and I'm actually already on store.docker.com
...
And like all the other editions of Docker,
this is where you get it.
So for Windows we're under Docker CE. Then we scroll down until we find Windows.
Now for the Toolbox, it's not the default option.
So if you notice up here at the top, it talks about that it needs Windows Professional
10 or Enterprise.
And then there's "for previous versions get Docker Toolbox."
So let's click on that and that will take us to a previous site where you could actually get stuff from
Docker which was on the docker.com site.
This is where the ToolBox is living for now.
Eventually it may go and live in the store but you just download the one for Windows.
It's the same one for all versions of Windows.
And I happen to already have that downloaded.
So right here,
just run that install and it'll walk you through the set up.
Now I recommend you do a full install here.
So on all the options, you want checked.
And in my case I actually already have it installed so it didn't check them all by default, but for yours,
it should have them all checked.
You want VirtualBox because that's how it's going to run the Linux VM in the background it's actually
going to run Docker for us. The Git for Windows allows us to actually have a Bash prompt that will
make it seem a little bit more like Linux or Mac when we're using Docker.
So let's say now that I've finished my Docker install and I'm going to DoubleClick the Docker QuickStart.
And that will automatically kick off the initialization process.
What that looks like is you'll see it's running something called the pre-create checks
and it's actually creating a VirtualBox VM and it's using a boot2docker.iso to do that, which is
a very small version of Linux.
Then you see that it's provisioning from networking now is probably going to prompt you a couple of
times for permissions.
That's totally normal that's a VirtualBox thing.
Eventually it'll get down to where you see the Moby, in ASCII format.
And that's a signal that it's working and you'll see that it's giving me a default machine IP of
192.168.99.100. Remember that this is in the resource lecture earlier in the section.
Now I'm going to clone this, but I want to clone it in Desktop.
If you've never used GitHub before, then you can use a GUI.
And that's probably one of the easiest ways if you're not used to GitHub. If you know GitHub then
you've got your own way to do it.
But here what I can do is I can actually use the GitHub GUI to download and clone my repo.
So I'm going to install that.
Then I'm actually going to put all of my code in a directory called code.
So I'm going to make a directory. You'll see on my machine, that I actually put all of my software code inside
a directory called code on underneath my user.
So that's where I'm going to clone this from GitHub.
So I'm going to log in as me. Now that I have GitHub installed, one of the ways I can clone it is
from the website, I can copy the URL and go back over to desktop and say clone repository.
Copy that in. Remember I wanted...
This is not going to be under Documents.
It's going to be under code, that's where I put my stuff.
So clone. Now the advantage of doing it this way instead of downloading the zip, is that you can come
in here and update it because I do update this repo when there's fixes or changes in Docker which happens
pretty pretty much every month.
So now if I do a dir in here, you can see them in the udemy docker mastery directory, and there
we go.
The last thing I want to point out is you need a code editor of some sort.
It's not that great to use notepad even though it does work.
So I recommend Visual Studio Code.
It's a free editor from Microsoft and you can get it over just by googling visual studio code and it's
free to download, runs on Mac, Windows, and Linux.
And actually it's running on the atom platform if you've ever played with Atom which is another editor
from GitHub, But this one actually has a nice add-on for Docker and a lot of other nice features that
I think really are great out of the box.
So download that you might see me use a couple of times during the course.
And there you go.
What's happening in the background here is VirtualBox is actually running silently and you don't see
the GUI necessarily but it doesn't mean it's not running it's actually sitting here running what
was automatically created which was the default machine.
So this is actually just a regular VM running Linux. Even though it is a small and limited version of
Linux that Docker installed,
you can change the properties of it especially when it comes to the hardware.
So I can't change anything right now because it's running so I could do a shut down here and then once
it's shut down, I could actually go in and change settings like how many CPUs it has access to, or how
much ram it has access to.
And that's really just dependent upon your system and how many resources you have.
For example, by default it gives it a GB of RAM and a single processor.
Maybe I want to bump it up to two and maybe I want to give it 2GBs of RAM.
I can just put that up something like that.
And then click OK. I could start it from here,
but we also can control it from something called Docker Machine. There will be a later lecture
on what Docker Machine can do.
But fundamentally Docker Machine creates VMs either in the cloud or on your local machine that run
Docker. If I just do a docker machine ls here,
you'll see that it sees the machine that it's automatically created, and the first machine it
creates, it always creates as default, and I could actually start it with docker machine start.
You'll see that it actually kick it off here.
And so I don't ever really need to use Oracle VM virtual box manager.
I don't actually have to play with that at all unless I want to change the hardware settings.
So now while that's starting and getting its IP again so that we can mess with it, I want to talk a little bit
about this QuickStart terminal.
So this is actually the default way. You need to run this at least once because then it's going to
automatically create that default machine. It's automatically going to set it up and do the
networking for you.
But after that you don't have to use it.
As long as you can get the Docker Machine from somewhere,
you can run Docker Machine in the Docker command line.
if you're a little bit more savvy user and you want to do a custom command line or a custom shell and
terminal.
You can try.
Commander, cmder.net,
and it really just changes the GUI and the functionality around that GUI. It's still inside it
running a PowerShell or cmd prompt or Bash, but it does give you a lot of features around the GUI.
I recommend downloading and extracting the full version.
And when you do that, make sure that you right click on the zip file and go into properties and unblock it.
Because once you unzip it, it doesn't actually have an installer you just need to unzip it and once
you unzip it, it won't run without a bunch of warnings and problems
unless you unlock it first...because it considers that a security feature in Windows; you've probably run into
that before.
So extract all that. You can extract that right into your Downloads folder.
That's what I do.
And then inside cmder you'll see something called cmder.
And if you simply run that by default it'll give you a command prompt, a
cmd.exe, and you'll see that you have some cool options here where I can actually run a PowerShell
prompt if I want. I can run multiple tabs and a lot of other nice features where I can actually expand
it and shrink it at will.
And that's great.
But how do we get Docker running in that.
Well it's not that hard.
It just takes a few extra steps.
So you can see over here that I have docker machine ls
LS, and that shows me that I have one machine with Docker running and as you learn in future lectures
in the next section, I can do a Docker version that will tell me the Docker version of both my client
and the server running in the background.
But over here I can do docker-machine ls
and I can do Docker version.
But you'll notice that it says it can't connect to server and that's a common problem on Windows or
on the toolbox specifically.
What that means is that Docker isn't actually running in Windows it's running in the VM.
So my client, my little command line Docker right here, can't talk to that unless I tell it where to
go.
And that's one of the things this nice little GUI over here does, that I need to set up over here.
And the way we do that is with Docker Machine.
So if I just do a docker-machine ls again, you see that has the one machine there, If I do a
docker-machine help, I get lots of help.
Get lots of information.
And one of the things I can do here is I can type docker-machine env default, because remember that's
the name of the default machine.
And that will actually get me some variables that I can then copy and paste
into my host.
But it actually tells me down here at the bottom that if I just do this it should work.
So let me copy and paste that.
And now what should happen if I do a docker version, I get back both the client and the server.
Now if you're savvy enough with cmder, you can actually have it do that stuff automatically on startup.
I'll leave that to you.
Otherwise just know that you can use the docker-machine env default to get the commands you need in order
to tell Docker how to find the server. Then once it can find it you can do all the Docker commands
that come in to later lectures.
In this lecture you learned how to get the Docker ToolBox on older versions of Windows.
I just want to give you a couple extra tips and summarize some of the things we talked about real
quick.
The Docker QuickStart Terminal is how you start it.
Remember you need to run that once
in order for it to automatically create the default machine and get everything set up. You can still actually
use Docker Machine after that to manipulate that Docker machine in the background.
But that actually defaults to the Bash shell and creates everything for you.
Do note that during this course we're going to talk about something called a Bind Mount. That's where
it connects source files that you've downloaded on your Windows machine into the Docker Linux machine.
OK.
And that's known as a Bind Mount. That actually works with the ToolBox, but it's only going to work for
code that you stored inside the user's directory.
So make sure that whenever you get downloads of code, you actually make sure
they're in your user profile, and not somewhere else on a different drive letter.
Unfortunately different drive letters and different paths will not work with the ToolBox. They have
to be in your user profile.
This also is a good thing that you don't use for databases. So I don't recommend that you do a bind mount -
and again we'll explain the details of that later - but that you do a bind mount for databases it's really
just for code. Because Windows file systems are quite different than Linux file systems and they don't
always work well together when they're sharing.
And again remember that you can always use docker-machine to actually recreate that Linux VM that it created
for you.
The default one.
Or additional ones. The great editor that I recommend is Visual Studio Code in this course.
If you would like a shell replacement, you might want to consider cmder.net and you can get that at
cmder.net.