Are you a Mac user and ready to use Docker.
Well this lecture is going to get you all the tools you need to use this course with Docker and to get
the best doc or set up on your Mac.
So the nice thing is I'm going to be using all the demos or at least most of the demos on my Mac so
it'll feel very native for you.
The required version of Mac isn't actually even recent So you probably will be on the minimum version.
It's actually a three year old OS at this point on Yosemite and really Yosemite works on every Mac hardware
for the last 10 years.
So as long as your laptop is less than 10 years old and you're using a version of Mac that was released
in the last three years that Docker for Mac product that you can get from store docker.com will work
and it's the best way to use Docker on your Mac.
It has all the features and all the new bonus sort of ease of use things going on in terms of like networking
and storage and stuff.
And we'll get into that.
But that's really the best way to go if for some reason you can't do that.
Maybe your office that you use your Mac from it requires an Mavericks or one of the older versions like
line or something.
That's OK there's still an option known as Doc or tool box which is sort of the legacy.
It was actually the only version of Dr We could use on a Mac.
Up until mid 2016 when they created Docker for Mac.
So Dr. toolbox is still supported still get the latest versions of Doc are in it.
It's just not going to have all of the nice little extra features and performance benefits of doc or
for Mac.
Other options for using Docker on your Mac include just installing it in a Linux VM.
I mean however you want to create a VM do that whether it's locally with virtual box or VMWare Fusion
or Parallels or installing it on a Linux VM on the Internet on the cloud.
You know right on us or Azure or Digital Ocean.
So wherever you can get a Linux VM installed you just can install Dagar on that and you can do 98 percent
of this course that way.
Other options include actually installing Docker in a Windows VM on your Mac.
That might sound kind of weird.
It's like too many layers of stuff going on right and actually that requires something called nested
virtualization.
So I don't really recommend it.
I won't support it in this course really I won't talk about it.
It is possible to make it work in case you for some reason just want to run DR on a Windows machine
on your Mac.
I personally just do that for testing and demo purposes but if you want to do that it works with VM
or fusion.
It does require a little special setting for nested virtualization which means virtualization inside
of virtualization.
So you've got to get that working.
But I'm told by the doctor team that it does work and the last little option here or tidbit I guess
is that don't use homebrew to install Docker.
If you've actually already done that you need to uninstall that doctor because what that is is the command
line only.
It's not going to actually have the Docker server or any of the other features that Docker comes with.
It's only going to have the Docker command line tool and that's useful if you want to use Docker to
talk to a server remotely.
But we're not going to do a whole lot of that in this course.
We're going to focus on using Dr on your machine.
So the setup process is going to basically go like this.
In this lecture we're going to actually install Docker and then check out some of the settings or preferences
for Doc or for Mac and tweak does a little bit and then we're going to download my get up repo that
you're going to need in this course.
With all of the code samples and stuff then we're going to talk about code editors and I prefer a specific
one visual studio code just because it works really well with Docker.
But just about any one will work whatever favorite one you use will work fine.
And then we're going to show some optional things where maybe you want to tweak your terminal or your
shell set up in your Mac so that it works easier from the command line if you're going to be doing or
stuff all day long.
OK so let's get started with the install.
So go to store dot dot dot dot com as you can see I'm already there and everything in this course is
focused on the free version or the Docker community edition Ducker S.E.
So when this interface changes because all interfaces changes on the web right you're going to have
to find the D'Agostini download area and you'll see that there is an addition for all sorts of different
Wes's and we're going to look for the Mac one which happens to be at the top and over here on the right.
I had this get download now you can just click this but you'll notice that.
Also if you're if you're an older version of Mac it'll tell you hey the backup option is Takhar tool
box.
But if we scroll down a little bit we get two options and I'm going to use the edge version.
The edge is kind of like a beta and I'm of course a tester so I like testing the software and I'd prefer
to see the new features first but I find edge actually to be quite stable.
And with this product only being like a year old I actually find that it gets the things I need the
new features or bug fixes faster as well so I don't know.
Your experience may vary and so generally I tell people if you're in an enterprise environment and you're
looking to have your whole team on exactly the same version that you have in production and to sort
of match all that up then I'd say that stick was stable for everyone else.
I say give em a shot and if at any time you want to change these two it's actually super easy in the
interface to change.
Built in from stable back to edge and back and forth.
So I'm going to do the edge and we're going to run that DMG file
and it should open up a screen that allows you to drag the Docker app into your applications folder
like a typical Mac would and it'll copy that over and allow you to run it and close this window.
You can actually close the web browser and go launched Docker.
Now the first time you run it it'll give you this warning just simply because you're downloading it
over the Internet and not from the Apple store.
So go ahead and click open but you won't get that after that.
Now we're going to walk through the setup process.
It's really easy.
We're just going to click next and it's going to ask us for root privileges and then we're going to
get a nice set up menu and one of the options is you can sign in and create a Docker I.D. It actually
gives you some neat cloud services that we'll talk later in this course.
But you don't have to do that right now.
That's not a requirement.
We're just going to wait for it to start and you'll see what a top it says Docker is now running.
And you'll notice that it gives me a menu bar icons so I can get lots of options from here including
everything from checking for updates to restarting Docker, to exiting Docker, and by default this thing
will start.
Every time your computer starts when you log in and away we go.
So before we go any further I want to talk about a few preferences that you might want to change.
One of them is I mentioned the option of switching between the edge and the stable versions in case
maybe you ever have an issue with edge.
You can actually do that here and it will sort of remove your Docker VM and then create a new one but
so you don't want to do this every day but in case you have a bug and you think maybe there's something
to do with the edge version you can always switch back to stable.
Second thing is whenever you're working with code that's on your host machine and you want to work with
it in a Docker container.
This is known as bind mounting.
We'll talk a lot about that later.
But for now just remember that when we get to that section you need to make sure that your code whatever
you're going to use is in one of these volumes or one of these directories on your Mac I should say.
And so really for me I just make sure that my code is inside my user directories and for me that slash
users slash Bret.
And for you it's your probably your user name after the users and so you notice that that's already
in here.
But if you're a someone who makes a custom root directory on your Mac you're going to need to add that
in here with the plus symbol.
Docker is actually on a Mac running a tiny VM in the background.
It's running a tiny Linux VM and that's because Docker doesn't run natively on the Mac kernel.
Apple hasn't actually built in Docker functionality into its OS kernel so we have to run this tiny
little VM.
And if you've ever run any virtualization you know that it can give it however many C-p use and however
much RAM and I normally leave mine at the to C-p use of the for my laptop and then I usually ramp my
RAM up to like let's say for.
You don't have to do that.
It all depends on how much memory is in your system.
I happen to have 16 gig of RAM on my Mac so I have plenty of room to give it more access in Mac or in
the Docker preferences.
Do note though that Docker won't actually take up all of that RAM unless it needs it.
So it's nice and conservative.
That's the same thing with the space too.
On the hard drive it won't take up a huge amount of space it will only grow as it needs to.
And so just because you're giving it for a gig bigger RAM doesn't mean that it's not able to share that
ram with other applications on your Mac.
It just means that Docker can use up to 4 gig of memory and my computer and over here I have to click
Apply and restart.
Now that I've made that change and there's lots of other options you can look at here and read about
and actually see the help on inside the menu.
But for now let's just get into the command line.
So I'm going to bring up the terminal.
It's actually called terminal it's the Mac application and if you're familiar with this you may have
all your own set up.
If you're not familiar with terminal it is like power shell or command prompt and windows and like a
standard Linux shell and Linux and it actually is by default.
Runs bash which is just a standard shell very common and you can see that it's here the top and I can
actually run Docker version here.
To know that my doctor is running.
And which version of Docker I've got running here so you can see the client and the server are both
listed and we'll talk in the next lecture after the section about what all that stuff means but this
basically getting this back does mean that your doctor is working and you can talk to it.
So now that we know that Docker is installed and working correctly let's clone my repository for this
course and if you're used to get and get hub then this is a super easy part that you probably have done.
Lots of times in your career.
Probably just this week and it's no big deal.
But if you're new to get or specifically to get hub then let me just drop you through a couple of quick
steps on the easiest way to get my repository downloaded.
So in a previous lecture in this section I gave you some information about where to find my repository
and the link to it.
It's a good dot com slash Bret Fisher slash you to me dasht auger Dasch mastery.
That's a lot to type.
So check out the previous lecture on cloning the class repository and that'll get you to this directory
and write in here is basically you can actually view it on the web but we need the whole thing on our
local computer so you would normally on get hub come over here to the clone and download area and I
don't recommend you download the zip.
The reason is is that this course is fluid right.
Tucker is always changing they're always updating and so this course will be as well and you actually
notice even on this page on this it like something changed.
Less than a month ago something changed two months ago so things are fluid and if you download a zip
it's not easy to update it once you're in the course.
But if you open it in the desktop it'll actually open it in the get hub gooey and let you keep it in
sync.
Doing a get pull on occasion and get hub now has a new desktop and once you've downloaded installed
that you can actually jump back over my repository and use several different options.
You can click the open and desktop which will open it in the gooey for get hub or you can copy the link
and manually paste it into this gooey and then you can put it on your local machine.
The one important part here is that you want to make sure that you're putting it inside your user directories
so slash users slash Brett is my user directory on my Mac and I just have a default standard.
I put everything inside a code directory.
The settings for Doc are as we mentioned previously one to make sure that you have all the location
on your hard drive where you might put code that is going to be used inside a container.
I won't cover that all again but if you make sure that it's in your side your user directory then you're
good to go.
Once you've downloaded it I would probably do a get pull once a month or so while you're still working
on the course to make sure that you have all the latest fixes and updates as this course evolves.
And while we're on the topic of this terminal this terminal works great.
You can use it your whole career there are lots of people that's been all day long in this particular
terminal application.
But in this course you'll see me use one with a few more features known as i term to.
And you can find that at.
I turned to dot.
It's actually open source and free.
And I actually donate money to them because I use it so often.
And there's one gentleman that actually develops it and I really like it.
So from here you're going to click the download and install it just like you would every other Mac application
and you can see that I have it here running on the right and then I have the terminal actually running
on the left and I can do a version on this right side.
And really honestly the only thing that I have different on my I turn to versus the standard terminal
is I've customized it.
I've changed the colors.
I've changed the shell and the options in there.
You can actually find more out about that at Brett Fisher Dotcom's shell.
That'll come at the end of this lecture I'll mention that again so you know where to go find it.
But there's lots of little things and tweaks and stuff I do that you can go get.
And as a reminder none of that is required for this course.
You can use a default terminal and the default Selye just like this or the entire course and it'll work
just fine.
And the next little tip I want to give you is to check out a visual studio code.
So if you don't have a preferred editor you can check out visual studio code.
It's actually a free version of a code editor from Microsoft that's very similar to Adam from get help
if you ever use that.
But it actually comes out of a box with a lot more functionality.
And one of the nice things is it has a darker feature that you can actually download as an extension.
So you'll see that I have downloaded and installed it already.
And under this button on the left there's an extension's option and you can see that I have some basics
like a spell-checker.
The darker one which is actually really handy in this course it helps you with darker files and compose
files that you will learn about and it gives you syntax highlighting and you'll see that commonly throughout
this course and I actually have a few other ones in there four different languages and tools but really
just the doctor one is the one that I recommend for this course.
And so the last little thing we're going to go through is actually the command tab completion.
So I'm going to bring up a new tab and I'll give you the link in the end of this lecture and also in
the resources for this lecture.
But Docker has some great documentation on how to get the Basche completion weren't working and what
that really looks like is when I'm in a shell and we make this a little bigger for you and I start typing
a doc or come in Docker container I get if I hit tab I get the options of what I can type and it helps
me complete Docker commands so I can do something like this and hit tab again and I get a bunch of options.
So you can do this on your system too.
And all we can do that real quick simply by copying this after we do a few things and all the instructions
are here.
So the first thing is it says to use homebrew Well what is homebrew if you're not familiar with homebrew.
It's actually a another tool.
And this by the way again all optional.
You can download it from the homebrew Web site which is brewed at SH and what it is is a command line
tool that helps you install open source command line utilities with a one liner.
It's very similar to apt get on Linux power shell also has one on Windows but basically once you have
it installed you can just type Brue install something and it and it will go get that.
So in this case what they're saying is that you need to make sure you have the bash completion.
So let's go through that real quick.
So first install homebrew using this command line right here which I already have on my machine but
it will install the homebrew application and then from that terminal window meaning large for you you
can actually type Brou install Bash completion.
And when I do that it's actually going to download the bash completion and automatically set it up on
my machine.
Now I already have that installed.
So when I hit Enter it's actually going to just tell me that it's already there but for you it will
actually install the best completion and set it up so that you're good to go.
Yeah it says it's already installed when it clear my screen here.
And then the next step is to actually link these three resources into your terminals.
So I'm just going to copy and paste that.
And those three lines will make permanent links so that way when I type.
Now Doctor container run dash dash and hit tab you'll see that it gives me all the options again and
I can also start from the very beginning and just type Docker and hit tab twice to get all the options
here or I can type part of one and hit tab and automake and complete it for me.
So basically I'm hitting tab all the time.
Right.
And that's known as tab completion.
It works out of the box in a lot of Linux distributions but that's how you get it set up on Docker.
I brought that into this lecture because a lot of people originally were asking me how to get that working
and the doctor's documentation is pretty good on getting that started.
OK.
To sum up this lecture Let's cover a few of the tips that I just talked about and also give you a couple
of extra ones before we get started.
So the command completion for your shell is totally optional but it will help you.
This link will actually be in the top left of your screen under the resources and then you can jump
over to the doctor documentation for that.
We talked about where to store your code for the samples and the work you're going to be doing in Dakar.
I recommend just sticking it inside slash users slash your user name on your Mac.
That's the easiest place to do it.
But if you do it somewhere else you have to change the settings.
And when you do that we're going to get into the bind mount thing later but just realize that you probably
shouldn't use the bind mounts for databases really just use it for software code.
That's really what it's meant for.
And it works the best with.
Next one is we didn't talk about this at all.
We will later in the course Docker machine allows you to create virtual machines on the fly with Docker
built into them and you can use that to create machines and manage them very easily either locally on
your Mac with something like virtual box or even on the Internet with Azure or digital ocean.
So do check that out if you're interested in that.
It's not required for this course but it is yet another way that you can use Docker and manage it pretty
quickly.
We talked about the code editor for this course.
I'm going to be using Visual Studio code a lot.
I will also sometimes use them but you can use whatever you want.
There is no requirement for anything specific.
It's really just text files.
We're gonna be editing and then we talked about I turned to as a potential replacement for terminal.
I know lots of people that are professionals that use Terminal all day long.
They're fine with it.
I just happen to like some of the features in term too.
And so hopefully you will too.
It's open source and it's great stuff.
And if you have any problems with your installation definitely check out the docs at doggers Web site.
That link is fantastic.
There is so much information there.
I personally recommend you just read it eventually because you'll learn more things about your doctor
install on your Mac and how the Mac works with it.
And lastly my specific shell set up that I'm going to be using in this course happens to be the I term
two plus not using the bash shell it's something called Oh My Zep's H.
And then I have a lot of other things.
I change the colors.
I have a little whale emoji in there.
I do lots of stuff right but that's not going to distract you from the course like don't think that
you have to have all those things set up.
But I do get a lot of questions from people on how my cool little shell is set up and I do spend an
obsessive amount of time trying to figure that thing out and make it perfect.
So do check out if you're interested in any of those add ons.
Brett Fisher dot com slash shell I do list everything that I currently use in my shell setup in there
and someday I might make a full video on how to set each one of those up.
But for now it's really just a list of links and information about them OK.
I hope you got Docker from X set up the just the way you want it and it's working great.
If you have to use doc or tool box for the legacy option on Mac do check out the lecture on Docker tool
box for Windows.
I know it's not Mac obviously but the tool box works the same way on Windows and on Macs so that lecture
will actually teach you how to use the toolbox.
If you have to but if you don't have to highly recommend the Duggar for Mac get it all set up at the
terminal working and then jump to the next section to get started right now with Dr..