Before we expand our services to start running across a bunch of nodes and all of the services talking
to each other, let's go over a couple of new concepts that Swarm brings to the table.
The first one is a new networking driver called Overlay, and you really just create a network like you're
used to creating it,
docker network create, and you put in a --driver overlay.
What that's like is basically creating a Swarm-wide bridge network where the containers across
hosts on the same virtual network can access each other kind of like they're on a VLAN.
This is only for intra swarm communication.
The overlay driver doesn't play a huge amount in traffic coming inside, as it's trying to take a wholistic
swarm view of the network so that you're not constantly messing around with networking settings on individual
nodes.
You can also enable full network encryption using IPiece SEC where it'll actually set up IPSec tunnels
between all the different nodes of your swarm.
But it's off by default really just for performance reasons.
When you create your services, you can add them to no Overlay networks, or one or more Overlay networks.
It really depends on the design of your application.
You know, a lot of traditional designs would have the databases on a backend network and the Web servers
on a frontend network. Then maybe you would have an API between the two that would be on both networks,
or something like that.
And you can totally do that in Swarm.
Let's see this in action. What I want to do is I want to show you what it would be like if we deployed
the Drupal example from a previous assignment with the Postgres Database, as services, and then created
an Overlay network for them to talk to each other.
First we need to create a network, so docker network create, and this hasn't changed for Swarm
other than the fact that we're going to use a new driver.
I'm just going to call it mydrupal.
OK.
So, I'm going to do a docker network ls, and you'll see I've got a new overlay. The ingress one is there by default.
You'll also see a new one because a swarm, which is actually an outgoing network that we won't need to mess
with.
So, let's create our Postgres service...docker service create name...let's call it psql network.
We're going to connect it to mydrupal network.
There's actually tab completion on the network names.
Then remember I need to add in that environment variable for the Postgres password.
So we can connect to it later.
Then we're going to use the Postgres image. Looks good.
You'll notice here that we don't get the whole image downloading and all that, because services can't be
run in the foreground, because they have to go through the orchestrator and scheduler. So, we can do a
docker service ls, and we can see that one of one of them is running.
If we do a docker service ps psql, we can see that this is actually running on Node 1.
So I can do a docker container logs psql, and then I can see the logs of that.
Yep. Looks like it's running.
All right.
Let's create our other service so
I'll go ahead and just call it drupal.
We also need to attach to that same network. Then we want to publish the port 80:80 like we did with
a docker run command. And we'll use the Drupal image.
OK.
We can see that it's starting there.
There's a trick. You can actually use the watch command in Linux to watch. It'll
basically...what it does is it's rerunning a command over and over again. It's installed by default on
Ubuntu.
If you just put watch in front of the docker service ls, it will keep running it every two seconds
by default until...ah, see?
Now we have one by one.
All right, and then I'll just Control c out of that. We can do a docker service
ps drupal and see that drupal is actually running on Node 2.
We have the database running on Node 1.
We have the Drupal website running on Node 2.
So, how do they know how to talk to each other?
Well, using the service names.
If I paste in one of the IP addresses, it should come up on the Drupal install. And if I tell it the database
here, database name, we're just going to do the postgres again,
postgres, my password.
For the host, just like when we were with Compose, we made the service names in the Compose file,
here, we're going to use the service name that we created for the database server. So, that was
psql.
This screen is basically telling us that it's able to talk to the database across the nodes and
set up the system.
That's the great thing about Overlay is it really just acts like everything's on the same subnet.
All right.
So we don't need this anymore.
I'm going to finish up this example real quick just to show you the next cool thing about Swarm. OK.
Now, this site is running. But I have three nodes, so how do I know which node it's going to be on and
which port I need to make sure that my DNS points to when I create this website name?
In my case, I have three IP addresses, and I can copy all three of them and put all three of those
IP addresses in
and...oops...I got the wrong one there.
So, if you see, it appears like the website is running on all three nodes because I'm looking at
all three IP addresses.
But if I go over here and do this service ps drupal, I know it's only running node 2.
I can even do a docker service inspect, and see that indeed it's only got one IP address on that
overlay network...right here.
So, why is it responding on all three hosts?
That leads us to our next, new feature.