So that little bit of magic wasn't actually magic. It was the Routing Mesh. The Routing Mesh is
an incoming or ingress network that distributes packets for our service to the tasks for that service,
because we can have more than one task.
This actually spans all the nodes, and it's using Kernel primitives that have been around a while
actually called IPVS.
...
So we're not talking about some fancy new service. We're really just talking about the core features
of the Linux Kernel. What it's really doing here is it's load balancing across all the nodes and
listening on all the nodes for traffic.
There's a couple of ways we can talk about how this works.
The first example is from one container to another.
If our backend system, like say the databases, were increased to two replicas, the frontends talking
to the backends,
wouldn't actually talk directly to their IP address.
They would actually talk to something called a VIP, or a Virtual IP, that Swarm puts in front of all
services.
This is a private IP inside the virtual networking of Swarm, and it ensures that the load is distributed
amongst all the tasks for a service.
So if you can imagine if you had a worker role in your application, and it had 10 different containers,
you don't have to put a load balancer in front of that.
This does that for you.
When you're talking about traffic from one service inside your virtual network talking to another service
inside your virtual network.
And the second example of how the routing mesh works is external traffic coming into your swarm can
actually choose to hit any of the nodes in your swarm.
Any of the worker nodes are going to have that published port open and listening for that container's
traffic, and then it will reroute that traffic to the proper container based on its load balancing.
What this means is when you're deploying containers in a swarm, you're not supposed to have to care about
what server it's on because that might move, right?
If a container fails, and the task is recreated by the swarm, it might put that on a different node. And
you certainly don't want to have to change your firewall around or your DNS settings to make that container
work again.
The routing mesh solves a lot of those problems by allowing our Drupal website on port 80 to be
accessible from any node in the swarm. And in the background, it's taking those packets from that server
and then routing them to the container. If it's on a different node, in it'll route it over the virtual
networks.
If it's on the same node, it'll just reroute it to the port of that container.
And we didn't have to do anything to enable this.
This was all out of the box.
Let's see a diagram of how this might work.
If I created a newsform service, and I told it to have three replicas. And it created three tasks, with
three containers, on three nodes. Inside that overlay network, it's actually creating a virtual IP that's
mapped to the DNS name of the service, right? And the service, by default, the DNS name, is the name of the
service.
In this case, I created a service called my-web, and any other containers I have in my overlay
networks that need to talk to that service inside the swarm,
they only have to worry about using the my web DNS. The virtual IP properly load bounces the traffic
amongst all the tasks in that service.
This isn't actually DNS Round Robin. That's actually a slightly different configuration. We could
enable that if we wanted to. There's actually an option to use DNS Round Robin.
The benefits of VIPs over Round Robin is that a lot of times our DNS caches inside our apps prevent
us from properly distributing the load.
Rather than fight with our DNS clients in DNS configuration, we're just relying on the VIP, which is
kind of like what you would have if you bought a dedicated hardware load balancer.
In the second example, this is actually showing what it would be like with external traffic coming
in.
This is similar to what we just did with Drupal, where when I created those yellow boxes, by creating
one service, called my web, and it created two tasks, and applied them to two different nodes, each one of
those nodes has a built-in load balancer on the external IP address. For me, because I'm using DigitalOcean,
that IP address is the one that DigitalOcean gave me. When I use the -p and published
it on a port, in this example it's using port 80:80, any traffic that comes in to any of these three nodes
hits that load balancer on port 80:80. The load balancer decides which container should get the traffic
and whether or not that traffic is on the local node, or it needs to send the traffic over the
network to a different node.
Again, this actually all happens in the background without any special effort on our part.
All right. Let's see this Routing Mesh in action.
We already saw the example with Drupal and how it listens on all three nodes.
But what if we had multiple tasks that see that load balancer working.
If we do a docker service create,
what we're going to do is, we're going to use an Elasticsearch container. We're going to call it search and
give it three replicas. And want to publish it on port 9200, which is its default port.
In this case, we definitely want the :2 in there because it's the easiest version to deploy
right now. While that's creating,
I'll just mention that Elasticsearch is actually a search database that's accessible via a JSON web
API.
So it's really easy to hit with curl and give us good examples of how this works.
I do a docker service ps search, we can see that it's smartly created each task on a different node.
If I just do a curl on my localhost, on node one on port 9200 because I published that port,
I'll get back the Elasticsearch basic information. Part of that is it will actually create a random
name.
That's just a feature out of Elasticsearch.
If I curl this multiple times, you'll see on this one it's Patch, the Patch server, and then a third
time,
Jane Foster, and then it'll start repeating itself like such.
That's actually the virtual IP acting as a load balancer and distributing my load across the three
tasks.
A few more notes on the routing mesh. In 17.03, which is the release that I'm showing you this on, the
routing mesh and the load balancing are currently a stateless load balancer.
If you've ever dealt with State inside of maybe Amazon's classic load balancer, or other load balancer
technologies, you know what this is about.
This is basically saying that if you have to use session cookies on your application, or it expects a
consistent container to be talking to a consistent client, then you may need to add some other things
to help solve that problem.
Out of the box, every time you hit a service with multiple tasks, it's going to give you potentially
a different result.
Also, if you get into the details of this, it's actually a layer-3 load balancer, and that actually
operates at the IP and port layer.
It doesn't actually operate at the DNS layer.
If you've ever run multiple websites on the same port, on the same server, this isn't going to do that
yet.
You're still going to need another piece of the puzzle
on top of that if you're actually wanting to run multiple websites on the same port, on the same swarm.
Luckily, that's a pretty common request, and there's several options you can do to solve both of these
problems.
One of them is to use Nginx or HAProxy, which there are pretty good examples out there of containers
that will sit in front with your routing mesh, and actually act as a stateful load balancer or a layer
for load balancer, that can also do caching and lots of other things. If you need that, you might want
to check some of those out in the resources of this section.
I should also mention that if you were to pay for a subscription of Docker Enterprise edition, with
it comes something called UCP or Docker Data Center, which is a web interface. But I should mention that
Docker Enterprise edition, if you get a subscription to that for your swarm nodes, it actually comes with
a built-in layer for web proxy that allows you to just throw DNS names in the web config of your swarm
services and everything just works.