All right, now that we've learned all about Swarm scaling with overlayed networking and routing mesh,
I want you to actually go through the process of creating the assets, or the objects, that you need to
deploy in a Swarm scenario.
So we're no longer using the docker run command, but the networking and the volumes are kind of the
same but slightly different.
I want to give you a real-world scenario of a multi-tier app, and we're going to use Docker’s Distributed
Voting App.
It's actually called the Example Voting App.
You might have seen it in Docker keynotes, or in other labs or tutorials.
It's a pretty common, and I think, a great app, because it's got at least five roles to it, or different
containers that you need to deploy.
And they all serve a special function and they're actually doing stuff that actually works, actually does
what it's supposed to do.
And so you can play with it and it has very typical, distributed architecture components like the web
frontend and the worker backend,
and the key value in a database. I think it's really helpful to do. In this case, you're going to use
the directory swarm-app-1. It's actually in our course repo. In there is nothing but a readme and
an image. From that readme, you're going need to create the volume and a couple of networks and five
services that are needed for this app to fully function.
It may help you to try some of these commands locally, or actually write them in your text editor
and sort of compose them, because they are going to be a little complex, right. When you do that docker
service create, you’re going to have to connect it to a specific network, and open up ports, and call it
a specific name, and use a specific image. So, it might be easier to edit it locally and then just cut
and paste into your shell, wherever your Swarm is at.
But that's just me.
Everything is going to use Docker Hub images because in the production Swarm you don't want to be building.
That's not a process you want on your production Swarm, typically.
Usually, you want to do your building either through some automated online service like Docker Hub or
Docker Cloud, or somewhere in your CI/CD pipeline that's not eating resources on your production Swarm.
In this scenario, we can imagine that our images are being built elsewhere and stored on Docker Hub and
we just need to pull those down, whatever the latest versions are, into our Swarm.
And I'll just say this, like many things in Computer Science, this is one half science, one half art form.
Your commands could be in totally different orders, or have totally different option orders than mine.
You might call your networks different things.
That's fine.
At the end result is that the application works, that they're able to talk to each other in the proper
way, that you've got all the ports published and that you’ve got the data protected in a volume.
Let's take a quick look at what you're up against.
Imagine you're having to design the commands and the architecture for this.
And this is what the developer would give to you that wrote this app.
Well in this case, it's probably lots of developers that wrote this app, right?
Because we've actually got a web frontend that's in Python we've got a Web backend that's running
in Node.
We've got a worker process that's running in .NET and then we've got a Redis key value store and
a PostgreSQL database.
This is actually something I see more and more often, where different teams are writing different parts
of a solution, and they're able to just pick the language that they think is best for that scenario.
And in the world of containers, this kind of application really shines. Because our applications are
all segmented,
they can still technically run on the same machine but they're all protected from each other so that
you don't end up with Node conflicting with dependencies on Python or whatever.
You’ll also notice here the traffic flow, and the voting-app doesn't have it,
but it should have a little arrow coming in that this is where the users would be coming in on the voting-app
part.
And you can see that the voting-app actually has to push your votes for this application which, by the way, you’re
going to be voting for cats and dogs.
It'll be pushing that into Redis and then the worker will actually be checking the Redis system for anything
in the queue and then be pushing the results into Postgres which will then be shown on a WebSockets
backend that's actually live-updating as you're voting.
If we jump into the Directory real quick I've put some notes in here to help you along the way because
there's a few things that are a little different and new.
But, the services area would be kind of written like it was from someone who knew their application but
didn't know actually how to implement this in Docker. And that's a pretty common scenario.
You can see that in the services I've listed which image you need to deploy,
the actual name that you need to give it, because those are important.
These are images that are, unfortunately, hard coded for what names they are going to look for on the network.
Ideally, you'd want applications that you could configure on the fly for what they need to do for names,
but, in this case, vote is going to specifically look for a DNS record called redis. You can see that
there's actually two networks here. We have a frontend and a backend network. That's pretty typical
also of a larger application where you maybe want to protect your database on a backend network so
that the frontend user app doesn't have direct access to it.
And that's what we are showing here and you’ll notice that the worker actually is connected to two networks.
So when you use your create command, remember you're using docker service create not docker run.
So when you using your docker service create command you're going to need to specify the --network
twice, once for the frontend, and once for the backend.
Obviously, you know to create your networks first.
So some of that’s specified up here. And if you need the image again the architecture diagram is also in
here, just in case that helps conceptually with how you're going to deploy this.
And, of course, you're going to have the Docker documentation. You might need to use the --help on
the service create command that will give you all the various options that you might need.
You only are going to need three or four of those. If you get stuck with the commands themselves, you
might want to review the actual documentation, which I will put into the resources of this section.
But this particular document under Swarm actually goes into creating services and configuring services.
So, it's a little wordy, but it's got a lot of information in it that might help you if you get stuck
in here.
The next video I will actually run through this whole thing myself as if I was you.
Good luck and have some fun.