Okay,
so what I'm going to do is, I'm going to walk through each one of these services based on this architecture,
and I'm going to create this app on the fly. I'm actually going to type the commands in here in the readme,
because that seems like a logical place for me to do it. And then I'll cut and paste them into my
node.
If you remember, I have a 3-node Swarm over here. If I do a docker node ls,
you’ll see that I have three nodes here. They're all manager nodes.
I have no containers running, and no services, obviously. First thing, I know up at the top,
it talks about I need networks, and I need a volume.
So, probably can get the networks out of the way and I can probably wing that. I can type docker
network create d overlay. Remember that the overlay network is the only kind of network we can use
in a Swarm because overlay allows us to span across nodes, as if they're all on the local network.
And then I want to call it backend.
And then, I want to do the same exact thing, only call it frontend.
Now, there's nothing inherently special about these two networks.
We're just going to segment our different services into one or the other to help act like a little firewall
that gives separation for protection.
On this vote one,
I know I need to do a docker service create, and I’ve got to name it, so I might as well put name vote. And then
I’ve got to publish the port 80 to 80 in the container, and it's got to be on a specific network. So, network
frontend. I need two replicas.
So, replica two. And then, I might as well just copy and paste this name.
Now, I'm going to go ahead and create all of these before I actually deploy them.
I’m going to actually copy this one down here. This one is going to be called...it’s not going to be called vote,
it's going to be called redis.
You don't have to worry about publishing any ports on that.
It's going to be on the frontend network.
I want two replicas, and then, I’m going to call it redis three two is the image.
Down here, docker service create name worker, is going to be on two networks. I’ve got to do network
frontend and...whoops.
I’m typing what I'm saying...let’s see, network backend, and then only one replica.
…
Because one replica is default,
I don't actually have to specify replica and I don't specify any ports.
I think, that's all I need there. I just need to copy over the image.
Okay, docker service create name db network backend.
See, one replica.
Oh, I need to do this volume.
Here's the thing about the volume. The -v command is not compatible with docker services. Because, for various
reasons, services are going to be more complex than maybe your typical docker run.
And there were problems and limitations with the -v back in the day.
So, Docker has learned from that and improved the format. But it happens to be a little bit more verbose
and maybe a little bit more difficult to remember the format starting out.
It also happens to be not well documented yet in the Docker Documentation because it's less than
a year old as a command. So, we're going to just copy and paste this. If it doesn't make sense to you,
basically, it's this list of values that are all a part of a single mount command and the minimums are
a type, a source, and a target.
There's also other things you can add on, but these are the only three we need in this scenario.
And you can see my source is just a named volume because I don't have any slashes in it.
And if we had slashes it would have been a bind mount and we would have to had specified a different
type.
So down here, --mount type volume, source db data, target.
I think that's correct.
And then you can just, postgres 9.4.
And then the last one is the result app.
So, docker service create name result network backend.
Publish the port. We’re going to use 5001 to port 80 in the container.
I only can run one of them. By the way, the only reason we're running one of these is actually a little
known issue on this app, is that this is actually using WebSockets, and WebSockets are something that require
a persistent connection.
...
So, in the routing mesh, doesn't really do WebSockets well yet because it's going to keep switching you
back and forth between containers and that WebSocket needs to be to a specific container persistently.
So, with this app what we should have really, is a proxy in front of it but it's not in this app yet so
probably in a later version they'll update it and fix it so that we have a proxy.
That way it can be redundant
and sure you're getting to the right container. We’re going to
copy and paste this to the end. I just realized I'm missing the last value on these.
Okay, and then I’m going to start at the top and just copy and paste. It's already created the networks.
Yes, this needs to be replicas. Let me update that over here.
Replicas. Okay, we’re going to create the redis. There we go.
All right, created that one. Now, you'll notice, by the way, I get back a service ID but it doesn't mean that
the service is actually deployed correctly.
We'll look at that in a minute.
Let me get the rest of these in there.
All right.
Now that we have that, we should be able to do the rest of our commands over here. So, docker service ls shows
us all five of them. And you'll notice that the replica numbers match.
That's a good sign.
That means that one has been created successfully.
And if I wanted to dig in deeper, I could do a docker service ps on each one.
All right, so that one's been running 28 seconds.
redis has been running a minute. db is running 53 seconds. vote.
worker.
And you'll see here in the worker, that we have a failed task that shut down, and then one that's running.
That's been running for 47 seconds.
Okay, so, I actually know why this happened, but you may not know, so maybe we would have to do a logs.
Now this is on node2.
An experimental feature that you can enable through an optional config in Docker, is actually to
do the new experimental feature, docker service logs. Which actually pulls the logs from many different nodes.
Hopefully, it'll be released in the next version of Docker later this year.
But for now, it's experimental. So I had to enable it inside of the etc docker daemon log, or daemon.
json file. And, just so you know, this is how you would enable an experimental.
That's not a part of this.
That's just something I did, just so that I could show this off real quick.
You might be seeing this error and you’re thinking, I don't know why is that happening?
We can look at that log. So, we can do a docker service log worker...oops...logs worker.
And this is on, this particular, let’s see, these are two different...
You can see here this is one, and then the number changes. Actually, yeah.
This is all one right here.
It says no such device or address.
So, what this basically means is, I created a service that was looking for a DNS record that didn't
exist because I hadn't created the other service yet. And it did the thing it's supposed to do in
“Dockerland”, which is when it has an error like that, the app should crash because Docker can actually
restart and redeploy things properly until the apps don't crash. And as soon as I get all my services
launched, everything stopped crashing and everything now works.
And we can tell that by just going back and looking at the ps worker. We see that it's been running
successfully for three minutes.
So let's take a look at our app.
If I just pull up the IP address, I should get the dogs and cats.  I'm going to vote cats.
And then if I go to that same IP on port 5001, I should see the results app. That's
the app.
We now know that it's working because the only way that this can change is if this goes all the way
through when it gets caught up by the redis, and then processed by the worker, and then put in the database.
So we know that each of our app services are able to talk to each other. And we can look at the logs
if we wanted to.
But, that's the demo.