Now that you understand the basics of creating a multi-node swarm and creating overlay networks and
Docker services, we're going to cover the next really cool thing about Swarm, which is stacks. Not stacks of
pancakes, but stacks of services. In 1.13, Docker added this really great feature that adds another
layer of abstraction on top of stacks. Basically it's Compose files for production of Swarm. Now
stacks accept Compose files.
Inside there is what we would call a declarative definition, where we're stating this is what I want
the end result to be.
And it's the swarm's job to figure all that out. Now it's not just services; it's networks and volumes
as well.
And a little sneak peek.
It's actually going to include secrets, which we'll talk about in the next few lectures.
We get to use a new command, which is docker stack deploy to import this Compose file and run the command
that we put in it.
The stack manages all of this.
It doesn't need us to go and first create networks, or first create volumes, but we can totally do that.
We can use something called External in our Compose file to say hey, these are already things that exist
in my swarm. Go ahead and use those, don't bother creating them.
But usually you end up having your stacks just doing it all for you because it's easier that way.
We're going to get some new features in our Compose file, so we're going to start with the ones that
look very similar to what we had before. But we're going to get this new deployed key in there, or dictionary,
that allows us to specify the things that are specific to Swarm.
How many replicas do we want?
What do we want to do when we failover? How do we want to do rolling updates, and all those sorts of
things that we wouldn't care about on our local development machine.
But that comes at a price, which is, that we can't do the build command yet. That may be something
that will never happen in Swarm because the mindset here is that building shouldn't happen on your production
swarm. Building is something that your CI system should do.
Maybe Jenkins or something else like Codeship.
Once you built your images and put them in your repository, this stack will actually be the one
to pull down those images and deploy them with the deploy options.
The good news there, though, is that they actually get along.
On your local machine, Compose will actually ignore when you run the docker-compose command.
It will actually
ignore any of the deploy information. It will actually say 'hey, you've got deploy information in here.
I can't really use it so I'm going to ignore it.'
Likewise, when you're on Swarm and you're deploying a new stack or an update to a stack, it'll actually say
'hey, you've got build commands in here.
I don't do builds so I'm going to ignore them and keep going.'
The nice thing is you don't have to change your file. We'll see later how we can actually have
a single Compose file that does everything that we need it to do on the development side and on the
production deployment side.
It's pretty cool.
Finally, you don't actually need the Docker Compose CLI, the binary. That doesn't need to be in
your swarm. Because again compose, the actual command, is not a production tool.
It wasn't designed to be production.
It was designed to be a developer and sysadmin helper tool.
It's really best for local work on our machines.
The swarm, which is basically the Docker Engine. The Docker Engine now can accept Compose files using
that stack command. It reads the Compose files without needing Docker Compose anywhere on the server.
Let's review real quick when we look back at our services.
This is what our service would look like.
We would create a service...
let's say it's Nginx. And let's say we specified three replicas of it.
So, it would then go and create three tasks in the orchestrator, and those tasks would find certain servers,
or nodes, to put them on and they would create containers.
In the new stacks, we're talking about multiple services, one or more, right. You can have dozens of
services in there. In that single YAML file.
They act just like the services that we had before, only now we get to do volumes and overlay networks
in that Compose file. And that results
in what we would call a stack. A stack controls all those things.
And it actually will put its name properly on all the objects so that you can easily tell which ones
are related to which stack. It'll actually put labels in there as well, which we'll cover later, which is
more metadata for you to be able to determine what stack this particular thing came from.
So this is really great.
We now get to use a YAML file to actually do all those things we didn't want to have to type in the
service commands. Because the service commands were already kind of getting unwieldy and long. And then
we ended up making Bash scripts in order to run those commands, and then it just got tedious, right.
So, now that we've had Swarm around for eight months, we now get this stack feature that manages
those services.
Notice that the stack is only for one swarm.
Right? It can't do many swarms.
It's only going to be running on one swarm so that it can control all the nodes and deploy all these
services, networks and volumes.
I should say that this diagram can actually have one more thing in it, which is secrets, because the
stack can control those as well. We'll see that in a later lecture in this section. OK.
Let's look at the stacks and how they work.
I'm back in my 3-node swarm that we built earlier. I'm going to maximize the window on node1
because I don't really need the other two nodes.
At least I don't need their ssh command line.
We're going to use the voting app example we did in previous lectures for this section.
If you remember our design for that, it was five different services, and they all had dependencies on
each other.
And it ultimately gave us two different websites.
You went through and I'm sure you crafted the best services list with all the values and options that
it needed and it was perfect, right?
I'm here to tell you that now, that is no longer needed.
It was really important for us to use them and not everything is going to need a stack file.
But now I have a stack file.
Let's just take a peek at it real quick because you'll notice that it looks very much like a Compose
file because it is. The only real key thing you have to change as it has to be at least version 3 or
higher.
The latest version right now is version 3.1, but I'm sure that will change as it continues
to change and mature.
But you need version 3 in order to use stacks.
You'll notice that we have our redis, and our db, and our vote, and all these things that are probably
very similar to you from your own work. You're probably very familiar with those and the images they
need, and the ports they need open and all that.
But in this case, you'll notice deploy.
Deploy here is a new option. You'll see here that I was specifying how many replicas I want, which is how many
copies of that image that need to run at a time.
And what happens when I do an update.
So when I do an actual stack update, which will then do service updates.
How do I want that to roll out?
Right?
Do I want to all go down at the same time? Do I only want one at a time?
How much delay between them?
There's all sorts of options here.
We're just kind of scratching the surface, but you can see like I have a restart policy here that if
the container fails, automatically restart it.
You can see down here under the database,
I've actually had constraints put in to make sure that it's on a specific node.
We haven't talked really a lot about constraints yet, but there are ways for us to label objects, that
is, containers or images or really anything that we can create or destroy in Swarm or in Docker itself.
We can actually assign labels to any of those, including nodes, and a node that is a manager gets its
own labels.
This is very easy for us to do to just say, hey, this container has to run on a node that has this
particular role.
Great example there. As we scroll down we've got some parallelism options which we've seen before.
This delay option is pretty cool. If you have sort of a warm up time when you have containers that spin
up. Maybe they've started but they don't actually go live for maybe 60 seconds or something.
You can add in delays there. We'll actually look at those later during production
blue-green deployments. For now, you can see those are all pretty standard.
We've actually got even more options down here. You can actually see that I assign this a specific label.
I have a window and a max attempt for restart policy.
So if it tries to restart, and it continues to fail, it's not going to try more than three times.
Let's check it out.
All I've got to do is do a docker stack deploy -c for compose. So I'm going to use a Compose file.
Now I'm going to call it voteapp. And there we go. It didn't actually create everything and spin it up
that fast.
All it did was create those objects in the scheduler, which will then go through the process of creating
the services, which then create the tasks, which then create the containers.
It also has to create the networks as you'll see here. Remember we had the frontend and the backend
so it created those, as well as a default network, which that particular stack file that I had was using
a default network.
And then you'll see this option for visualizer which is a new one we did not use before.
We'll see that in a minute.
So let's take a look at the docker stack command a little more.
You'll see that we can deploy. We've done that already.
Then we have an
ls, a ps, an rm, and services.
So this command doesn't have a whole lot of features to it.
It's pretty simple because all of the functionality is really in the Compose file and really in the
objects it's creating.
Since we've done all that already, we can do things like ls, which just shows us all of our stacks.
It's a pretty basic command. We only have the one. Then if I do a ps, it actually shows me...oops
I've got to specify the name.
vote.
It's called voteapp.
Got to get that right.
OK.
Let me back that up so that you can see that a little better. Right there.
These are the actual tasks. Then you can see which node they're running on.
It's not actually the containers. It's actually the task that we're seeing here. Because if it was the
actual container, we would see a big, long name. Because if you remember, the services we created earlier, they
had these really long names
if we actually went and did it docker ps. Right? If I did a docker container
ls, or a docker ps, you get these really long names. And that's because they all get a GUID, because every
container's got to be uniquely named.
So that's how they guarantee that they're always unique and never collide.
Then the last one here is docker stack
services voteapp.
I like this one the best, actually, because it shows me my replicas.
It's kind of like doing a service
ls. It shows me how many replicas I have started so I know whether I've got the proper number of containers
already started. Then if I want to dive deeper, then I could do a docker stack
ps. We actually get the task names here and we see what nodes they're running on.
These two together actually give you a complete picture of how this entire application is running.
If I wanted to dive into the networking, I could do a docker network
ls just like we normally would do.
And you can see these three new overlay networks that were created for this app. And notice that the
app name is always at the beginning. The stack always precedes the name of the service.
So each stack will make sure that it's name is at the front.
And then let's go check it out.
Let me bring up my browser.
All right.
We can see them on port 5000.
I've got the voting site running.
I go to 5001.
I've got the results site so I can hit this and then see the result.
Then this new one we have is called a Visualizer.
It's on 8080. The Visualizer is actually a pretty neat tool for demonstration purposes.
That's actually made...all this is made by Docker, by the way, and these are all an open source repo that
you can see in the Resources section of this section.
So we've got different colors for each service.
The voteapp result is a green.
And then the redis is kind of a mustardy, and the vote is a pink. You can see there's two votes and there's two
redises.
It's pretty great to kind of show what happens as things move around the swarm.
If I actually went into my file and did a change.
Let's go to the voting app and let's say we want to change the replicas to five.
We could go and update the service. But that's kind of an AntiPattern. If we go in and type manually,
commands into the service, like docker service update,
that would mean that the next time I reapply this YAML file, it's going to overwrite those changes.
If you've ever done a cloud formation in AWS or any other configuration management, you know that
once you're using a config file like this to manage your infrastructure, you really want to always use
this file because it's going to be the source of truth.
So it probably, in production, would be some sort of file that you keep in a Git Repository that you have
version control on, and you control changes, and that way you can roll back changes.
In this case, I'm just going to change that file real quick, and we're going to run the same command, docker stack
deploy.
Notice we don't have an update. Because we're going to deploy to the same stack and it's going to recognize
that it's existing, and that we're going to update it based on these changes.
In order to update it, we've got to make sure we use the right name.
So it's voteapp. And then notice that it's saying updating services, but recognizes that it needs to change them.
Then if we go over to our visualizer, you can see that we've already got it.
We're just too slow today, aren't we.
We're not able to keep up with the swarm. We've got now five of these voting apps already running.
If they took a while to run and launch, we would actually see their states change in here as they came
online.
But it's a simple web app, so it's going to start up pretty quickly.
Okay.
That's stacks.
Now let's add on the secrets to our stacks.