All right, so now that we've gone through secrets and the features, and how it works and all that,
let's actually look at some practicals.
So, what I have here is, I've got our 3-node swarm set up like before.
I'm in a secrets
sample 1 directory that you'll see in the repo.
And, all I’ve got in there is one text file. And in that text file is just a simple username, not even actually
a password.
There's two ways we can actually create a secret inside of Swarm.
And one of them is to give it a file, and another one is to pass a value at the command line.
So, let's use the file first. docker secret create. And then I need to give it a name in the secret database.
And I'll call it psql user.
It doesn't have to be the same name as the file, obviously. But I'm just going to call it that.
And then... It spits back the ID, like it does for other objects. And lets create another one. Let’s actually
put the password in.
And this time we're actually going to echo it from the command line.
If you see what I'm doing, I'm actually typing out a password in the command line with echo, and echoing
it in into the creation command.
And notice the dash on the end, because that's telling the command to read from the standard input. Which
is what we're giving it with the echo command.
Now, I should say that both of these have drawbacks.
The first one, you're actually storing the password on the hard drive of the server on the host.
And we really wouldn't want to do that.
So, maybe you would be using the remote API from that local command line on your machine. And then pass
in the files that way.
And, in the second one, it's actually going into the history of our Bash file for our root user.
So then technically, if someone were able to get into root, they could actually get this password out.
When you're dealing with your own production systems, you'll need to look at various ways to get around
these two potential security concerns.
So, what we have here is...now, if I do a docker secrets ls, you can see that I have both of them in there.
Now, I can actually inspect them, but I'm not going to ever see the passwords or the actual secret.
So, let me just do the user.
It's not going to give us the information, right. Because if it was this easy to get the information it
wouldn't really be that secret.
Right?
So, the goal here, is that once you put the secret in the system, it's stored in the database. And the only
thing that's going to have access to the decrypted secrets are going to be the containers and services
we assign it to.
So let's do that now.
I'm going to create a service manually.
docker service create. I’ll call it psql. And we're going to map the secret to it. Basically, we're telling this
create command take this secret called this particular name...
I can also use the ID of the secret... and assign it to this service, so that all containers in this service
will see this secret.
All right.
And then put the user in there, and then I’ve got to do it again for password.
Okay.
So this maps the secrets to the service, so that they show up as files inside the container.
But it doesn't tell the postgres database that we're creating from this image
how to use those secrets.
So, usually, we need to do something with the configuration of the image.
And in this case, the official images from Docker Hub have settled on a standard where you use environment
variables. But, instead of passing in maybe something like postgres password, that would be hard to use
with a file.
We'd have to actually, like, cat out the file into the environment variable and that's a little bit of
a pain.
So, they have the standard where, if you specify a file...and this would be the path...so it would be run secrets,
and then the name, right? So psql pass, the name of the secret.
If I do that, that's actually in the startup of the image that will look for this environment variable
being filled out.
And if it is, it will then pull that file in, and store it in the environment variable. The actual contents
of that file.
This is this is a really easy way to consume these secrets that are in the files.
But it does mean that the images you use need to have this standard in place.
We can also do the same thing for the user.
...
Hopefully, this makes sense to you. When I create the service
it's going to do the typical thing it does when it issues a scheduling request for a new container.
It's going to create one Postgres database and it's going to pass it
the environment variables for the locations of those two secrets.
And then it's going to map, in a tempfs, it's actually going to map in what look like files.
But again, it's really just a RAM file system or a tmpfs.
Let's go see what we can see in there.
So, I do a docker service ps psql, and that should tell us what node it's running on.
Okay, it's running on this node.
Let's do an exec to see what we can see inside the container.
docker exec -it.
And then the specific container name for that service, and then bash.
All right.
Now we should be able to do an ls on run secrets, and you'll see we get the two files there.
And if I do a cat on psql user, we see the value. It worked.
And if we look at the logs of that psql, we actually know it works. Because if it didn’t...if it
didn't have those files, the actual database would keep recreating itself, and not be able to work because
it didn't have a password and a user name to create the database.
If you did docker service ps again, what you would see if it wasn't working correctly in a database
scenario, is the database would actually be failing. And it would keep restarting and you would see new
containers being created here.
So now that we've actually assigned it to there, we can actually use a docker service update to remove
the secret. So, docker service update --secret-rm.
There's also secret-add. But if I removed one of these secrets what would actually happen is, it
would redeploy the container. Because secrets are a part of the immutable design of services.
If anything in the container has to change for the service, the service will not go in and change something
inside the container. It will actually stop the container and redeploy a new one.
Obviously, that's not ideal for databases. So we're going to have to come up with a different plan for
how we would update database passwords.
And that's something we can talk about later.
For now, I just want you to know that you can remove them and add additional ones to an existing service.
It's just going to recreate the container when you do it.