...
Now that we've seen secrets with services, let's look at secrets with stacks. In this directory, I'm in
secrets sample two, and
in this directory, I have a Compose file and then two secrets stored in text files.
So it's the similar password and user names that we had in the previous lecture, but now we've defined
all this in a Compose file. We have several things different here.
The first thing is the version of your Compose file now has to be 3.1. In order to have secrets,
we have to be at the .1 release of 3.
So we needed to have 3 in order to use stacks, but to use stacks with secrets we need it to be 3.1 or
newer.
The second thing we'll notice is that down here at the bottom we have this root secrets key now and
it's where we define our secrets.
The two ways you can do secrets in a Compose file are either using a file for each secret, or have
the secrets pre-created.
Here we actually are just using files,
but what we could do is create those secrets on our own in some other method either through the CLI,
like you've seen, or maybe through the API directly. Then we would just instead of the file:
underneath it, it would just say external: and it would be the name of the secret inside the secrets
list.
We need to tell the Compose file about our secrets and where they are, and then we actually assign them
to the services that need them.
That's key because what we're really saying here is that only the container that wants our secret
gets our secret. If this was a complicated Compose file where we had multiple services, we may have different
secrets for different services.
We would first define all of them down the bottom and then we would assign them specifically at each
service.
I will say that this is actually considered the short form or the easy way to do the secrets under
a service.
There's actually a long form that allows you to define things like the permissions and the users that
are allowed to access that using standard Linux mode and user ID syntaxes.
So if you were running applications as a non-root user, you'd want to target these secrets to only that
user being able to access them.
But for simplicity's sake in this first example, we're just using the short form.
All I need to do is use that file in a standard stack deploy command. So, deploy docker-compose, and
we'll call this mydb. You'll see, just like before, it actually created the network first.
In this case, it actually created the secrets first and then created the service.
If I went and did a Docker secret look-up, then you'll see that the two are in there and it follows the
same naming convention as all other stack components, where it's always the stack name and then the name
of the object.
Just like in the previous lecture, if I jumped on the SQL server and actually looked for those files,
they would be there just like they were before; only now, they're managed inside our stack file.
The nice thing here is if I removed my stack, it also cleans up the secrets and gets rid of them. In the
previous example,
if we wanted to remove our secrets, we would have had to do a docker secret rm to actually remove each
one. Just as a last reminder,
in these examples we've been using text files on this server, and that we're talking about 3-node
swarm here.
But if you're in a production environment or really anything that's not on your local machine, you should
not be keeping the secrets in files or in the bash history file or any place that could possibly be
on that host.
That's kind of defeating the purpose of having the secrets in the first place. Whatever your process
is for getting secrets into the Swarm,
just know that you may need cleanup once you're done there so that you don't leave residual secrets
around that are easy for people to get.