Now that you've seen all the ways to create secrets in our stack, I'm going to give you a little
assignment on using secrets with a previous stack you've used.
You remember our friend Drupal, the compose file we used earlier, in compose assignment 2.
I want you to take that, and we're going to actually extend it and make it stack ready.
First, we're not going to build a custom image right now.
We're just going to use the default Drupal.
Then you would need to remove the build section from your compose file. Then I'd like you to
add the secret at the bottom, and when you do that, instead of using a file-based secret, put in external.
You can also look that up in the resources for this section.
It'll be the documentation on Docker's website all about secrets.
It'll show you the formatting in there of a compose file. So you use external, which means we actually
have to use the CLI to put that secret in. Then you're going to pass the password file,
that is the secret file, into postgres, using the environment variable.
So, you'll need to add that to the postgres section.
Then before we actually deploy the stack, you need to actually put the secret into the swarm.
This will be a case where we're not using a secret file. We're simply going to manually, as an operator,
add the secret to our swarm. Then in the stack file,
we're going to actually specify that, using the external at the bottom.
Once you've got it all edited the way you think it's correct and you're ready to test it, just copy it
into a new YAML file on your swarm node1. Try and do a stack deploy and see if it works.
You may not get it right the first time, and that's fine.
A lot of times I won't either.
I have to go back and revise it, and then try a deployment again. The errors that you'll get back
are usually pretty good at telling you what your problems are.
For me, it's usually that my YAML isn't formatted correctly or something silly like that.
If you have any issues, don't hesitate to just watch the video after this where I actually walk through
this assignment for you.
But I think your brain will work better if you try it yourself and get your mind working about how you
would actually solve this assignment yourself.
Good luck, and I'll see in the next lecture.