This is me walking through the assignment for the secrets compose file that we're going to put
in our swarm stack.
This file was left over from our previous assignment when we were dealing with Drupal.
That was under a compose assignment 2 directory.
Now I'm up at the top here, and I know we covered this previously but I didn't mention it in the slide,
is that this version needs to be 3.1.
Because a stack and swarm will not accept any secrets in a file unless it's at minimum 3.1
compose format.
The worst case, though, is if I left it at the 2 and I forgot, when I try to deploy my stack, it'll
just say, 'Sorry, cannot use compose version 2 file.' So, it'll just be pretty obvious that you need to change
it.
All right. The next one was, I needed to change this image. We're not going to build a custom image
on our stack because, remember, swarm doesn't build.
At least not in the current version.
We're going to...um...go back to the official Drupal, 8.2, because in production, we should always pin our versions.
I'm going to just get rid of this build here. Technically, in a stack,
I can leave the build command here, but it'll just ignore it.
I'll actually just tell us, 'Hey. Don't need this build.
I'm not going to use the build. I'm going to just pull down the image.
Thank you.'
We could just leave it, but I'm going to, for this example, not be distracted by that thing and just
delete that line. Then I'm going to go down here to the environment, and we need to change this because
we're no longer going to use an actual password. We're going to use the file.
Then this is so this postges is just like the previous lectures where we talked about how the official
images now have this option for the file to support secrets.
Now I just have to give it the location of the file instead of the actual secret itself.
So, run secrets and we're going to call this one psql pw.
And then I need to actually specify the secret.
So, down here, under secrets, I want to call it psql pw. Then it's going to be external, which means
that we're creating it on our own from the command line and that it's not the stack's responsibility to
create it.
This is actually just a boolean value.
So, I specify that as true.
Oh, and then I almost forgot. I go up here,
I've got to add the secrets. I have to list it.
All right.
That looks good to me.
We're going to copy this over to the server on node1 of our swarm, and then we'll give the stack
a shot.
OK.
I have copied over the compose file from my local machine, so we should be able to do a docker
stack deploy now, -c docker compose, and I'm going to call it drupal.
And that's what happens when you forget to create the secret first.
So, just like the instructions said, I'm going to create the secret, and I'm going to just put some random
characters in here.
docker secret create psql pw, pass in the value.
OK.
Now, I should be able to deploy the stack. There we go.
So, docker stack ps drupal.
I've got my postgres and my drupal.
So I should be able to bring up a browser and go to node1 8080, and there we go.
I can install a Drupal.
Let's actually test to see if that password worked.
This is not actually required, but I just want to test it anyway.
postgres...postgres...postgres...
Database password...
postgres...there it goes! It worked!
All right.
And we're done.