This section is going to be all about container image registries.
There's a lot to go through,
so, we're actually going to start with basically saying that you need an image registry in your plan.
It's not really an optional part of the container ecosystem. The way that Docker and other tools are
designed is that they need a place, off your servers and off of your developer workstations, to actually
store your images.
Technically, they can be zip files and you can export and import them but that's really an arduous
situation.
So you really want to plan for a registry, whether it's on the internet or a private one.
We're going to actually go through some things and different lectures here where we talk about the
details of Docker Hub and some of the auto-build options there.
We're going to focus on the Docker Store for a lecture and how that's actually different than Hub.
And then the Docker Cloud option, which is actually also different than Hub, but also an add-on to the
Docker tool set,
and maybe could help you make it easier to deploy servers and your stuff into the cloud.
We also have the new Swarms feature now in Docker Cloud that Ill have a specific lecture on.
And then, you're going to learn how to build your own registry and deploy it on either your local machine
or on a Docker Swarm to use as a private registry.
It's actually open-source. And then we'll mention some of the third-party registry options in case you
don't want to use Docker Hub or the open-source Docker registry.
In this lecture we're going to cover some of the advanced topics of Docker Hub.
Now, it is the most popular image registry in the world for containers, but it's not the only one.
Let's just see what it does
in addition to what we've already discussed so far. In summary, Hub is a registry, but it also has image building
in it.
That's not normally a part of,
for example, the open-source registry and so it does have a little bit of extra stuff in it that allows
you to build images on the fly.
We're going to jump into some of those features here.
And then, also talk about linking your GitHub and BitBucket accounts to Hub and checking out some of
the auto-build features for building your images based on the commits.
And then, we're going to show some features around chaining image building together, so that you can make
it easier to make sure your images are always up to date.
We've already covered a little bit about Docker Hub
when we first learned about images earlier in this course. But, I wanted to go through some of the other
features that maybe we haven't discussed, and then compare that to the Docker Store, and then talk about
what Docker Cloud might do for us before we actually get into other registry options for ourselves.
Obviously, Docker Hub is a registry.
It's what we've been talking about this whole course.
It's how we pull all of our images, and it is the default registry for Docker. But, it's not the only one
by far.
Let's talk about what it can do besides what we've already done.
We can see that I have repositories here, obviously. You can tell that I actually have at least one private
one here. The private ones,
you get one free, and the rest you have to pay for.
You set up a billing account like normal and you pay for that. When you create repositories, and on
each one of your images, whether they're public or private, you can choose to give permissions to people.
This is what my view would look like for a repository that I own.
This happens to be a public one.
If I went into Settings, you can see that I can switch back and forth between making it private and
public.
I can delete it. I can create webhooks, and the webhooks are really handy for when your images are built
and pushed into Docker Hub.
You can have it send a webhook to some other service, like Jenkins or Codeship, or Travis CI, or something
like that, to have automated builds continue down the lines.
Those webhooks are there to help you automate the process of getting your code all the way from
something like Git or GitHub to Docker and all the way to your servers where you want to run them. The
Collaborators is the permissions area where you can set permissions for other people to do things with
your image.
And then we also have Organizations. So, you have your own permissions for your own repositories and then
you can give others permissions to your repositories. But, if you want to create organizations you can
do that as well.
They're totally free.
For example, underneath this organization, I can see all of their repos. And then, because I have the
permissions for each one, I can actually go in and change all their settings.
You can see that I can control team membership.
I can control billing like you would normally do for private images.
This is very much like GitHub, if you've used GitHub at all, or if you've ever paid for anything on GitHub.
It's very similar where everything that's open-source is free and then anything you want to be private
you have to pay for in-group plans. And the Organizations work the same way as GitHub.
There's not a whole lot else to it.
I just want to show you a few key things that you need to know if you want to start using it.
One is, if you're using a GitHub or BitBucket to store your code, don't click this button to create your
repository.
Also, don't do a Docker push before creating it first, because what you really want to do is go up here
to create and create automated build. The automated build allows Docker Hub to create this CI path
that will automatically build your image based on code commits.
This is like the reverse webhook.
The webhooks we just looked at a while ago are for Docker Hub to notify something else that it's finished
with an image.
But this process allows Docker Hub to be notified when something else happens.
I always set it up for auto-building my own repositories.
In this case, for instance, I just chose a repository I have access to and GitHub.
And then, I give it a short description and it allows me to create a repository.
But, in this case, it knows it's coming from GitHub.
Anytime there's a commit based on certain requirements, or certain branches, it will actually build
my image on the fly.
Then I get a nice little e-mail saying it's successful or not.
That's why you see on a lot of images that they're automated builds.
That's just one indication of quality because it shows that this image is likely always up to date
with wherever the source code is. You'll see here, like the Jekyll server that we used previously
in this course, that I have some of these automated options here that I didn't have in the previous repository
that wasn't set up for automation.
So here I have build details, build settings. You can see that each time it's built it's successful
in the history. And then, in the build settings, I can choose which branches I want to build. Something
I highly recommend is that, down here under repository links,
if you are building images on Docker Hub, and you're using a from statement that you're pulling from
some other image, then you want to set up repository links here, so that any time that software changes
your image gets rebuilt.
And that's a big deal because, over time your, image is going to have dependencies on it, and it's going
to need to update when those get updated themselves,
maybe based on security requirements or new bug fixes. And so, on mine, because it's running Ruby and Jekyll
inside my image, and it's from statement in the Docker file is actually the Jekyll,
I put those here so that any time those images get rebuilt, mine will then get rebuilt.
If you also want to create a build trigger...a build trigger is another inbound way for you to automatically
have an image be built, and maybe you have some other software that's not GitHub that you want to kick
off builds whenever something happens.
So you can create those unique post URLs there.