So what about the store? And what makes it different from Hub?
Docker Hub has been around for years, and is the place where we've been going throughout this course.
The Docker Store was released in the summer of 2016.
At first, it didn't have a whole lot for us to care about.
Since then, it's been continually evolving to be the place where we get more and more of this stuff.
As of today, in spring of 2017, I can tell you that the Docker Store is really for two things.
One, is for actual Docker software.
They've moved all their downloads here.
There's so many editions of Docker now with all the different cloud options and downloads that
we have for our local installations.
Any time you want to download Docker it forwards you to here.
And secondly, it's giving you a higher level of assurance about software from third parties. That software
might be images from Microsoft, or that might be software that's a add-on to Docker or a plugin.
Let's see some examples.
These are going to be listed images that are placed here by the creators. In this case we're seeing
Microsoft images, and with the little checkbox, they’re Docker certified.
This just indicates that Docker and Microsoft have worked together on this image to ensure that it
meets all Docker best practices and that it's truly from Microsoft and not someone pretending to be them
on Docker Hub.
What you won't see on the store is ten different versions of .NET from ten different people that
have all built it themselves the way they like it.
If I had to tell someone in an elevator pitch the difference between the Docker Store today and Docker
Hub, I would say Docker Hub is like the GitHub of images and that Docker Store is like an app store
for images. Or, maybe more specifically, the Apple Store for images, because the only way that something
gets here is when they partner and work with Docker to get their official software into the store. Over
time,
I believe what we're going to see is the things here that you could pay for, which is those things that
aren't necessarily open-source but maybe some more closed-sourced products from companies. You'll be
able to use the store to pay for subscriptions of those.
And you can start to see some of that happening today.
For instance, if we scroll down and we saw this Microservice Firewall from Polyverse, it's $50 a month
for you to have access to this image.
So, I guess the word store makes sense here, because it's essentially the place we could potentially pay
for images. But that's all I'm really going to go into on the Store.
You can check it out on your own. For this course,
we're going to spend all of our time in Docker Hub.