Okay.
Let's talk about Docker Cloud. Docker Cloud used to be called Tutum. Then, a few years back, Docker bought
them and converted it into Docker Cloud.
And they've been adding new features ever since. As a high level, Docker Cloud does two main things.
It is not a cloud hoster.
It is simply, on one side of it,
a web based orchestration system for your swarms and your Docker clusters. For those that already have
an Amazon, or an AWS, or Digital Ocean account and maybe don't want to use the CLI to deploy apps
or manage their servers,
they can use Docker Cloud to do that.
You'll see on the left here where I can create stacks and services and containers like we've been talking
about.
And then I can actually go down to nodes and provision them, including a simple little form that allows
me to create new nodes, which are basically servers on cloud hosters. And you can see I've enabled Digital
Ocean and Azure.
This would basically save me a few steps if I was wanting to deploy some infrastructure. And then, once
my infrastructure is created into the clusters, I can just copy and paste stack files in, and away we
go.
There's a new beta feature that came out this spring that allows us to use the latest 113 Swarm Modes
in here as well.
And the bonus of that, if you're on Windows or Mac, is that if you add or create swarms in here they will
actually show up in the GUI on your Mac or your Windows machine. And you'll be able to launch the Docker
CLI against that swarm.
So that's one side of cloud.
The other side is the build area.
Earlier, we looked at Docker Hub and how you could do automated builds of your images with Ducker Hub
and include web hooks maybe from GitHub. But in Docker Cloud you can pay to have more of those features,
including running tests and doing more customization, such as having those images automatically deployed
to your servers that are linked to Docker Cloud.
This has become its own continuous integration platform where it's a one stop shop for building and
testing your images and then deploying them to your servers.
If I opened up one of my own images, we see that under builds I can configure automated builds.
And, lastly, one of the coolest things that Docker Cloud can do for you, is if you had your own private
images that you actually wanted to security scan for any known vulnerabilities, you can do that here.
It's a paid service and I would go into one of these and set it up, and then pay for it through the Docker
Cloud subscription.
But you'll notice that that actually already is taking place on the official images.
If I went to an official image, like Nginx, and then over to its tags, youll notice that theres
there's this vulnerabilities
graphic on the right here.
And, as I scroll down, typically each version is different in the vulnerability section.
If you wanted, you can actually dive down into that image and find out exactly what layer the security
vulnerabilities appeared in.
And then, also what those actual vulnerabilities are.
The list of vulnerabilities you're seeing here are actually produced by the CVE, which stands for
common vulnerabilities and exposures, and is actually run by the U.S. Department of Homeland Security,
underneath the US-CERT program.
It's been around for years, if not decades.
It's how we publicly track vulnerabilities in software today.
It's not specific to Docker. It's just Docker linking their scanning engine that goes through each one
of these updates to these official public images, and comparing the binaries and libraries in those
images to the open CVE database.
What's nice here is you can go through the list and click on each one and actually find out what's going
on and the status of it.
Usually, when I show people this for the first time, they think, holy cow look at all those vulnerabilities!
Well, this is the state of software today.
Sometimes this red line is just one or two.
Sometimes this red line is a lot. But, I wouldn't necessarily say don't use software with this red line.
I would say that every piece of software I've ever seen in Docker Hub has something red or orange, and
that's not indicative of the quality of the software. That's just kind of the reality of the world that
we're living in today, where vulnerabilities are found every day. And all of the official repositories
here are kept up to date within days of any fixes found.
What you would see here, in this case, is if any of these vulnerabilities in this list were fixed upstream,
then this image would be updated and rebuilt.
And this little marker would go down a little bit.
I encourage you to poke around some of your own images that you might be using
and check out their security issues. Because I do find this stuff rather interesting to just understand
how complex software today has gotten.
That's it for my demos of Docker Cloud and I encourage you to go there and try it out.
You can actually create one node and deploy an app for free and it will give you credits under the cloud
settings for the different cloud providers so that you can actually play around and learn how to use
it without having to pay for anything for maybe the first few weeks or a month.