Docker Registry. We've previously discussed how it can be a registry that you store privately on your
network.
It's actually part of the docker slash distribution GitHub repo.
If you went looking for Registry, just so you know, there's an old version of Registry in GitHub
that is legacy. It'll clearly say that. The current V2 Registry that we're all using was rewritten in
Go and can be found in the Distribution code repository but you probably won't use it from GitHub,
you'll probably use it from Docker Hub. Docker has a pre-built official image for Registry,
so it's as simple as docker pull registry. I would say that it's pretty much the defacto back end
registry for storing your containers privately.
It is pretty bare bones.
There's no web GUI.
It's definitely not like a Docker Hub or other third party service. Out of the box,
it does support certificates and basic authentication, but they're not enabled by default and the authentication
is actually everything or none.
It's not RBAC or role-based access control.
It's more like an Apache htaccess where, if you have a username and password that you get through, you
have read/write access to everything.
It's probably only useful in small teams without some sort of tool on top of it to make it more enterprise-y
and scalable.
But at its core, it's really just a web API and a storage system to handle all of these large images
we're going to be dealing with.
The nice thing is it actually comes with a lot of built in storage drivers that allow you to put
the back end storage of it on S3 or Azure or Alibaba or Google Cloud. It's even got an OpenStack
Swift driver but we're just going to use the local which is default.
Basically, that just means using in the local file system in the image or on your host using volumes.
Real quick, before we get to installing the registry, I wanted to bring your attention to a few of
the resource links in this section that you should check out.
The first one is a basic set up with TLS so that you won't have to enable the insecure registry
option because, obviously, TLS is a good thing.
The second is a reference article from Docker around a garbage collection.
The thing about a registry is when you start using it in the real world, it really starts to take
up a lot of data and, especially if you're pushing images over and over, it can really start to eat up
disk space.
So you need to pay a little bit of attention to your decision around your storage driver and, as
well,
this article on garbage collection which will try to clean up old things and keep your storage in check.
Lastly, a really cool option is the registry mirror.
If you're deploying to production and one of your concerns is that you don't want to depend on the
Hub for a lot of your base images, then what you can do as a feature in Registry is to enable a proxy
mode and then you tell your Doctor daemons to use the proxy and what it will do is it will cache any
Hub images inside that registry. Which is pretty great if you're wanting to make sure that you can optimize
your bandwidth in case you've maybe got dozens or hundreds of servers, you definitely don't want to be
downloading the Ubuntu image on every single machine from the Hub.
Right?
So you could have this proxy much more closer to your metal, and then it also would provide some failover
in case the Hub would have issues.
You can still get your copies of the images locally.