...
Now we're going to start the actual registry. We've been talking about it for a while,
so let's actually do something with it.
The registry is actually really just an HTTPS server like we've talked about.
It runs on port 5000 by default.
What we're going to do is we're going to start it and then we're going to re-tag an existing image
that we have, that we actually got from Docker Hub. That's how you actually change where the registry,
which registry is going to be used rather, is you're actually going to re-tag existing images. Then
we're going to remove that image from our local cache and we're going to pull it down from the registry
after we pushed it up there. Then we're going to actually stop and recreate the registry to show how
you can change the storage.
In our case, we're just going to use local storage,
but there are lots of storage options that we'll talk about. I want to make a real quick note on
the registry and how it prefers TLS. Out of the box, Docker will not talk to any registry unless
it's running proper HTTPS security.
Right?
It wants to make sure that your authentication is encrypted and that anything else that's passed is
trusted.
So we call this Secure by Default.
Right? You've probably heard that before. It actually won't talk with the registry we're going to create
unless we're creating it on the local hosts, which we are.
That's how we're going to do it, is just running on our local host.
So that's easy.
We don't actually have to worry about TLS just to test this thing out of the box because, like most
websites, registry doesn't come with TLS built in.
You have to usually create your own certificate.
But, if you're going to do self-signed certificates for your registry or maybe you're going to run it
remotely without
TLS, which I don't encourage you to do but in case you need to, there's actually an insecure-registry
option that you would have to enable in the engine.
We're not going to cover that here.
But just to know, that in production, if you ever need to do a self-signed certificate, that you would
just need to enable that. You'll get a good error back from Docker, it'll say: "I can't talk to this registry
because I don't trust it." kind of thing,
if you try to do that.
Today, we're just going to run it with regular HTTP on port 5000.
Back to my local machine and do a docker container run -d -p 5000, and it defaults to 5000 in
the container,
and I'll just call it registry. Then we're using an image registry.
If I do a docker container ls, you'll see that it's running. In order to use it,
we actually use tags.
If you remember with our images with Docker Hub, we had to put them in the format of account name
and repository name but that's for Docker Hub. For any other registry,
we actually need to label it with the host in there as well.
I'm actually going to pull something called hello-world, because it's nice and small. When we run it,
it just spits out some text that basically validates that that container ran, perfect for this nice
little example. What I need to do in order to push it to my local registry is I need to give it another tag
that tells my daemon where it needs to send it.
We use docker tag and then the image I need to tag and then where I want to tag it to.
So 127.0.0.1:5000,
I have to put the port in there and then
hello-world.
This would be the equivalent of making my own official image at the root of my local registry.
If I do a docker image ls, you see the hello-world here has two tags and it's the same image ID because
all I did was give it another tag.
But then if I do a docker push, it won't actually push to Docker Hub, it will see that there is an IP
and port there and push up to my local registry.
Now let's remove our local copies so docker image remove and docker image.
OK.
Oh. Right.
Can't remove the image because we've got to get rid of that container first.
So docker container rm, and that's the container that ran hello-world,
now I can remove the image.
There we go.
OK so now if I do a docker image ls, I'm sure that I don't have it, right? I don't have that image.
Now I can do a docker pull from that same location.
There we go.
I pull down that image.
The first thing, if you're going to run your own registry for your own reasons,
the first thing you want to do is use a volume to store the data.
In this case, we could delete the registry and use a volume to do the same thing.
If I was in this directory where I'm registry-sample-1, I could do a docker container kill registry,
docker container
rm registry.
All right.
So we've cleaned up our registry container. Let's make it again docker container run d port 5000,
call it registry again. This time we're gonna give it a volume, and we're going to use the pwd trick
to give our current working directory,
and then I'm going to put a subdirectory in here of registry data. That needs to go to var lib registry.
The last part is we're using the registry image.
This is technically a new registry with a new database.
If you did an ll on the registry data, there wouldn't be anything there yet, but if I took the image
we just did a while ago and pulled it back down,
you'll see we have the hello-world still there.
If I do a docker push again, it should push it right back up there.
Now if I do an ll and the registry data directory, you'll see some information in there. I just
did a tree command
that may not be on your operating system but you don't actually have to run if you don't want. It's a common
Linux tool that would show me all the different paths here. You'll see that it actually breaks things
down into the data, or blobs, which is the actual binaries that are inside the image, then the
metadata around it, which is the manifest, and the tags and such. Everything is in their own SHA directories
because you've got multiple layers going on here.
It's not really particularly useful for us to dig around in there but it's interesting to see.
So there you go.
That's the basics of running a registry on your local machine.
Then next, we'll need to secure it with some TLS and then enable some authentication.
All right. That's the basics of running a Docker registry.
Here are the major commands that we ran in this lecture. You might want to pause here if you wanted
to write any down or make sure that yours are correct.
Now that you're done with this lecture, remember to clean up so you can start with a fresh slate
on the next lecture.