Now what about Docker Registry in a swarm?
It's not actually much different.
The nice thing is that we don't have to run a docker run command, we can actually use a docker service
command like we're used to or a stack file like we've talked about in a previous section. It's going
to work the same way as we did on the local host because we can actually just tell the swarm to talk
to itself for the registry.
So will use the same 127 address and we don't have to enable the insecure registry because that's already
allowed by the Docker Engine. The Routing Mesh basically allows all the nodes to talk to the registry
as if it's local,
right, because that's kind of the magic of the Routing Mesh.
I just want to remind you that this is a persistent data container.
It does store data that needs to last over time.
So you will have to deal in a real world production kind of scenario. You're going to have to deal with
a volume driver and how to deal, and basically make a decision around how you're going to store the
data.
But we won't do that here.
For this example with Swarm, I'm actually going to change it up a little bit and not use the three node cluster
that I had used in a previous section.
We're going to actually use Play With Docker this time. If you just go to play-with-docker.com,
we're going to actually prove that we're not a robot and then it's going to ask me some random
questions, it might ask you, it might not.
Then we're in.
Recently, the Play With Docker enabled a new feature that makes it even easier for us to set up a
test form and that's under the wrench object.
I guess that's a wrench. You see that there's options here that are basically templates for setting
up a swarm so instead of showing you this one set up like we've already done, I'm just going to set up
five managers, no workers, give it a second so it'll set all these up. Basically what we're going to
start with is a five node swarm. We're just going to run a registry real quick to show how it's pretty
much the same thing as before.
All right. Now I have five manager nodes and if I did docker node ls, You can just see that I have five
of them.
So yay. We have a swarm. Let's actually just run the registry but this time we're going to use the
service create
and call it registry.
We're going to publish it again like last time, port 5000,
and we're going to, the images registry.
There you go.
We can do a docker service ps registry and it says it's running. In Play With Docker,
we get this nice little button that shows up whenever we publish a web application.
It actually exposes the port and gives a nice little friendly URL that we can test that web app or
web endpoint.
But you know with Registry, at the root of it,
it is nothing, there's nothing that is returned other than a HTTP 200.
What we can do though is with any registry we can actually go and look at the catalog and that'll
return a simple JSON array.
You'll notice its repository is empty.
We could have done this in the previous lecture with it locally but let's just play with a little
bit here since we're in this easy solution with Play With Docker.
Let me do the same thing when I do a docker pull as before of the hello world. I'm now going
to do the tag remember again, so we're going to say tag hello world and then I'm going to rename it or
re-tag to a new repository 127.0.0.1 5000,
I'm going to do a docker push.
Let me zoom this in so it might be a little easier for us to see.
docker push.
Then we're going to do the 127.0.0.1
OK. Now it pushed that up to our repository. The way we can actually check, really quick, is
if you go to this other tab and I'll refresh, you'll notice that repositories now shows the name of the repo that is available.
As we add more to it this would actually expand the array and we would see all of them there.
At this point, I could just do as before, run that image, it would work just like we expected and scale
it up. To just prove that point,
I can do a docker pull nginx.
We can run a simple nginx web server,
docker tag nginx,
and then docker push,
push that back up to our registry.
Then you'll see here, that I have two now. I have two repositories there. Then
if I did a docker service create,
just like we do normally,
right,
we're going to do the nginx 80 80,
but this time I'm going to specify the image like so.
We're telling it we don't want to use the Docker Hub image,
right,
to start the service and we want to use this.
Now we're going to add in a couple of options.
I'm going to actually do replicas 5, so that one nginx will start on each node, and then we're
going to do a new option that started showing up in the 17.04 I believe, detach equals false and this will
allow us to actually see the command running in real time.
You'll see that it's preparing, which means it's basically downloading that image from the registry
to the nodes, and then it gets ready and then it's running.
There we go, we're done.
If I pull, you'll notice from the top, it's now showing the port 80 because it's a new service, and you'll
see that I have it here and it's working.
What's interesting about this is that when you're in a swarm, you cannot use an image that's only
on one node,
right?
A swarm has to be able to pull images on all nodes from some repository
in a registry that they can all reach. I didn't mention that in the swarm section, but it's an
important point because that means that you can't just build an image of your own on a local, like let's say
in this case manager1, and manager2 isn't going to be able to go over to manager1 and get it,
right?
They all have to do push and pulls from a central repository somewhere.
But because I ran the registry as a service here, they can all know how to access 127 zero zero one,
and then the routing mesh will actually steer them towards the correct container, wherever that registry
is running on one of the nodes, and then it'll pull that nginx image to all the nodes as they need
to be there.
...
If you did a docker service ps nginx, you'll see that there's one running on each node,
and you'll see that the image it's using is the one from our registry.
OK, so that's it for just showing off how Swarm is very similar with Docker Registry.
At the end we kind of mentioned, that new tidbit, that you need to make sure that your images that
you use in a swarm are just accessible in whatever registry they're going to be in.
They have to be accessible by all nodes. That that should be obvious, right, because the nodes can't
share images with each other. They actually all have to pull them from a registry
and so they all have to be able to reach it.
It just so happens that a routing mesh makes it much easier to run that.
Just as a last little ProTip, if you don't have to run your own registry, as cool it might be to
do so, just use one of the hosted ones on the Internet.
...
They're redundant.
They've got monitoring and all the proper stuff involved with managing the storage.
They're usually, especially if you're doing open source,
most of them are free.
If you're doing it for private reasons and need to store private images, most of them are very reasonable
cost, I mean very low cost to store your images.
So whether you use an AWS or Quay or Docker Hub or a lot of the options out there, I would say
try those first and only use your own registry if you really have some sort of, maybe, offline requirement
where it has to be available without the Internet, or if there is just some restriction of security that
you really can't use any hosted platform. Because it really just is one of those things where it's a utility
and it's great when you can just rely on someone else to solve that problem for you.
So I hope you play around with it and have some fun.
Now that you don't this lecture, remember to clean up so you can start with a fresh slate on the
next lecture.