All right. Volumes seem pretty simple up front, but there's actually a lot to it.
The first way you can tell a container that it needs to worry about a volume is in a Dockerfile.
Let's go check some of those out.
I'm just going to do what I do a lot.
I'm going to search for MySQL.
This is how I learned so much about Dockerfiles, and how to use them correctly, is the official repositories
have really sound defaults and best practices built into them.
When I go over here to MySQL one, I'm just going to click on the latest Dockerfile here. I
I bet you because it's a database, it's probably got a volume command in it.
There we go.
This is the default location of the MySQL databases. This image is programmed in a way to tell
Docker that when we start a new container from it, to actually create a new volume location and assign
it to this directory in the container. Which means any files that we put in there, in the container, will
outlive the container until we manually delete the volume.
And that's something we should point out here is that volumes need manual deletion.
You can't clean them up just by removing a container.
They're an extra step. That's just for insurance really, because the whole point of a volume command
is to say that this data is particularly important, at least much more important than the container itself.
If we do a docker pull on MySQL,
and then I do a docker image inspect on MySQL, we don't get to see the Dockerfile because the Docker
file isn't actually part of the image metadata, which you'll notice in this config area, that it specified
that volume there.
I can always tell that the config, that came from the Dockerfile when it was built, assigned a volume
to that path.
Let's run a container from it.
So docker container run -d --name mysql.
If you remember from earlier, the MySQL one is little special.
It now requires an environment variable
before it will work.
It's MYSQL_ALLOW_EMPTY_PASSWORD.
OK.
What you see is MySQL running. If we do a docker container
inspect mysql, we should see the same thing where it tells us in the config that there's a volume.
Here.
We can also see it up here under mounts. What this is, is this is actually the running container getting
its own unique location on the host, to store that data, and then it's in the background, mapped or mounted,
to that location in the container, so that the location in the container actually just thinks it's writing
to /var/lib/mysql.
In this case, we can see that the data is actually living in that location on the host. So let's
do a docker volume
ls, and we can see we have now one volume. Now we notice this has got that unique ID that we'll never
know what the heck that goes to,
Right?
So, let's do an inspect on that.
You don't have to type the whole thing out.
You can just type the first couple of characters and hit Tab to complete it. You'll get that similar
information about the volume itself.
If you're actually doing this on a Linux machine, you could navigate to that location on your hard
drive and see the data.
There will actually be some databases there.
If you're on a Mac or Windows, remember that Docker for Windows and Docker for Mac are actually doing
a little bit in the background that's hidden from us where it's actually creating a Linux VM.
So this data is technically inside that Linux VM. You're not going to be able to go to that path
on your Windows or Mac machine and see the data. It's actually inside that VM.
We'll see in a little bit, with mounted volumes, how we can get around that limitation as well.
By looking at this, you notice that it's not very user friendly in terms of telling us what's in it
or what this volume is assigned to.
We can see from the container's perspective what volume it's using, but we can't see from the volume perspective
what it's connected to.
Right?
If I were just to hit the Up Arrow and, let's see, create a mysql2.
That's now created another MySQL server running in the background.
If I do another docker volume ls, you'll see two of them.
You start to see the problem, right?
There's no real easy way here to tell one from the other.
If we just, to prove a point, do a docker container stop mysql, and a docker a container stop
mysql2.
We do a docker container ls, we'll not see any containers running. If we do an ls
-a, we get to see them all. And notice that they're stopped. And then we do a docker volume
ls, you notice we still have the two volumes.
If I do a docker container rm mysql, and then mysql2, because I can actually do both
of those in one command, it will remove both of my containers. If I now do a docker volume ls, my volumes
are still there. My data is still safe.
So, we've solved one problem.
The databases outlive the executable.
How do we make this a little more user friendly?
That's where named volumes come in and the ability for us to specify things on the docker run
command.
If I hit the Up Arrow a couple of times til I get to the docker container run, it doesn't really
matter which one you're going to run again.
In this case, we're going to actually throw in a -v command. A -v allows us to specify either
a new volume that we want to create for this container that's about to run, or it allows us two other
options.
One of them here is to create a named volume.
If I just did -v, and then the var lib mysql, that would do the same thing is what our volume
command in the Dockerfile did.
We don't really need to do that here. But what we can do is I can put a name in front of it
with a colon. That's known as a "named volume."
When I do that, and then do a docker volume ls, you'll see that my new container is using a new volume
and it's using a friendly name.
If we do a docker volume inspect on that mysql, you'll see that this is easier to use here.
If I deleted my container again,
and we have to put in a -f because it's still running, and then I run another one. And this time, I'll
give it a different name. And then we do another docker volume
ls, you'll see that it looks like we haven't created a new volume. It's still using the same volume.
Let's do a docker container inspect on the mysql3. Then what we'll see up here
is, yes, this is what was configured but what are we running?
This is our mounts up here.
We'll see here that not only is the name friendlier, but it actually changed the source location to
be a little friendlier as well.
For me, a little tip here is that when I am running for days or weeks at a time, a particular database,
in a particular container that I need to keep using over and over and I don't want a blank database
server, I'll end up creating my containers this way and naming them for the project so that I know what
that volume's for,
and that it needs to stick around.
One last thing here.
Why would you want to do docker volume create?
If we can create them from a docker container run command at runtime, and we can create them by specifying
them in the Dockerfile, there's only a few cases where you'd want to create it ahead of time. And you can
actually figure that out pretty quickly by using the help command.
Because here's the only way that we can actually specify a different driver.
Remember that plug-in stuff I'm going to talk about later?
Then any driver options that we want to use the -o on.
Then if we want to put labels on it, which we'll also talk about later in the production section.
Sometimes, in special cases, you do need to create the Docker volume ahead of time, but usually for
your local development purposes, just specifying it in a Dockerfile or at the run command is fine.