In this lecture, we're going to talk about bind mounting and persistent data in those mounts. The
requirements are really that you just know about container management and how to run containers.
Let's jump in. Let's talk about bind mounts. They're actually pretty cool.
When I first learned about them, it sort of gave me an aha of how I could use Docker easily for local
development.
Really, a bind mount is just a mapping of the host files, or directories, into a container file or
directory. You can do just that.
You can either specify a directory or just a single file. In the background,
it's basically just having the two locations point to the same physical locations on disk.
Again, this actually skips the UFS like the other volumes do so that it's not going to wipe out your
host location when you delete the container.
If there are any files in the container that you map the host files to, the host files win. It
doesn't actually delete the files in the container that it overwrote because it's not really overwriting
anything in the container.
It's just there while the bind mount exists.
The minute you don't need the bind mount any more and you re-run the container without it, you would
actually see the underlying data that was there before. Because bind mounts are usually host specific,
they need specific data to be on the hard drive of the host in order to work.
You can't specify them in a Dockerfile.
You have to use them at runtime when you use the docker container run command. You can see the format
here.
It's really the -v that we used before, only on the left side of the colon,
we're actually putting in a full path rather than just a name.
And the way the Docker actually can tell the difference between the named volume, like we did a while ago,
and the bind mount, is the bind mount starts with a forward slash.
On Windows, you'll notice that it's a two forward slashes and then the drive letter, and then your
path.
As long as you have the left colon and right sides, you can really map anything you want from the
host into the container, and you can also specify things like read-only.
Where this really comes to shine is with development and running services inside your container
that are accessing files you're using on your host or changing.
Let's do that with Nginx.
If you go to the root of our repository for this course, and then we go into the Dockerfile sample
2 directory. Now we were in here earlier.
If you remember, there's two files. This is for Nginx, right?
If we look at the Dockerfile real quick, it's pretty simple. It's just specifying a working directory
and then copying an index file into that directory.
There's no volumes here.
A bind mount doesn't require a volume to work, although one could certainly be there.
The host always wins, remember? So, when we're doing a docker container run, then we do a
-d...let's name it nginx.
Let's give it the port 8080 like before.
Then we're going to give it the volume this time. And I need to tell it my current working directory
is going to be actually mounted into that working directory in the container. Because my index file is
here in this folder,
I want it to be in the container so I can edit it here, and it is seen live in the container.
So it will make sense in a second.
Here's a quick little tip. Instead of me having to figure out my whole path and type the whole thing
in, you can use pwd here like so.
Which is a shell shortcut that says, 'print out the working directory and replace this command with that
path.'
Then we're just going to use the same working directory from the Dockerfile there, and then we're going to
specify the Nginx image.
What I'm going to do, real quick, is I'm actually going to open up another terminal window so we can
do two things at once.
You don't really need to do this.
Basically, we're just going to edit the file on our host, and then I'm going to be in the container and
see what's happening.
So just to make sure it's working,
let's go to localhost.
OK, so this isn't the default Nginx HTML file.
And we used the regular Nginx image.
We didn't actually use the custom one from this directory.
We just used a stock image. To prove that point, we can actually do that same, exact command again but
take out the -v, and I'll run it on port 8080 instead. And I'll call this one nginx2.
If I go over to my browser and go to localhost 8080, that's the default nginx index.html
file.
This one is the custom one that we have living in this directory.
So, already we can see that it mapped it correctly.
If I open up another tab here and get a command line in the container.
Then go to that directory.
You'll notice that we can actually see the Dockerfile because we map the whole directory.
If over on the left, if we actually made a new file and I can just use that Linux touch command here
to create a new file. Then over on the right...oops...just keep forgetting that...ls -al, and you'll
see that in your file.
Hopefully you understand what's going on here, that both these locations are the same location.
And if I echoed something into that testme file,
and then...
there you go.
Our nginx is able to see the changes because it's just a normal file path in the container,
and those files are on the host.
If I was to delete them in the container, they would be deleted on the host because it is the same
file.
This is when I usually get a developer to get mine thinking about all of their development environments
that they have that are this complicated setup. Maybe they're using Vagrant, or some other manual method
of setting up their perfect environment, and they can start to see how this could make that so much simpler.
Because I didn't have to do any complicated setup on my Mac, I just ran a container.
I used the -v command with the mount, and now my code, on my host, can be edited on my host.
And I really never need to go into the shell of the container.
Usually, you can just run the container and look at its logs to see if there's any errors while you're
coding.
Of course, this is a simple example with Nginx. Later on, we're actually going to have specific
examples of different development environments for local development and containers.