All right. Now that you've learned all about volumes and bind mounts, and why we need to worry about persistent
data, let's do something that's a real-world scenario, which is database upgrades.
Imagine a situation where you're running a particular version of a database.
Let's say postgres, and you're needing to update the patch version because maybe there's a security
fix, or a bug fix, or something.
Normally on a system, you would just update the software. You'd do a package management system update
or upgrade, and it would handle all the updates to the libraries and everything by itself.
But how do we do that in a container?
Because, if we're trying to follow the best practice of not updating applications in containers, but rather
replacing the container with a new version, how do we do that with the database?
What you're going to do for this assignment is you're going to use Docker Hub to get you some info around
updating the specific version of postgres. We're going to start with you specifically creating a
container using version 9.6.1, which is an older version. And you're going to need to create a named volume.
You're going to have to lean on Docker Hub's documentation for this, using the official postgres repository.
You'll need to go into the Dockerfile for that specific version and learn what the volume path
needs to be. Then you can name your volume whatever you want on the left side.
But remember that colon on the right side of it, that has to be the path where the actual databases are
going to be in the container.
Once you've got all that figured out and you started your container, you should start checking
the logs to see when it's finished creating the databases and all the startup stuff. Because the first
time you start a database container, typically it does a bunch of stuff in the background, like creating
the admin user, and a default database, and so on.
There will be a point where the logs will stop and then it'll just be running.
If you've done it correctly, you'll be able to do a docker volume ls and see the volume listed there,
with the name that you gave it, and you should be able to stop that container. Then you're going to create
a new container with a new version.
It's going to be a very similar command to the first one, only you specify a different version,
you'll also make sure you want to specify the samed name volume because it needs to be using the data that
you used in the first one.
Of course, make sure that you have the first one stopped because both of these can't access the same
data at the same time.
Once you've started it, then go ahead and check the logs again for that new container.
What you should see is that it only has a couple of lines of startup logs because it doesn't have
to do all the work of the initial startup.
That's kind of how you know it's using the same named volume
is that the second time it starts up, it may only have four or five log entries.
So this is a real-world scenario.
You'll do this if you ever run production databases or anything that you need to keep current.
Do note that most database systems don't do major upgrades automatically.
It usually requires a tool. With postgres or MySQL, there's a separate tool for each one of them
that you have to run.
This is really just about upgrading the patch versions or that last number which doesn't require
schema changes or any major updates to the data code itself.
Like before,
if you get stuck, no worries because this is a new thing and it may not be that clear in Docker Hub.
If you get stuck at some point and Docker Hub isn't helping you out,
just check the next lecture, which is me going through this same exercise as I would do it.
Good luck.