OK.
This is me going through the named volumes assignment for updating a database. I know it's supposed
to be postgres and I'm probably going to need some information from Docker Hub.
Let me switch over to that. OK.
It says I need to start with version 9.6.2.
No, I'm sorry. 9.6.1. I'm supposed to go to 9.6.2. Start with 9.6.1.
I don't see 9.6.1 in here, but I can actually find that over here hopefully in tags. I'm just going
to search the page for 9.6.1.
All right.
There we go.
Cool.
Now this is actually a different way
to look at what the Dockerfile is doing.
I could...it's got a volume path right here.
I'm going to assume that that's the same volume path for both.
Because they don't change that kind of thing
very often.
I going to call it 9.
So, OK. docker container run.
I don't have to worry about ports or anything.
We don't need ports for this.
I'm going to use a -d to put it in the background. Then I'm just going to name it psql. Then I'm going to call the
volume psql.
I'm going to paste in that volume to store the data. Then I need to call the container post...
the image...I need to type the image here.
9.6.1. K. Now, docker container logs
follow..I'm going to do the -f command so that it keeps watching as it runs.
I think it's actually done booting.
Database system is ready to accept connections.
OK.
I'm going to Control c out of that.
So that's good.
I'm going to do a docker container stop psql.
I going to hit the Up Arrow. I'm going to change this to a 2. I need to change the name to a 2, because
I can't have two with the same name.
I'm going to do a docker container
ps -a, I should see
two different versions. One that stopped a few minutes ago. I do a docker
volume
ls. I can see that I have one volume with that correct name.
If I do a docker container logs
on this one...
Yeah.
Short, very short logs there.
And database system is ready to accept connections.
I successfully updated.